<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.0 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="chapter-12" label="12">
    <title>Case Studies</title>
    <subtitle>Applying the Roadmap</subtitle>
    <info>
        <itermset>
            <indexterm zone="chapter-12">
                <primary>organizing system</primary>
                <secondary>case studies</secondary>
            </indexterm>
        </itermset>
        <author>
            <personname><firstname>Robert</firstname><othername>J.</othername><surname>Glushko</surname></personname>
        </author>
    </info>
    <bridgehead>Overview</bridgehead>
    <para audience="CORE">We now fulfill the promise of this book, with a set of case study examples
        that apply the concepts and phases of the roadmap. <phrase role="parenthetical">(The first
            four case studies appeared in the first print edition of the book. All the others have
            been contributed by students or other readers of the book and edited for
            consistency.——Ed.)</phrase></para>
    <sidebar xml:id="ch12-stats" userlevel="Editor" condition="epub3 print" role="statistics">
        <?dbhtml sidebar-width="60%"?>
        <?dbhtml float-type="right"?>
        <?dbfo sidebar-width="60%"?>
        <?dbfo float-type="inside"?>
        <informalfigure xml:id="inf-fig-ch12-stats">
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="Visualisations/ch11-stats.png" format="JPG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase role="ALT descriptive">This graphic describes the content breakdown of
                        the chapter. A wheel with colored segments depicts core content versus
                        disciplinary content in this chapter, and a bar chart illustrates the
                        disciplinary content distribution. In this chapter, Archives notes
                        predominate, followed closely by Computing, then Museums and Business, then
                        Law and LIS, followed by Philosophy, Web, CogSci, and Linguistics. There are
                        no IA notes in this chapter. (Not all sections in this chapter contribute to
                        the book's notes.) </phrase>
                </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
    </sidebar>
    <important role="editorial" xml:id="nav-ch11" condition="epub3">
        <?dbfo float-type="none"?>
        <title>Navigating This Chapter</title>
        <simplelist>
            <member><xref linkend="section-12.1"/></member>
            <member><xref linkend="section-12.2"/></member>
            <member><xref linkend="section-12.3"/></member>
            <member><xref linkend="section-12.4"/></member>
            <member><xref linkend="section-12.5"/></member>
            <member><xref linkend="section-12.6"/></member>
            <member><xref linkend="section-12.7"/></member>
            <member><xref linkend="section-12.8"/></member>
            <member><xref linkend="section-12.9"/></member>
            <member><xref linkend="section-12.10"/></member>
            <member><xref linkend="section-12.11"/></member>
            <member><xref linkend="section-12.12"/></member>
            <member><xref linkend="section-12.13"/></member>
            <member><xref linkend="section-12.14"/></member>
            <member><xref linkend="section-12.15"/></member>
            <member><xref linkend="section-12.16"/></member>
            <member><xref linkend="section-12.17"/></member>
            <member><xref linkend="section-12.18"/></member>
            <member><xref linkend="section-12.19"/></member>
        </simplelist>
    </important>
    <bridgehead>Case Study Template</bridgehead>
    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-bd2_5gp_qs">For the sake of consistency, we employ the
        questions posed in <xref linkend="chapter-2n"/> as a template for the case studies. We
        remind you of six groups of design decisions, itemizing the most important dimensions in
        each group:</para>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- Having trouble with this. Epub3 check is emitting five errors, corresponding to W5 list items. -->
    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-cd2_5gp_qs"><xref role="transclusion" linkend="list-W5"
            endterm="list-W5"/></para>
    <para xml:id="para-dd2_5gp_qs">As we discussed in <xref linkend="section-2n.7"/>, when location
        is a constraint, it will typically be identified as such in the other questions. As result,
        we will only examine <quote>Where?</quote> as distinct design dimension in cases where it is
        warranted.</para>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-12.1" label="12.1">
        <title>A Multi-generational Photo Collection</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-12.1" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>case studies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>photo collection</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Overview.</title>
            <para>Your grandfather has died, at age 91, and under his bed is <hardware>a suitcase
                    containing several photo albums with a few hundred photos</hardware>. Some of
                them have captions, but many do not. What do you do with them?</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.1-t3p_vpr_lr">Your first thought was to create a
            digital photo archive of Grandpa’s collection so that you and all your relatives could
            see them, and you would also want to generate accurate captions where none exist. Since
            you have an extensive digital photo collection of your own in a web-based application,
            perhaps you can combine the two collections to create a multi-generational photo
            organizing system.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.1-djp_vpr_lr">This project involves <phrase
                remap="action">digitization</phrase>, <phrase remap="action">archiving</phrase>,
            social media issues, and negotiations with and collecting information from other family
            members who might have different views about what to do.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>What is being organized?</title>
            <para>It is easy to find advice about how to digitize old photos, but there are more
                choices than you might think. What resolution and format should you use? Should you
                do the work yourself or send Grandpa’s precious photos to a service and take the
                risk that they might get lost? Should you do any restoration or enhancement of the
                photos as part of the digitization process?<footnote xml:id="endnote-566"
                    label="646" audience="CogSci">
                    <para audience="CogSci" xml:id="para-12.1-akp_vpr_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-566" audience="Markup">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>CogSci</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-566" userlevel="Professional">
                                    <primary>cognitive science</primary>
                                    <secondary>citations</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info><citation xml:id="cite_Ctein2010" linkend="Ctein2010">(Ctein
                            2010)</citation> and <citation xml:id="cite_Taylor2010"
                            linkend="Taylor2010">(Taylor 2010)</citation> are popular guides for
                        photo digitization and restoration.</para>
                </footnote></para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.1-gkp_vpr_lr">More fundamental design questions
            concern the scope and scale of the organizing system. If you are digitizing Grandpa’s
            photos and combining them with yours, you are skipping a generation. Should not you also
            include photos from your parents and the rest of Grandpa’s children? That generation has
            both printed photos and digital ones, but it is not as comfortable with computers as you
            are, and their digital photos are stored less systematically on a variety of
                <abbrev>CD-ROM</abbrev>, <abbrev>DVD</abbrev>s, flash memory sticks, and
                <abbrev>SD</abbrev> photo cards, making the digitizing and organizing work more
            complicated. Do these differences in storage media reflect an intentional arrangement
            that needs to be preserved? And what about that box full of Super 8 cartridges and
                <abbrev>VHS</abbrev> tapes with family videos on them, and the audio cassettes with
            recordings made at long-ago family gatherings? </para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.1-wkp_vpr_lr">A family history management system that
            includes many different resource types is a much bigger project than the one you
            contemplated when you first opened Grandpa’s suitcase. It is easier to consider using
            separate but related organizing systems for each media type, because there are many
            web-based applications you could use. In fact, there are far too many choices of web
            applications for you to consider. You might compare some for their functionality and
            usability, but given the long expected lifetime of your organizing system there are more
            critical considerations: whether the site is likely to last as long as your collection
            and, if it does not, how easily you can export your resources and resource
                descriptions.<footnote xml:id="endnote-567" label="647" audience="Web">
                <para audience="Web" xml:id="para-12.1-dlp_vpr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-567" audience="Markup">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Web</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-567">
                                <primary>Web</primary>
                                <secondary>photo storage</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>For example, <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://web.appstorm.net/roundups/media-roundups/top-20-photo-storage-and-sharing-sites/"
                            ><uri>http://web.appstorm.net/roundups/media-roundups/top-20-photo-storage-and-sharing-sites/</uri></link>
                    reviews 20 photo storage and sharing sites and <link
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://photo-book-review.toptenreviews.com/"
                            ><uri>http://photo-book-review.toptenreviews.com/</uri></link> compares
                    10 sites for creating printed albums from digital photos in case you want to
                        <quote>round trip</quote> from Grandpa’s photos and print photo books for
                    family members.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Why is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The overall goal of preserving Grandpa’s photos needs no justification, but is
                preservation the primary goal? Or, rather, is to enable access to the images for
                far-flung family members? Or is it to create a repository for family photos as they
                continue to be produced? Alternatively, is it less about the images themselves and
                perhaps more about collecting family history information contained in the photos,
                thus making the collection of metadata (accurate information about when and where
                the photo was taken, who is in it, etc.) most important?</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.1-rlp_vpr_lr">These decisions determine requirements
            for the interactions that the photo organizing system must support, but the repertoire
            of interactions is mostly determined by the choice of photo storage and sharing
            application. Some applications combine photo storage in a cloud-based repository tied to
            a very powerful set of digital photography tools, but this functionality comes with
            complexity that would overwhelm your less technology-savvy relatives. They would be
            happy just to be able to browse and search for photos.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How much is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Because you realize that a carefully designed set of categories and a controlled
                tagging vocabulary will enable precise browsing and search, you chose an application
                that supports grouping and tagging. But not everyone should be allowed to group or
                tag photos, and maybe some of the more distant relatives can view photos but not add
                any.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.1-cmp_vpr_lr">Will your categories and tags include
            all of those that Grandpa used when he arranged pictures in albums and made notes on the
            back of many of them? Do you want to allow annotations? Maybe this is a picture from a
            vacation; if you go back to the same place, do you want to create an association between
            the pictures?</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.1-kmp_vpr_lr">Do not forget to keep Grandpa’s original
            albums in a safe place, not under a bed somewhere.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>When is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Once you create your categories and tags, you can require people to use them when
                they add new photos to the collection. Perhaps the existing resource descriptions
                can be completed or enhanced as a collective activity at a family reunion. Do not
                put this off too long<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>the people who can identify Grandpa’s
                sister Gladys, her second husband, and his sister in an uncaptioned photo are
                getting on in years.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How or by whom is it being organized?</title>
            <para>You have taken on the role of the editor and curator, but you cannot do everything
                and having a group of people involved will probably result in more robust
                organizing. A group can also better handle sticky situations like what to do if
                people get divorced or have a falling out with other family members; do pictures
                taken of or by them get deleted?</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Other considerations.</title>
            <para>Maintenance of this collection for an indefinite time raises the important issue
                or a succession plan for the curator. If only one name is on the account and only
                that person knows the password, you run the risk of losing access to the photos if
                that person dies. One of Grandpa’s mistakes was dying without clearly specifying his
                intentions for his photo collection, so whatever you decide you should document
                carefully and include a continuity plan when you are no longer the curator.<footnote
                    xml:id="endnote-568" label="648" audience="Law">
                    <para audience="Law" xml:id="para-12.1-jnp_vpr_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-568" audience="Markup">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Law</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-568">
                                    <primary>law</primary>
                                    <secondary>digital afterlife</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info><citation xml:id="cite_Herbst2009" linkend="Herbst2009">(Herbst
                            2009)</citation> is a thoughtful legal primer on the novel property,
                        jurisdiction, and terms of service complexities in gaining access to
                        accounts of deceased people. A popular treatment about what has come to be
                        called the <quote>digital afterlife</quote> is <citation
                            xml:id="cite_Carroll2010" linkend="Carroll2010">(Carroll and Romano
                            2011)</citation>.</para>
                </footnote></para>
        </formalpara>
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-12.2" label="12.2">
        <title>Knowledge Management for a Small Consulting Firm</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-12.2" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>case studies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>knowledge management</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Overview.</title>
            <para>A senior professor who has done part-time consulting for many years is very
                pleased when his latest book becomes a best-seller and he is inundated with new
                consulting opportunities. He decides to take a two-year leave of absence from his
                university to start a small consulting firm with several of his current and former
                graduate students as his junior consulting partners.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.2-hrf_xpr_lr">An organizing system for knowledge
            management is required, but what gets designed will depend on the scoping decision. Is
            the goal of the system to support the consulting business, or also to support ongoing
            and future research projects that sooner or later will generate the consulting
            opportunities? </para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>What is being organized?</title>
            <para>The professor concludes that since his consulting is based on his research, he
                needs to include in the new knowledge management system his research articles and
                the raw and analyzed data that is discussed in the articles. These resources are
                already organized to a great extent according to the research project that led to
                their creation. These have been kept in the professor’s university office.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.2-lsf_xpr_lr">The professor also has a separate
            collection of consulting proposals, client reports, and presentations that he has made
            at client firms. Because of restrictive university rules about faculty consulting, the
            professor has always kept these resources in his home office rather than on
                campus.<footnote xml:id="endnote-569" label="649" audience="Law">
                <para audience="Law" xml:id="para-12.2-btf_xpr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-569" audience="Markup">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Law</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-569">
                                <primary>law</primary>
                                <secondary>consulting rules</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.spo.berkeley.edu/guide/consultquick.html"
                            ><uri>http://www.spo.berkeley.edu/guide/consultquick.html</uri></link>
                    is an example of such a policy. Indeed, it is because of rules like these that
                    the professor determined he needed to take a leave of absence from the
                    university.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.2-mtf_xpr_lr">In addition to these existing resource
            types, it will be necessary to create new ones that make systematic and explicit
            information that the professor has managed in an informal and largely tacit manner. This
            includes consulting inquiries, information about prospects, and information about
            specific people in client firms.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Why is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The professor has usually just done one consulting project at a time, very
                opportunistically. He has often turned down projects that involved more work than he
                could do himself. He now sees the opportunity to do much more consulting and to take
                on more significant projects if he can leverage his expertise in a more efficient
                way.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.2-q5f_xpr_lr">The professor can take on the
                <quote>rainmaker</quote> role to secure new consulting engagements and make the
            important decisions, and he is confident that he can train and support his new staff of
            current and former students to do much of the actual consulting work.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.2-evf_xpr_lr">The knowledge management system must
            enable everyone in the firm to access and contribute to project repositories that
            contain proposals, plans, work in progress, and project deliverables. Much of this work
            can be reused from one project to another, increasing the productivity of the firm and
            the quality of its deliverables.<footnote xml:id="endnote-570" label="650"
                audience="Business">
                <para audience="Business" xml:id="para-12.2-rvf_xpr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-570" audience="Markup">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Business</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-570">
                                <primary>value</primary>
                                <secondary>capture</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-570">
                                <primary>business</primary>
                                <secondary>value capture</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>For a high-level theoretical framework about capturing value from
                    knowledge assets see <citation xml:id="cite_Teece1998" linkend="Teece1998"
                        >(Teece 1998)</citation>; for a detailed case study see <citation
                        xml:id="cite_Goodwin2012" linkend="Goodwin2012">(Goodwin et al.
                        2012)</citation>.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.2-awf_xpr_lr">Just as it is essential that the
            professor’s knowledge is systematized and made available via a knowledge management
            system, so must the knowledge created by the new staff of consultants. The professor
            cannot expect that all of the students will work for him forever, so any knowledge that
            they acquire and create in the course of their work will be lost to the firm unless it
            is captured along with the professor’s.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.2-mwf_xpr_lr">The consulting firm probably will not
            have an indefinite lifetime. After his leave of absence, the professor might return to
            his university duties, perhaps on a part-time basis. The knowledge management system
            will enable him to leave the firm in someone else’s hands while enabling him to keep
            tabs on and possibly contribute to ongoing projects. Alternatively, if the firm is doing
            very well, perhaps the professor will resign his university position and take on the
            role of growing the firm. A larger consultancy might want to acquire the professor’s
            firm, and the firm’s valuation will in part be determined be the extent to which the
            firm’s capabilities and resources are documented in the knowledge management
            system.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How much is it being organized?</title>
            <para>A small firm has neither the money nor the people to invest in complex technology
                and a rigorous process for knowledge management, but appropriate technology is
                readily available and affordable. Decisions about organizing principles must be made
                that reflect the mix of consulting projects; resources might be organized in a
                shared file system by customer type, project type, the lead consultant, or all of
                these ways using a faceted classification approach.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.2-exf_xpr_lr">Standard document templates and style
            sheets for the resource types created by consultants can be integrated into word
            processors and spreadsheets. Contact and customer management functionality can be
            licensed as a hosted application.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.2-sxf_xpr_lr">Many small teams make good use of wikis
            for knowledge management because they are very flexible in the amount of structure they
                impose.<footnote xml:id="endnote-571" label="651" audience="Business">
                <para audience="Business" xml:id="para-12.2-zxf_xpr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-571" audience="Markup">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Business</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-571">
                                <primary>business</primary>
                                <secondary>Poole and Grudin</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><citation xml:id="cite_Poole2010" linkend="Poole2010">(Poole and Grudin
                        2010)</citation>.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>When is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The professor’s decision to take a leave of absence reflects his belief that
                getting the firm started quickly is essential if he is to capitalize on his recent
                bestselling book to generate consulting business. This makes managing the prospect
                pipeline and the proposal-writing process the highest priority targets for knowledge
                management.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.2-vyf_xpr_lr">Much of the other organizing work can
            emerge as adjuncts to consulting projects if some effort is made to coordinate the
            organizing across projects.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How or by whom is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Because many of the early organizing decisions have implications for the types of
                customers and projects that the firm can take on, only the professor is capable of
                making most of them. The principal goal of the knowledge management system is to
                enable the professor to delegate work to his consulting staff, so he needs to enlist
                them in the design of the organizing system to ensure it is effective.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Other considerations.</title>
            <para>As the consulting firm grows, it is inevitable that some consultants will be
                better than others at creating and using knowledge to create customer value, and
                they will expect to be compensated accordingly. It is essential for the ongoing
                success of the firm not to let this create disincentives for knowledge capture and
                sharing between consultants. The solution is to develop a company culture that
                promotes and rewards them.<footnote xml:id="endnote-572" label="652"
                    audience="Business">
                    <para audience="Business" xml:id="para-12.2-b1g_xpr_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-572" audience="Markup">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Business</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-572">
                                    <primary>business</primary>
                                    <secondary>Hansen</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-572">
                                    <primary>Hansen, Morten</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info><citation xml:id="cite_Hansen2009" linkend="Hansen2009">(Hansen
                            2009)</citation>.</para>
                </footnote></para>
        </formalpara>
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-12.3" label="12.3">
        <title>Smarter Farming in Japan</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-12.3" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>case studies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>farming</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Overview.</title>
            <para>Unlike the first two case studies, this is an actual case rather than a
                hypothetical or composite one. It shares with the first two cases a focus on
                preserving valuable resources but in the radically different domain of
                farming.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.3-ksc_ypr_lr">This case concerns an initiative by
            Fujitsu, a Japanese technology firm, to apply <quote>smart computing</quote> and lean
            manufacturing techniques to the agricultural sector, which lags in technology use.
            Fujitsu is testing a <quote>farm work management system</quote> at six Japanese farms.
            In this case study we will focus on the farm highlighted in a <date>2011</date>
            <orgname>Wall Street Journal</orgname> story.<footnote xml:id="endnote-573" label="653"
                audience="Business">
                <para audience="Business" xml:id="para-12.3-ktc_ypr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-573" audience="Markup">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Business</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-573">
                                <primary>business</primary>
                                <secondary>Wakabayashi</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><citation xml:id="cite_Wakabayashi2011" linkend="Wakabayashi2011"
                        >(Wakabayashi 2011)</citation>.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.3-h5c_ypr_lr">This test farm is located in southern
            Japan. It has 60 different crops spread over 100 hectares (about 250 acres), an area
            slightly larger than the central campus of the University of California at
            Berkeley.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>What is being organized?</title>
            <para>Sensors are deployed in each of 300 different farm plots to collect readings on
                temperature, soil, and moisture levels. Video cameras also monitor each plot.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.3-rvc_ypr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-12.3-rvc_ypr_lr">
                        <primary>location</primary>
                        <secondary>tracking</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-12.3-rvc_ypr_lr">
                        <primary>GPS</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>The 72 relatively unskilled workers on the farm are also managed resources. Each
            of them carries a mobile phone for communication, transmission of pictures, and
                <abbrev>GPS</abbrev> tracking of their location.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Why is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The highest-level goal for Fujitsu is to expand its reach as a technology firm by
                applying the concepts of lean manufacturing, statistical process control, and
                continual improvement to new domains. Farming is an obvious choice in Japan because
                it is a relatively unproductive sector where the average age is over sixty. It is
                essential that farms use more computing capability to increase efficiency and to
                capture and reuse the scarce knowledge possessed by aging workers.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.3-uwc_ypr_lr">The Fujitsu farm work management system
            supports numerous types of interactions to achieve these goals. For example, workers can
            send pictures of infected crops for diagnosis by an expert farmer in the farm’s office,
            who can then investigate further by studying recorded video from the affected
            plot.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.3-lxc_ypr_lr">As more farms deploy the Fujitsu system,
            the aggregated knowledge and sensor information can be analyzed to enable economies of
            scale that will allow separate and widely distributed farms to function as if they were
            all part of a single large firm with centralized management.<footnote
                xml:id="endnote-574" label="654" audience="Business">
                <para audience="Business" xml:id="para-12.3-yxc_ypr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-574" audience="Markup">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Business</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-574">
                                <primary>business</primary>
                                <secondary>integration</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><citation xml:id="cite_Hori2010" linkend="Hori2010">(Hori, Kawashima, and
                        Yamazaki 2010)</citation>. Fujitsu expects that the system will eventually
                    integrate business management functions, production history, and operational
                    support for best practices.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How much is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The current design of the system treats farm workers as relatively passive
                resources that are managed very closely. The system generates a daily schedule of
                planting, maintenance, harvesting, and other activities for each worker. At a daily
                wrap-up meeting the farm manager reviews each worker’s performance based on
                    <abbrev>GPS</abbrev> and sensor readings.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.3-uyc_ypr_lr">The sensor data is analyzed and
            organized extensively by Fujitsu computers to make recommendations, both agricultural
            ones (e.g., what crop grows best in each plot and the work schedule that optimizes
            quality and yield) and business ones (the profitability of growing this crop on this
            plot of land).</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>When is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The farm work management system is continually organizing and reorganizing what it
                knows about the farm as it analyzes sensor and production information. In contrast,
                the information created by the workers is captured but its analysis is deferred to
                an expert.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.3-qzc_ypr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-12.3-qzc_ypr_lr">
                        <primary>Moore’s law</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>It is conceivable that as the farm workers become more expert as a result of the
            guidance and instruction they receive from the system that they can be more autonomous
            and do more analysis and interpretation on their own. It is also likely that the
            inexorable forces of Moore’s law will enable more data collection and more processing of
            the sensor data at its time of collection, which might result in increased real-time
            information exchange with the workers.</para>
        <formalpara xml:id="para-12.3-f1d_ypr_lr">
            <title>How or by whom is it being organized?</title>
            <para audience="CORE"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-12.3-f1d_ypr_lr">
                            <primary>computational</primary>
                            <secondary>agents</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info>The physical organization of the farm, with 300 small plots of land with 60
                different fruits and vegetables, is the legacy arrangement of the farm before the
                Fujitsu trial began. Because of the sizable investment that Fujitsu has made in the
                farm to deploy the system, it is likely that the farm manager defers to
                recommendations made by the system to change crop arrangements. So it is reasonable
                to conclude that most of the decisions about the organizing system are made by
                computational processes rather than by people.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Other considerations.</title>
            <para>Fujitsu built this system for managing farms, but there are several other resource
                domains with similar challenges about capturing and reusing operational knowledge:
                vineyards, forests, and fish farms come to mind.<footnote xml:id="endnote-575"
                    label="655" audience="Computing">
                    <para audience="Computing" xml:id="para-12.3-abd_ypr_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-575">
                                    <primary>sensor network</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-575">
                                    <primary>Burrell, Jenna</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-575" audience="Markup">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Computing</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-575">
                                    <primary>computing</primary>
                                    <secondary>sensor networks</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>See<citation xml:id="cite_Burrell2004" linkend="Burrell2004"
                            >(Burrell, Brooke, and Beckwith 2004)</citation> for a study of the use
                        of sensor networks in Oregon vineyards.</para>
                </footnote> It will be interesting to see if the farm work management system can be
                made more abstract and configurable so that the same system can be used in all of
                these domains.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.3-hbd_ypr_lr">Farm crops, vineyards, trees, and fish
            pens do not move around, so a more challenging application of sensor technologies arises
            with cattle herd management. Nevertheless, sensors inserted in the genitals of a female
            dairy cow can trigger a text message to a herd manager’s cell phone when the cow is in
            heat, preventing the economic loss of missing a reproductive cycle.<footnote
                xml:id="endnote-576" label="656" audience="Linguistics">
                <para audience="Linguistics" xml:id="para-12.3-vbd_ypr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-576">
                                <primary>linguistics</primary>
                                <secondary>sexting</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-576" audience="Markup">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Linguistics</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><citation xml:id="cite_Tagliabue2012" linkend="Tagliabue2012">(Tagliabue
                        2012)</citation>. We cannot resist describing this as <quote>sexting</quote>
                    by cows.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.3-bcd_ypr_lr">Somewhat more remote domains for
            potential application of systems that combine sensor networks with workforce management
            include sales, field support, and logistics.</para>
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-12.4" label="12.4">
        <title>Single-Source Textbook Publishing</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-12.4" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>case studies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>textbook publishing</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Overview.</title>
            <para>The fourth case is also an actual case—a self-referential one. It is a case study
                about the organizing system involved in the creation, production, and distribution
                of <citetitle pubwork="book">The Discipline of Organizing</citetitle>. See <citation
                    linkend="Glushko2015" xml:id="cite_Glushko2015">(Glushko
                2015)</citation>.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.4-x42_zpr_lr"><phrase xml:id="TDO-book-source-files"
                >We have known since the beginning of this project that this book should not just be
                a conventional text. A printed book is an intellectual snapshot that is already
                dated in many respects the day it is published. In addition, the pedagogical goal of
                    <citetitle linkend="Glushko2013b" pubwork="book">The Discipline of
                    Organizing</citetitle> as a textbook for information schools and similar
                programs is made more difficult by the relentless growth of computing capability and
                the resulting technology innovation in our information-intensive economy and
                culture. We think that the emergence of ebook publishing opens up innovative
                possibilities as long as we can use a single set of source files to produce and
                update the print and digital versions of this book.</phrase></para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>What is being organized?</title>
            <para>The content of this book began in early <date>2010</date> as more than 1000 slides
                and associated instructor notes for a graduate course <quote>Information Organizing
                    and Retrieval</quote> that <personname><firstname>Robert</firstname>
                    <othername>J.</othername>
                    <surname>Glushko</surname></personname>, the primary author and editor of
                    <citetitle pubwork="book" linkend="Glushko2013b">The Discipline of
                    Organizing</citetitle>, was teaching at the <orgname>University of California,
                    Berkeley</orgname>. These slides and notes were created in XML and transformed
                to HTML for presentation in a web browser.<footnote xml:id="endnote-577" label="657"
                    audience="Computing">
                    <para audience="Computing" xml:id="para-12.4-hq2_zpr_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-577" audience="Markup">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Computing</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-577" userlevel="Professional">
                                    <primary>computing</primary>
                                    <secondary>citations</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info><citation xml:id="cite_Wilde2007" linkend="Wilde2007">(Wilde and
                            Catin 2007)</citation>. Looking back it seems ironic to start with a
                        single-source XML publishing system, abandon it to author the book in Word,
                        and then convert the files Word back to XML to enable single-source
                        publishing.</para>
                </footnote></para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.4-br2_zpr_lr">The first decision to be made about
            resource organization led to the iterative sorting of the slides from 26 lectures into
            the 10 chapters in the initial outline for the book. The second decision concerned the
            granularity of the new content resources being created for the book. The team of authors
            was organized by chapters, which made chapters the natural granularity for file
            management and version control. Because authors were widely dispersed we relied on the
            Dropbox cloud storage service to synchronize work. Nevertheless, the broad and deep
            topical coverage of the book meant that chapters had substantial internal structure
            (four levels of headings in some places), and many of these subsections became
            separately identified resources that moved from chapter to chapter until they found
            their natural home.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.4-jr2_zpr_lr">In addition to the text content and
            illustrations that make up the printed text, we needed to organize short videos,
            interactive examples, and other applications to incorporate in digital versions of the
            book.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.4-ds2_zpr_lr">Finally, it has been essential to view
            the software that transforms, assembles, formats, and assigns styles when turning source
            files into deliverable artifacts as resources that must be managed. For the first and
            second editions of the book, we were fortunate to get much of the software required to
            build both print and ebooks from O’Reilly and Associates, an innovative technology
            publisher that has been developing a single-source publishing system called Atlas.
            Because we have recently been experimenting with including richer interactivity and
            navigation capability, reader-controlled personalization, and other features that go
            beyond what Atlas enables, we now use our own custom-built single-source publishing
            system. </para>
        <formalpara xml:id="para-12.4-ps2_zpr_lr">
            <title>Why is it being organized?</title>
            <para audience="CORE"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-12.4-ps2_zpr_lr">
                            <primary>costs</primary>
                            <secondary>human factors</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info>Publishing print and ebook versions of a text from the same source files is
                the only way to produce both in a cost-effective and maintainable fashion.
                Approaches that require any <quote>hand-crafting</quote> would make it impossible to
                revise the book on a timely schedule. Furthermore, a survey of Berkeley students in
                the summer of <date>2012</date> revealed a great diversity of preferred platforms
                for reading digital books that included laptop computers, Apple and Android tablets,
                and seven different dedicated ebook readers. Only an automated single-source
                publishing strategy could produce all these outputs.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.4-zs2_zpr_lr">The highly granular structure for the
            content resources that comprise this book makes cross-referencing vastly more precise,
            making it easier to use the book as a textbook and job aid. It will also make it easier
            to maintain and adapt the text for use in online courses. (The emerging best practice
            for online courses is to break up lectures and study content into smaller units than
            used in traditional classroom lectures.) </para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How much is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The nature and extent of resource organization for this book reflects its purpose
                of bringing together multiple disciplines that recognize organizing as a fundamental
                issue but from different perspectives. The book contains many specialized topics and
                domain-specific examples that might overwhelm the shared concepts. Our solution was
                to write a lean core text and to move much of the disciplinary and domain-specific
                content into tagged endnotes. These categories of endnotes are somewhat arbitrary,
                but the authoring task of identifying content to go into endnotes is a non-trivial
                one. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.4-e52_zpr_lr">The extent of resource organization is
            also affected by the choice of <abbrev>XML</abbrev> vocabulary, and we carefully
            considered whether to choose <abbrev>DITA</abbrev> or DocBook. <abbrev>DITA</abbrev> has
            the benefit of having more native support for modular authoring and transparent
            customization and updating, but DocBook is much older and hence has better toolkits. We
            eventually chose DocBook.<footnote xml:id="endnote-578" label="658" audience="Computing">
                <para audience="Computing" xml:id="para-12.4-r52_zpr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-578" audience="Markup">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Computing</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-578">
                                <primary>computing</primary>
                                <secondary>DITA and DocBook</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-578">
                                <primary>DITA</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-578">
                                <primary>DocBook</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><citation xml:id="cite_Kimber2012" linkend="Kimber2012">(Kimber
                        2012)</citation> seems destined to become the definitive resource for
                    DITA-based publishing. The definitive source for DocBook has long been <citation
                        xml:id="cite_Walsh2010-10.1" linkend="Walsh2010">(Walsh
                    2010)</citation>.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <formalpara xml:id="para-12.4-dv2_zpr_lr">
            <title>When is it being organized?</title>
            <para><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-12.4-dv2_zpr_lr">
                            <primary>tradeoffs</primary>
                            <secondary>among authoring environments</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info>Despite the fact that the lecture notes with which the book began were in
                    <abbrev>XML</abbrev>, we decided to author the book using Microsoft Word. Many
                of the authors had little experience with <abbrev>XML</abbrev> editors, and the
                highly developed commenting and revision management facilities in Word proved very
                useful. This tradeoff imposed the burden of converting files to <abbrev>XML</abbrev>
                during the production process, but only two of the authors were still working on the
                book at that stage, and both have decades of experience with hypertext markup
                languages.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How or by whom is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The chapter authors used Word style sheets in a careful manner, tagging text with
                styles rather than using formatting overrides. This enabled a conversion vendor to
                convert most of the book from Word to <abbrev>XML</abbrev> semi-automatically. Some
                cleanup of the markup is inevitable because of the ambiguity created when the source
                markup with Word styles is less granular than the target markup in
                    <abbrev>XML</abbrev>. We do not know whether the amount of work left for us was
                atypical.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.4-gw2_zpr_lr">Nevertheless, waiting until the book was
            substantially finished to convert to <abbrev>XML</abbrev> meant that we were also
            deferring the effort to mark up the text with cross references, citations, glossary
            terms, and index entries, because these types of content were not included in the Word
            authoring templates and style sheets. As a result, a substantial amount of effort has
            been required of our copy and markup editor that could have been done by chapter editors
            if they had authored natively in <abbrev>XML</abbrev>. However, having a single markup
            editor has given this book a more consistent and complete bibliography, glossary, and
            index than would be have possible with multiple authors. </para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Other considerations.</title>
            <para>Because every bit of content in the book is tagged as either <quote>core</quote>
                or discipline-specific, our source files collectively represent a <quote>family of
                    books</quote> with 2048 different members, any one of which we can build by
                filtering the content to include any combination from zero to eleven disciplines. It
                is impractical to publish this many editions, but we hope to use this flexibility to
                enable instructors to tailor the text for a wide range of courses in many different
                academic disciplines and customize the text for both graduate and undergraduate
                students. Better still would be an approach that defers the generation of a
                particular version of an ebook from <quote>publishing time</quote> to <quote>reading
                    time.</quote> The same algorithms apply, but now the reader decides when and how
                to apply them, enabling the dynamic configuration of the book's content. This
                radical capability is experimental as of August 2015, but we expect it to generally
                available before too long.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.4-tx2_zpr_lr">This design for a book challenges
            conventional definitions of book editions and forces us to imagine new ways to
            acknowledge collaborative authorship. But asking <quote>What is <citetitle
                    linkend="Glushko2013b" pubwork="book">The Discipline of
                Organizing</citetitle>?,</quote> given these new authoring and publishing models, is
            a similar question to the one asked in <xref linkend="chapter-4" xrefstyle="short"/>,
                <quote>What is <citetitle pubwork="manuscript" linkend="Shakespeare1623"
                    >Macbeth</citetitle>?</quote>
        </para>
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-12.5" label="12.5">
        <title>Organizing a Kitchen</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-12.5" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>case studies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>kitchen</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.5-rvg_1qr_lr">By
                    <personname><firstname>Emilie</firstname><surname>Hardman</surname></personname>,
                <date>April 2013</date>.</para>
        <formalpara xml:id="para-12.5-zvg_1qr_lr">
            <title>Overview.</title>
            <para><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-12.5-zvg_1qr_lr">
                            <primary>location</primary>
                            <secondary>kitchen</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info>Just about everyone has a kitchen in their home or apartment, and most
                kitchens contain many of the same resources. These include pots and pans, dishes,
                bowls, drinking glasses, silverware, and cooking tools of various kinds. Kitchens
                are also often the location for organizing food items, cooking ingredients, spices,
                wine, and other beverages. Kitchens also invariably contain refrigerators and
                freezers for storing prepared and preserved food. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.5-qwg_1qr_lr">The organizing system for a kitchen is
            highly influenced by the size, shape, and arrangement of the counters, cabinets,
            shelves, and other parts of the physical environment of the kitchen. A person building a
            new home might be able to design this kitchen environment, but most people treat this as
            a given and work within its affordances, often because there are limits to how much the
            physical environment can be easily changed. </para>
        <sidebar xml:id="sidebar-Kitchen">
            <title>Kitchen Organizing System</title>
            <info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-Kitchen">
                        <primary>kitchen</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>
            <?dbhtml sidebar-width="62%"?>
            <?dbhtml float-type="right"?>
            <informalfigure xml:id="PICTURE-S12.5-Kitchen">
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="Pictures/10.7.5-Kitchen.jpg" format="JPG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                        <phrase role="ALT">Image of <personname><firstname>Emilie</firstname>
                                <surname>Hardman</surname></personname>’s kitchen.</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.5-wwg_1qr_lr"><phrase role="caption"
                                >My kitchen. I did my annual deep kitchen clean and it deserved a
                                picture.</phrase></para>
                        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.5-gxg_1qr_lr"><phrase role="credit"
                                    >(<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                    xlink:href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/quintanaroo/2741672230/"
                                    >Photo by
                                            <personname><firstname>Emilie</firstname><surname>Hardman</surname></personname>.</link>
                                Creative Commons CC-BY-SA-2.0 license.)</phrase></para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
        </sidebar>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>What is being organized?</title>
            <para>Our wine, wine glasses, cocktail glasses and ingredients, as well as tea and
                coffee stuff were stored in the cabinet by the fridge, close to the center worktable
                so people could have easy access to them. Because of space limitations, this meant
                that our water glasses had to be somewhere else, but as we would usually put out
                water for dinner parties or have a pitcher and glasses on a tray when people came
                over, we thought this was reasonable, since the things people would most often be
                looking for and need easy access to for themselves would be these more social
                drinking glasses.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.5-byg_1qr_lr">We also bought a freestanding worktable
            with a butcher’s block and stainless steel for pastry and chocolate work, as well as
            extra counter space in general. It worked as a prep space and as an area to lay out
            finished dishes or drinks for people to serve themselves when we had parties.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.5-hyg_1qr_lr">Some kitchen tools were kept with the
            food items to which they applied: for example, the coffee and the coffee grinder, or the
            cutting board, toaster, bread knife and bread all together. Other tools were kept with
            like tools: potato peelers, julienne tools, knives, etc. This was probably because of
            the kind of flexibility something like a potato peeler would have versus a coffee
            grinder; it also made more sense to put lots of these little things together in a drawer
            rather than leave them strewn out around the apples or potatoes.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.5-vyg_1qr_lr">Pots and pans had their own spaces and
            were stacked within one another; same with dishes. Most frequently used things were
            given preference over specialty tools.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.5-bzg_1qr_lr">Other things that were organized around
            the social dimensions of the kitchen were some food items and serving elements. For
            example, we used bowls to organize chocolate bars and treats that might easily be
            grabbed to set out and serve. Similarly, we kept stacks of serving bowls easily at hand
            so we could empty pretzels or tortilla chips, olives, etc., quickly and casually.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Why is it being organized?</title>
            <para>We wanted to emphasize a feeling of comfort and openness in our kitchen, so people
                would feel free to get what they wanted when they needed it. It also had to work on
                a practical level to be an efficient work area in a small space, so those concerns
                had to be balanced as well.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>When is it being organized?</title>
            <para>We ended up moving silverware at one point because friends would consistently open
                a particular drawer in our center work island to look for silverware. Initially, I
                had specialized tools in that drawer because they were what I would reach for when I
                was working on something like making chocolates, but because of the continuous
                confusion, we moved those tools to another drawer and put the silverware where
                people seemed to expect it.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.5-f1h_1qr_lr">The fridge and freezer was organized by
            type of food for orderliness, ease of access, and immediacy of knowing when we had. We
            have a pull-out freezer, so things could get a little hidden, but assuming no one had
            compromised the system, you would know it was frozen fruit all of the way down in one
            segment and flours in another.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.5-l1h_1qr_lr">Some food items demanded different
            placement or storage based on their ripeness, the season, etc. In <date>August</date> we
            might be overrun with tomatoes, for example, and the window sills would fill up with
            them, whereas we would usually put them in a bowl if there were just a few.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How or by whom is it being organized?</title>
            <para>I think one thing to sum up would be to say that my partner is a librarian and I
                am trained as an archivist. We both care about classification and public service, so
                as people who also entertain a lot, I think these very practical and intuitive
                systems of grouping things is a motivation. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.5-nbh_1qr_lr">My father, an engineer who in his
            retirement does a lot of woodworking, built two cabinets that would
                <emphasis>just</emphasis> fit into the space and provide more storage than the two
            upper cabinets and three base cabinets provided in the kitchen.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Other considerations.</title>
            <para>The whole kitchen was not organized around guests, though. We also arranged things
                to be practical for cooking and for space saving. Food in the cabinets was organized
                by general function: for example, there was a shelf of dried beans in jars, another
                of dried chilies and spices—things that give flavor. Spices were organized within
                that by general type in rows and then alphabetically within those rows. This was
                because the rows helped group things which might be likely used together (e.g.,
                cinnamon, cloves, mace, nutmeg) and alphabetically because so many of them look the
                same from the outside; knowing that the oregano would necessarily be shelved before
                the thyme was useful. Beans, though, because they are more immediately identifiable,
                less used, and certainly not as often used in concert (as one would with spices), I
                was a little more loose with and sometimes just arranged to a general aesthetic
                preference; if we had heirloom money beans, I might have preferred to see them over
                the standard red lentils, for example.</para>
        </formalpara>
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-12.6" label="12.6" revision="3.0" revisionflag="added">
        <title>Earth Orbiting Satellites</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-12.6" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>case studies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>earth orbiting satellites</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.6-zvh_bqr_lr">By
                    <personname><firstname>Daniel</firstname>
                <surname>Brenners</surname></personname>, <date>December 2014</date>.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Overview.</title>
            <para>Twenty two thousand miles above our heads, a global race for orbital real estate
                is underway. A single circular orbit around the Earth, called the geostationary
                Earth orbit (GEO), is the only area in space that allows a satellite to remain in a
                fixed point in the sky above Earth's surface while it
                    rotates.<superscript>1</superscript> This prime location allows for satellites
                to have consistent communication with the ground below. Satellite television, a $100
                billion industry, relies on satellites within the GEO to broadcast signals to homes
                across the world. Global positioning systems (GPS) and military applications also
                depend on satellites within this thin ring around the Earth. Unfortunately, space is
                severely limited in the GEO, and tension is growing over who gets to send their
                satellites to this valuable parking lot in the sky. The principles used to organize
                which satellites get to be placed in the GEO have many unforeseen legal and
                sociopolitical complications. As room becomes limited, it becomes increasingly
                important to find a solution to the problem of multiple organizing agents competing
                to organize this system to support varying interactions.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>What is being organized?</title>
            <para>The scope of resources being organized are the satellites being deployed to the
                GEO. These are physical objects that have been launched into orbit. The satellites
                are each unique and are able to provide a variety of interactions. The only unifying
                attribute that they share is that they are computers that are able to send and
                receive radio signals to and from Earth. To stay in orbit, they are also able to
                adjust their position with propulsion systems. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para xml:id="para-uhv_wsm_qs">This organizing system is designed to manage a collection in
            which resources are continually added and removed. The International Telecommunications
            Union (ITU) records which portions of the orbit are already
                occupied.<superscript>2</superscript> Satellites cannot stay in the orbit forever,
            as they expend lots of energy performing computational processes and maintaining orbit,
            and eventually run out of power. The resources follow a lifecycle that is unique to each
            individual resource, but the timescale is typically one to fifteen
                years.<superscript>3</superscript></para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Why is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Satellites are being organized in the GEO to support several interactions. The GEO
                allows satellites to move at the same rate as the Earth, giving it a stationary view
                of more than 40 percent of the Earth's surface. Such a view is ideal for
                broadcasting signals to large regions and performing remote sensing, such as weather
                forecasting. They also serve as crucial relay points to transfer telecommunications
                across the globe. Other interactions that these satellites provide include
                surveillance, scientific research, global positioning, navigation, and military
                    reconnaissance.<superscript>3</superscript> Longitudinal positioning along the
                GEO shapes which interactions can occur and which users can interact with the
                satellite. For instance, a satellite directly over the Atlantic Ocean may not be
                well suited to broadcast a television signal, but may be positioned to relay signals
                from North America to Europe. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para xml:id="para-odb_vsm_qs">The users are practically everyone on Earth. Civilians use
            geostationary satellites directly when they use GPS or need to have a call relayed to
            distant regions of the world. Commercial organizations, such as television providers,
            use these satellites to broadcast signals down to viewers. Geostationary satellites are
            also particularly useful for early warning systems used by the military to detect
            ballistic events around the globe.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How much is it being organized?</title>
            <para>If resources are able to be placed in the GEO, they are placed in a vacant slot
                that the applicant chooses, based on what types of interactions they want to support
                and what users they want interacting with the satellite. To prevent signal
                interference and collision, satellites need to be placed very far apart, leaving
                only 2,000 total orbital slots where satellites can be placed in the
                    GEO.<superscript>4</superscript> The ITU uses a first-come, first-served
                organizing principle to decide which resources are placed into orbital slots,
                provided the applicant completes the lengthy application process.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para xml:id="para-mpr_zsm_qs">The organization applying for the slot chooses where to place
            its satellite. The ITU catalogs these slots as degrees longitude, and includes other
            resource descriptions such as the name of the satellite, country of operator, types of
            users, mass, expected lifetime, and contractor.<superscript>3</superscript>
            Organizations choose to place satellites around the longitude of the Earth that the
            satellite is supposed to interact with. Since the latitude is fixed at zero degrees,
            countries with the same longitude but different latitudes (countries directly north or
            south of each other) must vie for the same slots.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>When is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Satellites are added as soon as they can be approved by the ITU and launched into
                orbit. At the end of their life cycle, the Federal Communications Commission
                mandates that U.S. satellites are pushed into what is called the graveyard orbit,
                which is a few hundred kilometers outside of the GEO.<superscript>5</superscript> At
                this point, another satellite can be added to the vacant slot via the ITU
                application process.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How or by whom is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Many organizing agents are competing with each other to organize this system
                according to their own needs. Applications to occupy the GEO come from countries,
                scientific organizations, companies, and civilians. Satellite TV companies such as
                DirecTV, Dish Network, and Intelsat own a large number of the slots across the
                western hemisphere. Countries such as the United States, Russia, and the United
                Kingdom own a majority of the military satellites, and multinational European
                organizations own a large share of orbital slots as
                    well.<superscript>3</superscript></para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Other considerations.</title>
            <para>Although the ITU serves as an authoritative entity for this organizing system, the
                reality is that the ambiguous legality of ownership in outer space means that anyone
                can attempt to organize this system. The ITU is in place to perform the useful task
                of cataloging occupied slots and facilitating the filling of vacancies, but it has
                no way of enforcing these guidelines.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para xml:id="para-ipn_gtm_qs">This organizing system is interesting because many agents are
            attempting to organize the same system. There are also interesting social implications
            that stem from the system’s principles of organization. The first-come, first-served
            system of the ITU has the effect of allowing only technologically advanced organizations
            to manage the collection. It does not take into consideration that by the time many
            countries are finally ready to use this type of technology, there will be no more room
            in the GEO belt.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-cvz_htm_qs">Ironically, the only legal claim to sovereignty that has been
            made of this organizing system has been from countries that, generally, have no means of
            organizing it themselves. In 1976 eight equatorial countries, which lie directly below
            the GEO belt, stated that they had exclusive rights over these slots in a document known
            as the Bogotá Declaration.<superscript>6</superscript> The tenuous claim was that the
            orbit is not a part of outer space, because its existence is solely dependent on Earth's
            gravity, and that the earth within the borders of the equatorial countries creates GEO
            with its gravitational pull. Many experts disagree, stating that the gravitational pull
            from the moon and other celestial bodies defines the GEO, and state that the orbit does
            indeed lie in outer space because it is further than 100 kilometers from Earth. This
            demarcation, known as the Kármán line, is a widely accepted definition of when space
                begins.<superscript>7</superscript> This would then make the GEO fall within the
            1967 Outer Space Treaty, effectively leaving no possibility for ownership of the
            orbit.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-l4v_ltm_qs">Finding a dividing line between space and Earth’s atmosphere
            is an interesting topic, especially considering that ownership of valuable resources may
            be decided based on what is included in the category of space versus the category of
            atmosphere. In this case, the Kármán line roughly represents the altitude at which an
            aircraft would have to propel itself faster than the speed at which the Earth rotates to
            establish enough lift to keep itself up. While this is not intuitive (hardly carving
            nature at its joints), it does serve as a useful demarcation that is not completely
            arbitrary. It can be seen as a goal-based category, where the goal is using traditional
            means of traveling through the air using aeronautics. It makes sense that this is the
            line the Fédération Aéronautique Internationale uses to divide astronautics and
            aeronautics.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-zrd_mtm_qs">The limited availability of spots in the GEO, along with the
            relatively small number of countries able to launch satellites, has the potential to
            further divide countries. By the time most countries will be able to launch satellites,
            there will likely not be any room left. Although there are only around 400 satellites
            currently in geostationary orbit, there are already more filings for ITU applications
            than there are spots available.<superscript>4</superscript> Only a select few countries
            will be able to take advantage of the GEO, leaving others to depend on these countries
            for communication, scientific research, and surveillance. Furthermore, this could limit
            the interactions of these less developed countries to those interactions dictated by the
            countries with geostationary satellites. In particular, these developed countries can
            greatly influence the information that citizens in other countries can receive via
            satellite.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-py2_4tm_qs">But even within the technologically advanced countries,
            competition for orbital slots may be heating up. In early 2014, the US unveiled its
            Geosynchronous Space Situational Awareness Program (GSSAP), which aims to create
            maneuverable satellites that monitor and protect the precious GEO
                belt.<superscript>8</superscript> This reveal comes only months after China was seen
            practicing its anti-satellite missile capabilities.<superscript>9</superscript> In
            Russia, $300 million is being spent to construct a craft that would act as a
                <quote>space broom</quote> to push satellites out of geostationary orbit. The US has
            a similar program, named the Phoenix project under DARPA, developing a robotic device
            that can help maintain satellites and possibly dismantle others without causing excess
            space debris.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-wtf_rtm_qs">Although this might simply be countries attempting to flex
            their military muscles, these technologies represent a newfound ability for countries to
            organize resources in the GEO to fit their own agenda. Years ago, the countries that
            were able to get satellites into orbit were the ones that could reap the benefits. Now,
            it seems that we may be entering an age where a country’s ability to make room for
            itself, possibly by force, will determine if it can make use of precious interactions
            created by these limited resources.</para>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Notes:</title>
            <para xml:id="para-l41_dsm_qs">The following notes relate to this case study.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para xml:id="para-jyx_2sm_qs">NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory Basics of Space Flight
                    Section 1 Chapter 5: Planetary Orbits <link
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www2.jpl.nasa.gov/basics/bsf5-1.php"
                            ><uri>http://www2.jpl.nasa.gov/basics/bsf5-1.php</uri></link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para xml:id="para-fcl_fsm_qs">ITU Space Services Department (SSD) 2014 <link
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.itu.int/ITU-R/go/space/en"
                            ><uri>http://www.itu.int/ITU-R/go/space/en</uri></link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para xml:id="para-gbv_fsm_qs">Union of Concerned Scientists Satellite Database
                        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.ucsusa.org/nuclear_weapons_and_global_security/solutions/space-weapons/ucs-satellite-database.html#.VJKNXmTF-5I"
                            ><uri>http://www.ucsusa.org/nuclear_weapons_and_global_security/solutions/space-weapons/ucs-satellite-database.html#.VJKNXmTF-5I</uri></link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para xml:id="para-pwb_gsm_qs">Posen M., Have We Got a Slot? RPC Telecommunications
                    Ltd. World Space Forum Dubai March 2010 <link
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.rpctelecom.com/files/Have%20We%20Got%20A%20Slot.pdf"
                            ><uri>http://www.rpctelecom.com/files/Have We Got A
                        Slot.pdf</uri></link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para xml:id="para-fzy_gsm_qs">De Selding P., FCC Enters Orbital Debris Debate.
                    Space News, 28 Jun. 2004</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para xml:id="para-wrd_hsm_qs">Finch M., Limited Space: Allocating the Geostationary
                    Orbit. Northwestern Journal of International Law Vol 7 Issue 4 Fall 1986</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para xml:id="para-p4j_hsm_qs">Haraszti G., Questions of International Law Volume 2.
                    Akademiai Kiado Budapest 1981</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para xml:id="para-bf4_hsm_qs">Hsu J., Global Conflict Could Threaten Geostationary
                    Satellites: China, Russia and the U.S. have the ability to destroy one another’s
                    eyes in the sky. Scientific American March 31, 2014 <link
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/global-conflict-could-threaten-geostationary-satellites/"
                            ><uri>http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/global-conflict-could-threaten-geostationary-satellites/</uri></link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para xml:id="para-t25_hsm_qs">Shalal-Esa A. U.S. sees China launch as test of
                    anti-satellite muscle. Reuters May 2013 <link
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2013/05/15/us-china-launch-idUSBRE94E07D20130515"
                            ><uri>http://www.reuters.com/article/2013/05/15/us-china-launch-idUSBRE94E07D20130515</uri></link></para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <!--
        <formalpara role="CORE"><title>Related Readings</title>
          <para>See <ulink
                url="http://DisciplineOfOrganizing.org">
                <uri>DisciplineOfOrganizing.org</uri></ulink></para></formalpara>
-->
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-12.7" label="12.7" revision="3.0" revisionflag="added">
        <title>CalBug and its Search Interface Redesign</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-12.7" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>case studies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>CalBug Search Interface</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.7-yvc_cqr_lr">By
                    <personname><firstname>Gracen</firstname>
                <surname>Brilmyer</surname></personname>, <date>December 2014</date>.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Overview.</title>
            <para>The CalBug project, housed out of the The Essig Museum of Entomology at the
                University of California, Berkeley, is a collaborative initiative between nine
                California institutions with a goal to digitize over a million specimens.
                Digitization involves imaging both specimens and their labels as well as storing
                their collection info in a database. The CalBug project also is attempting to
                georeference, or locate the original latitude and longitude coordinates, for these
                million specimens (some dating back to the 18th century) so that they can be better
                used for research. The project uses many student workers, graduate students, and
                volunteers to capture the images and data. Over the past few years, it has
                participated in the Notes from Nature project, which helps connect citizen
                scientists to scientific research. Through the images generated of the specimen
                labels by the team at the Essig Museum, citizen scientists digitally transcribe the
                data that can be read from the image. The Essig, after each label is transcribed by
                24 citizen scientists, runs an R program to find the most accurate transcription and
                transfer it into the Essig’s database. These combined efforts have accumulated in
                over 209,000 specimen records and over 400,000 images and counting. This project has
                a large scope and an ever-increasing scale.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>What is being organized?</title>
            <para>The insect specimens in the CalBug project are digitized on an individual level,
                with unique identifying numbers, and new specimen records and their associated data
                are continually being added to the digital collection. Both the specimens and their
                data are being organized. Existing groups of specimens are prioritized for
                digitization and new physical specimens are accessioned into the collection and are
                databased upon arrival.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Why is it being organized?</title>
            <para>An individual specimen’s associated data can be highly variable; however, as long
                as a specimen has the time and place of its collection (no matter how vague)
                associated with it, it is valuable research material. The physical specimens are
                organized to facilitate the collection manager’s use of the collection. When
                physical specimens need to be borrowed, they must be efficiently found, packaged,
                and sent out on loan, so fastidious organization is key when locating thousands of
                specimens. The digital organization of the collection also facilitates the duties of
                museum staff and the collection manager by allowing for expanded interaction with
                the collection by using the database. The digital collection’s web interface,
                undergoing a redesign as of the time of this writing, makes the collection
                accessible for researchers and novices alike, as well as to foster data sharing to
                other data repositories. Since the specimen data follows digital curatorial
                standards, a web interface that allows these fields to be easily searchable and
                navigable can add to the use of the collection for a broader audience, which is a
                major impetus for the redesign.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <figure xml:id="Figure-12.6-fig1">
            <title>CalBug search interface</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="Pictures/11.7-calbug-1.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase role="ALT">This is the search form for the redesigned CalBug user
                        interface, which contains three sections for Specimen Details, Taxonomy, and
                        Collection Information. Specimen Details has fields for locating a specific
                        specimen description or image. Taxonomy has fields for locating specimens
                        according to their species or genus. Collection Information has fields for
                        locating specimens according to where and when they were collected.</phrase>
                </textobject>
                <caption>
                    <para xml:id="para-qnv_dgn_qs">CalBug's redesigned web search interface</para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <formalpara xml:id="para-12.7-hzc_cqr_lr" audience="CORE">
            <title>How much is it being organized?</title>
            <info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-12.7-hzc_cqr_lr">
                        <primary>Darwin Core</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>
            <para>As discussed in the previous section, the specimens and their information are
                subject to multiple levels of organization, and each level of organization supports
                a different type of user. The data of the CalBug Project is organized according to
                Darwin Core (DwC), a standard <quote>designed to facilitate the exchange of
                    information about the geographic occurrence of species and the existence of
                    specimens in collections.</quote><superscript>1</superscript> Certain specimen
                attributes have concrete institutional parameters, such as unique identifying
                numbers and taxonomic identification, while others have less strict parameters (e.g.
                a precise location of where a specimen is found), although they still must use
                specific DwC fields. Although there are institutional taxonomies in place for
                information associated with a specimen’s collection and identification, the CalBug
                search interface design in <xref linkend="Figure-12.6-fig1"/> allows for an
                outward-­facing reorganization of the existing fields.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>When is it being organized, and by whom?</title>
            <para>The categorization and organization happens at multiple times for one specimen. If
                identified, the specimen is already inserted into the taxonomic classification
                scheme—the hierarchy of how species are related. This scientific warrant is
                inherited and replicated in the physical curation of the collection, and specimens
                are further sorted (within a taxon) by geographic region. Aligning with taxonomic
                categories provides a clear hierarchy for sorting and locating physical specimens
                and, with changes in taxonomy having to be published, makes collection maintenance
                fairly consistent.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para xml:id="para-dyn_dvm_qs">The specimens are organized a second time when they are
            databased, either by interns or through Notes from Nature. The data is stored in a MySQL
            database that uses mostly DwC fields, an institutional taxonomy for specimen data. The
            digitization of specimens, through utilizing DwC institutional semantics, makes
            collection maintenance, governance, and interaction easier, as the collection manager
            can search in a multifaceted manner, better understand the holdings of the museum, and
            track specimens for loans. The unique specimen numbers allow for individual tracking,
            and the other DwC fields provide multiple areas for accurate search and
            retrieval.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-zgj_2vm_qs">For the CalBug web search interface, the specimens retain
            their classification hierarchy within the database. However, the outward-facing search
            fields aim to serve a broader audience, not just the collection manager and museum
            staff. Thus the search application organizes the resources a third time <quote>on the
                way out</quote> of the database in response to a user query. As this design is
            optimized for researchers and students, the classification appears to focus more on
            taskonomy instead of the institutional taxonomy (see <xref linkend="Figure-12.6-fig1"
            />). The 20 search fields provided in the search interface, while actually searching
            through the ~100 fields in the database, facilitate precise information retrieval.
            Although fewer search fields might yield lower accuracy, user testing has shown that the
            new search design improves accuracy by not requiring users to know exactly which DwC
            field to query.</para>
        <figure xml:id="Figure-12.6-fig2">
            <title>Crosswalk table </title>
            <info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="Figure-12.6-fig2">
                        <primary>crosswalk</primary>
                        <secondary>CalBug search redesign</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="Pictures/11.7-calbug-2.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase role="ALT">This figure shows the Crosswalk Table for the redesigned
                        CalBug user interface. It is organized according to the three sections of
                        the new user interface, namely Specimen Details, Taxonomy, and Collection
                        Information. For each of the input fields, the table lists one or more
                        fields in the underlying database that are searched for the content of the
                        input field. For example, the Other Number field in the simplified CalBug
                        user interface maps to eight fields in the database, including Collection
                        Code, Accession Number, and Collectors ID.</phrase>
                </textobject>
                <caption>
                    <para xml:id="para-xjd_bgn_qs">This crosswalk table maps the fields in the
                        CalBug search interface to the underlying database columns.</para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para xml:id="para-slj_gvm_qs">The search is further expanded by having a ‘Search any field’
            box, which literally looks in every DwC field for a term, as well as a <quote>Common
                Name</quote> field, to support novice searches, such as <quote>beetle</quote> and
                <quote>butterfly</quote> instead of <quote>coleoptera</quote> and
                <quote>lepidoptera.</quote> The intrinsic properties of the specimens lend the
            results to simple (alphabetic and numeric) sorting as well as filtering (through the
                <quote>Refine</quote> option) on the list view of the results pages. Additional
            views of results, including a map view showing collection locations and a grid view that
            displays specimen photos, help users locate desired specimens and reorganize as needed
            to suit their needs.</para>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Notes:</title>
            <para>1. <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://wiki.tdwg.org/twiki/bin/view/DarwinCore/WebHome"
                        ><uri>http://wiki.tdwg.org/twiki/bin/view/DarwinCore/WebHome</uri></link></para>
        </formalpara>
        <!--
        <formalpara role="CORE"><title>Related Readings</title>
          <para>See <ulink
                url="http://DisciplineOfOrganizing.org">
                <uri>DisciplineOfOrganizing.org</uri></ulink></para></formalpara>
-->
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-12.8" label="12.8">
        <title>Weekly Newspaper</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-12.8" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>case studies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>weekly newspaper</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.8-rlz_cqr_lr">By
                    <personname><firstname>Ian</firstname>
                <surname>MacFarland</surname></personname>, <date>December 2013</date>.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Overview.</title>
            <para>A weekly neighborhood newspaper in New York City now covers the entire borough of
                Queens. Rather than publish a single weekly edition for this highly diverse area of
                more than 2 million people, its owners have opted to produce 14 separate editions,
                each centered on a different neighborhood. All editions share a deadline, delivery
                schedule, and staff pool, but each has unique content tailored to its target
                readers.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>What is being organized?</title>
            <para>The newspaper’s resources—its content—consist mainly of articles and photos
                generated by staff and freelance contributors throughout the week. Often, newspapers
                will assign their reporters to beats based on subject matter (politics, education,
                    <quote>cops and courts,</quote> etc.), making them domain experts who cover
                stories on that beat throughout a wide geographical area. However, because of this
                paper’s historical orientation toward <quote>hyper-local</quote> neighborhood news,
                it has given each of its seven full-time reporters a more granular geographical beat
                that corresponds to two of the 14 editions’ coverage areas, within which they are
                responsible for general assignment reporting. Most reporters also have a specialty
                for covering news that is of more general interest throughout the borough, such as
                citywide government or transportation issues, and they will include coverage of
                these domains in their story budgets for the week as well. The staff maintains a
                centralized story list that includes a handful of resource descriptions for each
                story: its slug (an abbreviated, descriptive name, including tags for its relevant
                neighborhoods), its length, and whether it has <quote>art.</quote></para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Why is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The media market in New York is crowded and extremely competitive, and this
                newspaper believes its competitive edge lies in its laser-focus on individual
                neighborhoods. Furthermore, most of its readers are subscribers who receive the
                paper in the mail, not newsstand buyers. As a result, the paper generally eschews
                the familiar tabloid approach of splashing the most salacious story of the week
                across the front page and usually fronts two stories that are
                    <quote>small-bore</quote> but extremely relevant to the neighborhood, such as
                the doings of local school or government officials, notable crimes, or
                human-interest stories featuring neighborhood residents. The deeper into the paper
                one goes, the less local its content becomes, and stories often appear in more than
                one edition, in different locations and even with different headlines, to tailor
                them to an appropriate level of localization. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.8-s4z_cqr_lr">On a more general level, of course, the
            paper must support the conventional interactions all readers expect from newspapers.
            Readers are rarely expected to progress through the paper from front to back, so it
            supports a wide variety of reading styles; large headlines and photos and concise,
            compelling story <quote>ledes</quote> (opening paragraphs) facilitate skimming and
            scanning interactions, and dividing the paper into sections, such as
                <quote>Opinion,</quote>
            <quote>Sports,</quote> and <quote>Arts &amp; Entertainment,</quote> lets readers skip
            directly to their areas of interest after turning past page one.</para>
        <formalpara xml:id="para-12.8-epz_cqr_lr">
            <title>How much is it being organized?</title>
            <para><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-12.8-epz_cqr_lr">
                            <primary>location</primary>
                            <secondary>granularity</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info>The level of organization behind the scenes at this small, local newspaper is
                surprisingly complex. The primary organizing principle that determines a story’s
                placement is its relevance, which is a function of location granularity (does it
                directly affect the people of this neighborhood? Did it happen here?), significance
                (will readers find it important?), and time (is it old news? Has anyone else
                reported it yet?). Counterbalancing that is the economic reality of the struggling
                newspaper industry, which results in often severely limited space for the news
                (because paper and press time are costly physical constraints) and manpower with
                which to produce all 14 editions before deadline. The result is a hierarchical
                system in which the 14 editions are categorized into three zones; in each zone,
                about two-thirds of the pages are common to all editions, and the remaining third
                (including, most crucially, pages one through three) are unique to each single
                edition. Thus, for instance, a general-interest story about transportation need not
                be laid out 14 separate times, but one about a fatal car accident can appear on page
                one for the neighborhoods where it occurred and where the victims were from, and
                further back (or not at all) for other neighborhoods.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>When is it being organized?</title>
            <para>In a weekly news cycle, selection, creation, and organizing of editorial resources
                is largely concurrent. The story list is updated on a rolling basis throughout the
                week, and an article or photo’s placement in the paper is often planned based on its
                intended subject matter well in advance of when the resource is actually created.
                However, organizing must be completed long before it reaches its intended users,
                because the final layouts must be printed, collated, and mailed to readers, which,
                due to logistical concerns, takes several days—so the paper is laid out on
                    <date>Tuesday</date> (as late as possible to maximize the window for ad sales),
                printed on <date>Wednesday</date>, and delivered by the <orgname>Postal
                    Service</orgname> on <date>Thursday</date> or <date>Friday</date>.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How or by whom is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Human agents—specifically, editors—are the newspaper’s primary organizers. They
                rely heavily on the judgment of the reporters, who are most familiar with their
                beats, to determine a story’s relevance and placement for each edition, as well as
                their own news judgment, assessment of the story’s quality, and estimation of where
                the story will physically fit based on ad placements (which are decided first). The
                implementation of their organizing system is carried out by page layout designers,
                with some software automation on the part of the paper’s content management
                system.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Other considerations.</title>
            <para>Part of the grind of a weekly news cycle is that the effectivity of the paper’s
                resources is never guaranteed; when the next edition comes out, they all become
                yesterday’s news, and one never knows when new developments will render a story
                irrelevant or incorrect; in fact, because of the latency between layout and
                delivery, a story’s effectivity may even expire before its publication.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <!--
        <formalpara role="CORE"><title>Related Readings</title>
          <para>See <ulink
                url="http://DisciplineOfOrganizing.org">
                <uri>DisciplineOfOrganizing.org</uri></ulink></para></formalpara>
        <para>More about Queens at <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queens"
                    ><uri>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queens</uri></ulink></para>
-->
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-12.9" label="12.9">
        <title>The CODIS DNA Database</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-12.9" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>case studies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>CODIS DNA database</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.9-hdz_dqr_lr">By
                    <personname><firstname>Becca</firstname>
                <surname>Stanger</surname></personname>, <date>December 2013</date>.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Overview.</title>
            <para>Operating on a local, state, and federal level, the
                        <citerefentry><refentrytitle>Combined DNA Index
                        System</refentrytitle><manvolnum>CODIS</manvolnum></citerefentry> is the
                    <abbrev>FBI</abbrev>
                <abbrev>DNA</abbrev> database. As of <date>October 2013</date>, the
                        <citerefentry><refentrytitle>National DNA
                        Index</refentrytitle><manvolnum>NDIS</manvolnum></citerefentry>, or the
                federal level of the <abbrev>CODIS</abbrev>, contained over 10,647,800 offender
                profiles, 1,677,100 arrestee profiles, and 522,200 forensic profiles. Designed to
                help solve crimes, this database has generated over 255,400 hits and has aided over
                216,200 investigations. While this organizing system has played a crucial role in
                reducing crime by enabling more interactions in the law enforcement agency than ever
                before, it provokes numerous ethical questions worth exploring.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <note userlevel="Editor" xml:id="note-ch12-Editor-tj2_1cs_lr">
            <title>Editors' Note</title>
            <para xml:id="para-12.9-w2z_dqr_lr">Bob, Ian asks about fact-check. Murray never did
                one.</para>
        </note>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>What is being organized?</title>
            <para>The <abbrev>CODIS</abbrev> database maintains digital records or
                        <quote><abbrev>DNA</abbrev> profiles</quote> for a wide range of people
                involved in criminal justice cases, including convicted offenders, arrestees,
                missing persons, and more. Specifically, these profiles are measurements of one or
                two alleles of 13 predetermined unique genetic sequence loci. These precise
                measurements provide enough granularity for the profiles to uniquely identify a
                single individual. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.9-ufz_dqr_lr">These resource descriptions are
            generated, often with polymerase chain reaction technology, from the original
                <abbrev>DNA</abbrev> specimen resources by accredited laboratories nationwide. Upon
            creation, the resources themselves—the specimens—are kept at the laboratories, while the
            resource descriptions—the digital profiles—are added to the <abbrev>CODIS</abbrev>
            database. No offender personal identifiers are assigned to the profiles; however,
            information on the submitting agency, specimen, and personnel is stored with the
            profile.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.9-igz_dqr_lr">Rather than focusing on collecting
            resource descriptions, the <abbrev>FBI</abbrev> could have chosen to collect the
            original resources themselves. Presumably, though, this level of coordination of
            physical resources (e.g., shipping, storage, maintenance, etc.) would have placed an
            additional cost on the federal government and required legislative approval. Thus, it is
            understandable that the <abbrev>FBI</abbrev> would choose to minimize cost and effort by
            focusing on the resource descriptions alone.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Why is it being organized?</title>
            <para>In the past, law enforcement agencies were limited to solving crimes within their
                geographic region. A detective working on a murder in California, for example, may
                never have heard of a related murder in New York. The <abbrev>CODIS</abbrev>
                database organizing system encourages that coordination between law enforcement
                agencies in an effort to solve crimes. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.9-qhz_dqr_lr">With 10,647,800 offender profiles in the
                <abbrev>NDIS</abbrev> alone, though, the massive <abbrev>CODIS</abbrev> database
            required an organizing system in order to prove useful to the law enforcement agencies
            involved. The successful creation and maintenance of this organizing system has offered
            newfound interactions to a wide variety of government officials. In addition to law
            enforcement agencies, judicial courts, criminal defense agencies, and population
            statistics agencies can access the <abbrev>CODIS</abbrev> organizing system, enabling
            them to perform a wide variety of functions, including identifying potential suspects in
            criminal investigations, identifying missing persons, collecting population statistics,
            and exonerating convicted criminals.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How much is it being organized?</title>
            <para>As mentioned previously, the high degree of resource description granularity in
                measuring 13 specific genetic sequence loci enables <abbrev>DNA</abbrev> profiles to
                uniquely identify each individual in the database. That being said, the
                    <abbrev>DNA</abbrev> profiles are not simply heaped into one massive database.
            </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.9-n3z_dqr_lr">Instead, the databases are maintained on
            both a state and federal level. A new profile might be checked against a smaller state
            database as well as the larger national one. In addition, the databases are divided into
            different indices dependent on the <abbrev>DNA</abbrev> source, including an offender
            index, arrestee index, forensic index, and missing persons index. </para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.9-cjz_dqr_lr">This division of the database into
            separate indices poses a tradeoff dilemma, though. If <abbrev>CODIS</abbrev> did not
            subdivide the database into federal, state and source indices, it is possible the
            algorithm would be able to find more obscure hits, since the search parameters would be
            broadened. This increase in hit frequency might result in more investigations aided. </para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.9-ljz_dqr_lr">The tradeoff, however, is that the
            broadened search parameters would also necessitate a more complex search algorithm and a
            longer search process. This delay would most likely lead to fewer hits overall. Thus, in
            government institutions where time and resources are limited, it is more important for
            the <abbrev>CODIS</abbrev> organizing system users to generate a larger number of hits
            with subdivided databases than more accurate hits in one collective database. Categories
            in the <abbrev>CODIS</abbrev> organizing system help simplify the interaction
            processes.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>When is it being organized?</title>
            <para><abbrev>DNA</abbrev> profiles enter the <abbrev>CODIS</abbrev> organizing system
                when participating, accredited local, state, and federal laboratories submit them.
                Thus, the laboratory technicians handling the resource and resource description
                decide on a case-by-case basis how a given profile should be categorized and which
                indices it should be added to and checked against. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.9-qkz_dqr_lr">That being said, the lab technicians are
            given strict standards on how a given <abbrev>DNA</abbrev> profile should be
            categorized. These standards vary state by state depending on state law. </para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How or by whom is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Beyond laboratory and state involvement in <abbrev>CODIS</abbrev>, the
                    <abbrev>FBI</abbrev> ultimately maintains and oversees the
                    <abbrev>CODIS</abbrev> database. It maintains the software and search
                algorithms, performs searches throughout the system, and oversees strict quality
                assurance standards for all participating laboratories. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.9-nlz_dqr_lr">To avoid the risk of bias or error
            amongst lab technicians, the <abbrev>FBI</abbrev> could potentially choose to instead
            perform the laboratory processing and categorization themselves. This alteration,
            however, would present new challenges, such as new federal costs related to maintaining
            and processing the resources mentioned previously. In addition, pulling together all
            resources into a <abbrev>FBI</abbrev> processing center would necessitate a meticulous
            record of the resource’s originating state to ensure resource descriptions are
            categorized in accordance with state laws. The <abbrev>FBI</abbrev>’s strict maintenance
            of standards and laws is the best option for addressing the risk of error and
            bias.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Other considerations.</title>
            <para>The <abbrev>CODIS</abbrev> organizing system presents a wide range of intriguing
                ethical questions surrounding race, gender, criminal justice, and privacy. Perhaps
                the most hotly debated issue surrounding <abbrev>DNA</abbrev> databases arose when
                the private <abbrev>DNA</abbrev> testing company <orgname>23andMe</orgname>
                announced that it would discontinue the sale of its genetic tests in response to
                    <abbrev>FDA</abbrev> demands, prompting more media questions than ever before on
                the maintenance and use of <abbrev>DNA</abbrev> databases. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.9-mmz_dqr_lr">Likewise, many have questioned the
            legitimacy of the <abbrev>CODIS</abbrev> maintenance of <abbrev>DNA</abbrev> profiles.
            The <abbrev>ACLU</abbrev>, for example, has noted the possibility of <quote>function
                creep</quote> in the maintenance of a government DNA database which could lead our
            country down a slippery slope towards a <quote>brave new world</quote> where private
            genetic information could be collected and used in abusive, discriminating manners. </para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.9-bnz_dqr_lr">With the commercial surveillance of
                <orgname>23andMe</orgname> and government surveillance by the <abbrev>NSA</abbrev>
            at the forefront of media attention, it is possible we will see more attention turned to
            the legitimacy of the maintenance of the <abbrev>CODIS</abbrev> organizing system in the
            coming years. </para>
    </section>
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <section xml:id="section-12.10" label="12.10" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added">
        <title>Honolulu Rail Transit</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-12.10" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>case studies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>Honolulu Rail Transit</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <para role="CORE">By <personname><firstname>Carlo</firstname>
                <surname>Liquido</surname></personname>, December 2015</para>
        <formalpara role="CORE">
            <title>Overview.</title>
            <para>The Honolulu Rail Transit Project is an urban rail rapid transit system under
                construction in Honolulu on the island of O’ahu, Hawaii. Honolulu’s notoriously bad
                traffic has plagued locals and tourists for decades, and for almost as long,
                proposals to address the traffic problems and pay for the solution have been very
                contentious and political. Construction began in 2011 and is expected to finish in
                2019, but delays have been frequent.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara role="CORE">
            <title>What resources are being used?</title>
            <para>The new railway transit system under construction in O’ahu will run along the
                southwest region of the island spanning a total of 20 miles, from East Kapolei to
                Downtown Honolulu with a total of 21 stops strategically placed throughout. There
                are a number of ways in which one could scope this project. What are the cultural
                and political limitations? What are the environmental effects and resources that
                will be indirectly affected? What are the topographic constraints of a railway
                system in Hawaii? In terms of the scope of my analysis, however, the people—namely
                the things the organizing system is intended for—are the primary resources. The
                principle guiding the organizing system is to reduce traffic and make the traveling
                experience more efficient as a whole.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <sidebar xml:id="sidebar-Oahu-1">
            <?dbhtml sidebar-width="50%"?>
            <?dbhtml float-type="right"?>
            <?dbfo sidebar-width="40%"?>
            <?dbfo float-type="outside"?>
            <title>O'ahu Traffic</title>
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="Pictures/11.10-Honolulu-a.png" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                        <phrase role="ALT descriptive">Infographic shows map of the island of O'ahu,
                            Hawaii, overlaid with markers to indicate traffic density. </phrase>
                    </textobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ydq_csz_nw"><phrase role="caption">O’ahu
                                traffic is usually congested, especially in and around Honolulu on
                                the south and southeast sides of the island</phrase></para>
                        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-zdq_csz_nw"><phrase role="credit">(<link
                                    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                    xlink:href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/telemax/3210740644/in/set-72157612806869067"
                                    >Hawaii Dep. of Economic Development and Tourism</link>. <link
                                    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                    xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/"
                                    >CC-BY-2.0</link>.)</phrase>
                        </para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
        </sidebar>
        <formalpara role="CORE">
            <title>Why are the resources organized?</title>
            <para>The guiding principle behind the organizing system of a rail transit system is to
                reduce traffic and make commuting more efficient. According to the
                    <orgname>Department of Business, Economic Development and Tourism</orgname>, the
                amount of traffic on almost every major highway on O’ahu has increased from
                2012-2014. Moreover, the dearth of job creation on other parts of the island, namely
                the west side, has focused traffic into and out of downtown Honolulu, as shown in
                the first map. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para xml:id="para-vwy_2zv_nw">This skewed traffic pattern, limited real estate, and
            inflexible road infrastructure has necessitated an above-ground railway system linking
            the west side of O’ahu with the burgeoning downtown area of Honolulu. This new
            organizing system seeks to rebalance the traffic system by reorganizing its resources,
            that is, by taking drivers and bus commuters off the road and onto the rail. O’ahu has
            only three major freeways, the H1, H2, and H3. The freeway H2 bottlenecks from the west
            into H1. Drivers and bus commuters are organized in such a way that peak hours of
            traffic are unavoidable. The new transit will conceivably provide an additional layer of
            organization to the currently </para>
        <formalpara role="CORE">
            <title>How much are the resources organized?</title>
            <para>There are 21 planned stations that run along the 20-mile span of track. The train
                stations are arranged to serve as many people as possible by concentrating them in
                the most densely populated areas.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <sidebar xml:id="sidebar-Oahu-2">
            <?dbhtml sidebar-width="50%"?>
            <?dbhtml float-type="left"?>
            <?dbfo sidebar-width="50%"?>
            <?dbfo float-type="inside"?>
            <title>Population Density</title>
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="Pictures/11.10-Honolulu-b.png" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                        <phrase role="ALT descriptive">Infographic shows map of the island of O'ahu,
                            Hawaii, where darker areas represent high-density tracts while lighter
                            areas represent low-density tracts.</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-e3s_msz_nw"><phrase role="caption"
                                >Population in Honolulu area is highly concentrated in lowland
                                areas.</phrase></para>
                        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-f3s_msz_nw"><phrase role="credit">(<link
                                    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                    xlink:href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/telemax/3210740644/in/set-72157612806869067"
                                    >Hawaii Dep. of Economic Development and Tourism</link>. <link
                                    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                    xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/"
                                    >CC-BY-2.0</link>.)</phrase>
                        </para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
        </sidebar>
        <para xml:id="para-fgk_gzv_nw">Darker areas represent high-density tracts while lighter
            areas represent low-density tracts. The densely-populated stretch from Keahi Lagoon to
            Honolulu Downtown, also has the highest density of traffic. It makes sense that this
            portion of the rail system constitutes almost half the number of total stops in just a
            quarter of the total mileage.</para>
        <sidebar xml:id="sidebar-Oahu-3">
            <?dbhtml sidebar-width="50%"?>
            <?dbhtml float-type="right"?>
            <?dbfo sidebar-width="50%"?>
            <?dbfo float-type="outside"?>
            <title>Honolulu Area Income per Household</title>
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="Pictures/11.10-Honolulu-c.png" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                        <phrase role="ALT descriptive">Infographic shows map of the island of O'ahu,
                            Hawaii. </phrase>
                    </textobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-h3q_4sz_nw"><phrase role="caption"
                                >Household income is lowest in the most densely populated
                                areas.</phrase></para>
                        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-i3q_4sz_nw"><phrase role="credit">(Hawaii
                                Dep. of Economic Development and Tourism. <link
                                    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                    xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/"
                                    >CC-BY-2.0</link>.)</phrase>
                        </para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
        </sidebar>
        <para xml:id="para-ob1_hzv_nw">Income per household also plays a vital role in how these
            stops were selected. The rail transit system predominately runs along areas of
            low-income neighborhoods (tan and brown indicates low income per household, while green
            indicates high income per household). This design principle embodies an assumption that
            people with lower incomes are more likely to rely on public transit.</para>
        <formalpara role="CORE">
            <title>When are the resources organized?</title>
            <para>As with any construction project of this magnitude, the organizing system was
                planned in detail before construction—down to the number of pillars, the amount of
                concrete, the imported steel for rail cars, etc. However, after construction
                excavation revealed ancient burial sites, the Native Hawaiian community demanded
                many changes to the project. The number of stops has remained the same but the route
                has changed dramatically.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara role="CORE">
            <title>How or by whom is it being organized?</title>
            <para>There are a number of interested parties with varying degrees of power. At the
                forefront, the government—that is, the State of Hawaii—makes the final decision.
                However, the people of Hawaii directly influence their decisions.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para xml:id="para-mwx_3zv_nw">The protection of cultural resources, practices, and beliefs
            is important in Hawaii, both as a matter of law and of culture. Private archeology
            firms, state officials, and cultural descendants work together to reduce and mitigate
            impacts to archaeologically significant properties. The <orgname>Oahu Island Burial
                Council</orgname>, for instance, is a state council created to help protect
                <foreignphrase>iwi kupuna</foreignphrase> (ancestral bones). It stresses the
            importance of consulting recognized lineal descendants before  any excavation for the
            rail project is carried out.</para>
        <formalpara role="CORE">
            <title>Where is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The <quote>where</quote> component of the organizing system is not as important
                for the scope of this analysis as other design questions. However, the physical
                nature of the project highly constrains how the system can be organized. The
                volcanic origin of O’ahu, does not allow for a below-ground rail system. The limited
                real estate, similarly, does not allow for a ground-level system. The sharp and
                steep volcanic ridges that cut across the island are barriers that limit where the
                rail system might go.</para>
        </formalpara>
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-12.11" label="12.11">
        <title>The Antikythera Mechanism</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-12.11" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>case studies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>Antikythera Mechanism</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm zone="section-12.11">
                    <primary>Antikythera Mechanism</primary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.11-skg_gqr_lr">By
                    <personname><firstname>Murray</firstname>
                <surname>Maloney</surname></personname>, <date>2 March 2014</date>.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Overview.</title>
            <para>In <date>1900</date>, a strange looking mechanical device was recovered from a
                shipwreck off of the island of Antikythera, Greece. Only in the <date>1970s</date>
                was it determined that the device was an ancient mechanical computer that performed
                astronomical calculations; it had a manual crank control with a rate of one turn per
                day, forward or backward in time; its user interface presented calendrical, solar,
                lunar, and planetary positions.<superscript>1</superscript></para>
            
        </formalpara>
        <sidebar xml:id="sidebar-12.11-Antikythera-Exhibit">
            <?dbhtml sidebar-width="50%"?>
            <?dbhtml float-type="right"?>
            <?dbfo sidebar-width="48%"?>
            <?dbfo float-type="outside"?>
            <title>The Antikythera Mechanism</title>
            <info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-12.11-Antikythera-Exhibit" condition="print" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>sidebar</primary>
                        <secondary>Antikythera Mechanism</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-12.11-Antikythera-Exhibit">
                        <primary>Antikythera Mechanism</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>
            <informalfigure xml:id="PICTURE-12.11-AntikytheraWhole">
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="Pictures/11.11-Antikythera-Exhibit.jpeg" format="JPEG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                        <phrase role="ALT descriptive">Photo of The Antikythera Mechanism exhibit at
                            the National Archeological Museum of Athens. Grecian urns are on display
                            in the background. </phrase>
                    </textobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.11-s4g_gqr_lr"><phrase role="caption"
                                >The <hardware>Antikythera Mechanism</hardware> exhibit at the
                                    <orgname>National Archaeological Museum of
                                Athens</orgname>.</phrase></para>
                        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.11-hpg_gqr_lr"><phrase role="credit"
                                    >(<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                    xlink:href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/telemax/3210740644/in/set-72157612806869067"
                                    >Photo by Tilemahos Efthimiadis</link>. <link
                                    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                    xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/"
                                    >CC-BY-2.0</link> license.)</phrase>
                        </para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
        </sidebar>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.11-ing_gqr_lr">The Antikythera Mechanism persists
            through time as a collection of artifacts and a model of intellectual achievement.
            Thought to have been constructed by
                <personname><surname>Archimedes</surname></personname> at Syracuse or by
                    <personname><surname>Posidonius</surname></personname> at Rhodes, the mechanism
            was recovered from a ship wreck near the Greek island of Antikythera in
                <date>1900-1</date>. The significance of the find only began to become apparent in
            the <date>1970s</date> when researchers applied modern scanning
                technology.<superscript>2</superscript></para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <?need 2.5cm ?>
            <title>What is being organized?</title>
            <para>The Antikythera Mechanism was an arrangement of resource descriptions that
                represented a classical Alexandrian sol-lunar calendar, complete with an almanac of
                the positions of the sun, moon, known planets, and specific stars over time. The
                resource descriptions are represented simply by the measurements of the gears, and
                the corresponding information that is displayed on the front and rear panels, based
                on the position of those gears. These resource descriptions accounted for the range
                of known astronomical phenomena at the time.<superscript>3</superscript></para>
        </formalpara>
        <para xml:id="para-12.11-uqg_gqr_lr">The organization of the mechanism consists of a main
            solar gear connected to a hand crank and a collection of gear trains that ultimately
            control the rotation of pointers indicating the calendar, lunar position and phases, the
            position of the sun and of all the known planets, and the nearest eclipse. The mechanism
            was housed in a wood frame box with bronze panels whose physicality was obviously
            intrinsic to the use of the device; the panels the back door was inscribed with what
            seems to be a user’s guide.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-pzz_w4n_qw">The Antikythera Mechanism calculated the position of the moon
            by employing five gear trains to take into account the Saros, Metonic, Callipic, and
            Exeligmos cycles. Thus, it was able to predict the dates of solar and lunar
            eclipses.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-12.11-fqg_gqr_lr">Today, the Antikythera is a collection of the
            eighty-two fragments that have been recovered from the ship wreck and sea bed, twenty
            three of which are evidently inscribed. The fragments have been dated to about <date>70
                BCE</date> based on the coincident presence of some coins from Pergamum and Ephesus
            that were recovered in the <date>1970s</date>.</para>
        <?need 2.5cm ?>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Why is it being organized?</title>
            <para>From a purely pragmatic perspective, the Antikythera Mechanism was a relatively
                portable computational device. that would have been used to accurately reckon a very
                specific calendar system, and to predict the cycles of days, months, years, and
                saro, as well as lunations, eclipses, and Olympic games. It would be an invaluable
                tool for astronomers, mathematicians, civil engineers, and cartographers of the
                time. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para xml:id="para-12.11-utg_gqr_lr">From a philosophical perspective, the Antikythera
            Mechanism was built to prove that it could be done. It represents a fulfillment of
            Aristotelian thought. Through the ages, the lure of scientific answers to the
            mathematical riddles presented among the patterns in the heavens has challenged our
            burgeoning intellects. The Antikythera Mechanism realized then-modern thinking on
            mathematics, engineering, astronomy and calendrical calculation in a portable mechanical
            computational device.<superscript>4</superscript></para>
        <?need 2.5cm ?>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How much is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Some of the major fragments are on display at the <orgname>National Archaeological
                    Museum of Athens</orgname>; the others are stored.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <sidebar>
            <?dbhtml sidebar-width="50%"?>
            <?dbhtml float-type="left"?>
            <?dbfo sidebar-width="30%"?>
            <?dbfo float-type="inside"?>
            <title>The Gears</title>
            <info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-12.11-Antikythera-Model" condition="print"
                        userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>sidebar</primary>
                        <secondary>Antikythera gears</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-12.11-Antikythera-Model">
                        <primary>Antikythera gears</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>
            <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata format="JPEG" fileref="Pictures/11.11-Antkythera-Gears.jpg"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                        <phrase role="ALT descriptive">Arrangement of gears.</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-nx2_q35_lw"><phrase role="caption">Gear
                                arrangement.</phrase></para>
                        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ox2_q35_lw"><phrase role="credit">(Wiki
                                Commons.)</phrase>
                        </para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
        </sidebar>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.11-lwg_gqr_lr">The Antikythera Mechanism is reported
            to have had about thirty gears within a frame whose size was less than the volume of a
            large book. The level of miniaturization and the precision of fabrication was not
            thereafter seen until the next millennium. The engineering and machining would have
            required trial models, accurate plans, and custom tooling. There have been various
            modern attempts to re-create the Antikythera Mechanism, or at least to re-create the
            model it seems to have manifested.<superscript>5</superscript></para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>When is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The person who operates the mechanism turns a hand-operated crank to establish a
                date, or contra-wise confirms the current date by taking sightings and comparing
                with the dial settings. The front face offers a solar-lunar calendar dial, a
                tropical zodiac dial, and an almanac dial with rising and setting times of various
                stars. The rear panel offers dials representing the five lunar cycles.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <sidebar xml:id="sidebar-12.11-Antikythera-Model">
            <?dbhtml sidebar-width="50%"?>
            <?dbhtml float-type="right"?>
            <?dbfo sidebar-width="48%"?>
            <?dbfo float-type="outside"?>
            <title>The Antikythera Mechanism</title>
            <info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-12.11-Antikythera-Model" condition="print"
                        userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>sidebar</primary>
                        <secondary>Antikythera Mechanism</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-12.11-Antikythera-Model">
                        <primary>Antikythera Mechanism</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>
            <informalfigure xml:id="PICTURE-12.11-Antikythera-Model">
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="Pictures/11.11-Antikythera-Model.jpeg" format="JPEG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                        <phrase role="ALT descriptive">Photo of a display case containing a metallic
                            object with two sets of concentric circles inscribed on its face, and
                            dials akin to those of an analog clock or watch. Museums patrons in
                            background.</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.11-gsg_gqr_lr"><phrase role="caption"
                                >A recreation of the Antikythera Mechanism on display at the
                                    <orgname>National Archaeological Museum of
                                Athens</orgname>.</phrase></para>
                        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.11-qsg_gqr_lr"><phrase role="credit"
                                    >(<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                    xlink:href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/telemax/3471161471/in/set-72157612806869067"
                                    >Photo by Tilemahos Efthimiadis</link>. <link
                                    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                    xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/"
                                    >CC-BY-2.0</link> license.)</phrase>
                        </para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
        </sidebar>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.11-p1h_gqr_lr">The organization of the engineering
            data required to build, operate, and maintain the Antikythera Mechanism is staggering to
            imagine, yet it pales in comparison to the organization required to collect and archive
            astronomical sightings on clay tablets for hundreds of
                years.<superscript>6</superscript> (See the sidebar, <xref
                linkend="sidebar-Cuneiform-Pergamon"/>.)</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.11-ndh_gqr_lr">The organization of the fragments of
            the Antikythera Mechanism is in the hands of the Bronze Collection of the
                <orgname>National Archeological Museum in Athens</orgname>. </para>
        <?need 2.5cm ?>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How or by whom is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Ancient Chaldean, Greek, and Roman astronomers and engineers; modern divers,
                marine archaeologists, curators and researchers. In <date>1978</date>,
                        <personname><firstname>Jacques</firstname>
                    <surname>Cousteau</surname></personname> led an expedition to the sea bed and
                returned some historical artifacts, that, while unrelated to the Antikythera
                Mechanism itself, provide additional historical context and may help date the
                discovery.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para xml:id="para-cnh_ryv_lw"><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xlink:href="http://www.antikythera-mechanism.gr"> The Antikythera Mechanism Research
                Project</link> is a collaboration of  academic, industrial, and scientific
            researchers, who are applying some of the world's most advanced technology to study the
            capabilities and applications of the Antikythera Mechanism, as well as its historical
            context and significance.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Other considerations.</title>
            <para>From the perspective of one ship’s unlucky captain and crew, the Antikythera
                Mechanism was likely just a piece of cargo, although it may have accompanied an
                equally unlucky passenger carrying the world’s first computer to
                        <personname><surname>Caesar</surname></personname>’s court in Rome. It
                remains unknown how or why the device was aboard the ship or what fate befell it,
                but that is a story for researchers and historians to uncover in the fulness of
                time.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Notes:</title>
            <para xml:id="para-hpj_fwt_lw">The following notes relate to this case study.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para audience="CORE Computing" xml:id="para-owx_sxt_lw"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="para-owx_sxt_lw">
                                <primary>computing</primary>
                                <secondary>Ancient Computer</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>PBS aired <citetitle>Ancient Computer</citetitle> on <date>April 3,
                        2013</date>. The BBC aired <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/6191462.stm">Ancient
                        Moon ‘computer’ revisited</link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para audience="CORE Museums" xml:id="para-swq_cyt_lw"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="para-swq_cyt_lw">
                                <primary>museums</primary>
                                <secondary>Antikythera Mechanism Research Project</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.antikythera-mechanism.gr"> The Antikythera Mechanism
                        Research Project</link> recently published <citetitle>The Inscriptions of
                        the Antikythera Mechanism. 2016. </citetitle>Y. Bitsakis, M.G.Edmunds, A.
                    Jones, <foreignphrase>et alia</foreignphrase>  Almagest 7-1, May 2016</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para audience="CORE Philosophy" xml:id="para-fpz_jyt_lw"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="para-fpz_jyt_lw">
                                <primary>philosophy</primary>
                                <secondary>Cicero</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>Cicero wrote about a similar device, created by Archimedes, in <link
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.thelatinlibrary.com/cicero/repub1.shtml#21">M. Tvlli
                        Ciceronis de Republica Liber Primvs</link></para>
                <para audience="CORE Computing" xml:id="para-v5m_myt_lw"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="para-v5m_myt_lw">
                                <primary>computing</primary>
                                <secondary>calendar computer</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/1006146">Gears from the Greeks. The
                        Antikythera Mechanism: A Calendar Computer from ca. 80 B. C.</link> Derek de
                    Solla Price Transactions of the American Philosophical Society New Series, Vol.
                    64, No. 7 (1974), pp. 1-70</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para audience="CORE Philosophy" xml:id="para-m3g_syt_lw"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="para-m3g_syt_lw">
                                <primary>philosophy</primary>
                                <secondary>Aristotle</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><personname><surname>Aristotle</surname></personname>’s work on the
                    subject <citetitle pubwork="manuscript" linkend="Aristotle350BC">On the
                        Heavens</citetitle> (<date>c 350 BCE</date>) avers to the mathematical
                    symmetry and perfection in the travels of the spheres, envisioning cycles and
                    epicycles in motion.</para>
                <para audience="CORE Archives" xml:id="para-pnb_qyt_lw"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="para-pnb_qyt_lw">
                                <primary>archives</primary>
                                <secondary>astronomical observations</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>In <date>343 BCE</date>,
                        <personname><surname>Aristotle</surname></personname> was head of the
                    Macedonian Academy, where he tutored
                        <personname><surname>Alexander</surname></personname> and his future
                    general, <personname><surname>Ptolemy</surname>
                        <othername>Soter</othername></personname>. Following
                            <personname><surname>Alexander</surname></personname>'s conquest of
                    Babylon in <date>331 BCE</date>,  he ordered
                            <personname><surname>Kallisthenes</surname></personname> to organize the
                    translation of all historical astronomical observations, initiating the transfer
                    of the world's greatest collection of astronomical observations, dating back to
                    747 BCE. Within a year, <personname><surname>Callippus</surname></personname>
                    had developed a new calendar, designating the summer solstice of 330 BCE as an
                    epoch for astronomers and calendrical calculation. The Callipic cycle of 76
                    years less a day, equates to 27,759 days, and 940 lunations, is represented in
                    the gearing of the mechanism.</para>
                <para xml:id="para-m3g_syt_lwz" audience="CORE Philosophy"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="para-m3g_syt_lwz">
                                <primary>library science</primary>
                                <secondary>Alexandria</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><personname><surname>Ptolemy</surname></personname> established his
                    capital at Alexandria and founded a museum, spawning the need for a library, in
                    the Platonic style. His successors, through to Cleopatra, added to the papyrus
                    rolls. Mathematicians, astronomers, mechanical engineers, scientists; the most
                    famous thinkers of the ancient world studied in the halls of the Library at
                    Alexandria. Notable to us in this context are
                            <personname><surname>Euclid</surname></personname>,
                            <personname><surname>Archimedes</surname></personname>,
                            <personname><surname>Eratosthenes</surname></personname>,
                            <personname><surname>Hipparchus</surname></personname>,
                            <personname><surname>Aristarchus</surname></personname>, and
                            <personname><surname>Posidonius</surname></personname>. </para>
                <para audience="CORE Philosophy" xml:id="para-nwx_npv_lw">According to Pliny, the
                    calendar reform of <personname><firstname>Julius</firstname>
                        <othername>Caesar</othername></personname>, was assisted by
                            <personname><firstname>Cleopatra</firstname></personname>'s astronomer,
                            <personname><surname>Sosigenes</surname>
                        <lineage>of Alexandria</lineage></personname>, who <quote>brought the
                        separate years back into conformity with the course of the sun.</quote>
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para audience="CORE Archives" xml:id="para-ygl_wyt_lw"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="para-ygl_wyt_lw">
                                <primary>archives</primary>
                                <secondary>Lego Antikythera Mechanism</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>In <date>2010</date>, <personname><firstname>Andrew</firstname>
                        <surname>Carol</surname></personname> built a Lego model of the Antikythera
                    Mechanism on a dare. <personname><firstname>John</firstname>
                        <surname>Pavlus</surname></personname> wrote and directed a short film,
                        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://blog.smallmammal.com/post/2156532687/behind-the-scenes-lego-antikythera-mechanism"
                        >Behind the Scenes: Lego Antikythera Mechanism</link>.</para>
                <para audience="CORE Business" xml:id="para-ygl_wyt_lwy"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="para-ygl_wyt_lwy">
                                <primary>business</primary>
                                <secondary>Hublot</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><orgname>Hublot</orgname>, the Swiss maker of luxury time pieces, created
                    a special edition <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.hublot.com/en/news/the-hublot-antikythera-watch"
                        >Antikythera Watch</link>. Hublot is also sponsoring ongoing research. See
                        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://antikythera.whoi.edu">Return to Antikythera: A project of
                        the Hellenic Ministry of Culture and Sports with support from the Woods Hole
                        Oceanographic Institution</link></para>
                <para audience="CORE Computing" xml:id="para-ygl_wyt_lwx"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="para-ygl_wyt_lwx">
                                <primary>computing</primary>
                                <secondary>Antikythera simulation</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>A simulation of the Antikythera Mechanism is available as an <link
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="https://github.com/fivasim/Antikythera-Simulation">open source
                        application</link> on Github.</para>
                <para audience="CORE Museums" xml:id="para-ygl_wyt_lww"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="para-ygl_wyt_lww">
                                <primary>museums</primary>
                                <secondary>Antikythera</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.antikythera-mechanism.gr"> The Antikythera Mechanism
                        Research Project</link>  maintains a list of <link
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.antikythera-mechanism.gr/data/models/solid-models"
                        >Solid Models of the Antikythera Mechanism</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para audience="CORE Archives" xml:id="para-n52_2zt_lw"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="para-n52_2zt_lw">
                                <primary>archives</primary>
                                <secondary>astronomy</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>In his <citetitle pubwork="book">Almagest</citetitle>,
                            <personname><firstname>Claudius</firstname>
                        <surname>Ptolemy</surname></personname> marks the beginning of an epoch in
                    recorded time, 1 Thoth 1 Nabonassar, with the coincident occurrence of a solar
                    eclipse and the ascension of the Chaldean,
                            <personname><honorific>King</honorific>
                        <surname>Nabonassar</surname></personname> in <date>747 BCE</date>. (See the
                        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.staff.science.uu.nl/~gent0113/astro/almagestephemeris.htm"
                        >Almagest Ephemeris</link>.) Nabonassar’s calendar reform began a period of
                    seven hundred years of meticulous record keeping, indexing, summarizing, and
                    studying. The scientific study of astronomy based upon recorded observation is
                    thought to have begun with Nabonassar. When we talk about the discipline of
                    organizing, we can tip our hats to Nabonassar. </para>
                <para audience="CORE Archives" xml:id="para-ukm_yc5_lw"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="para-ukm_yc5_lw">
                                <primary>archives</primary>
                                <secondary>ecliose times</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>John M. Steele (2000). Observations and Predictions of Eclipse Times by
                    Early Astronomers. Kluwer Academic Publications. pp. 43–45.</para>
                <para audience="CORE Archives" xml:id="para-xwd_zc5_lw"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="para-xwd_zc5_lw">
                                <primary>museums</primary>
                                <secondary>astronomical diaries</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><orgname>The British Museum</orgname> stores the <quote>Babylonian
                        astronomical diaries,</quote> a highly systematized collection of ancient
                    cuneiform texts that record periodic astronomical events, commodity prices and
                    weather conditions over a period extending from <date>652 BCE</date> to the
                        <date>1st century BCE</date>.</para>
                <para audience="CORE Archives" xml:id="para-ztr_zc5_lw"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="para-ztr_zc5_lw">
                                <primary>museums</primary>
                                <secondary>Babylonia</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>Aaboe, Asger. <citetitle pubwork="book">The culture of Babylonia:
                        Babylonian mathematics, astrology, and astronomy.</citetitle> The Assyrian
                    and Babylonian Empires and other States of the Near East, from the Eighth to the
                    Sixth Centuries B.C.E Eds. John Boardman, I. E. S. Edwards, N. G. L. Hammond, E.
                    Sollberger and C. B. F. Walker. Cambridge University Press, (1991)</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Related Readings</title>
            <para>See <xref linkend="section-4.5"/></para>
        </formalpara>
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-12.12" label="12.12">
        <title>Autonomous Cars</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-12.12" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>case studies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>Autonomous Cars</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.12-i3d_hqr_lr">By
                    <personname><firstname>Jason</firstname>
                <surname>Danker</surname></personname>, <date>December 2015</date>.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Overview.</title>
            <para>Automation in cars is nothing new. Automatic transmissions and cruise control have
                been around since 1939 and 1958 respectively, but these systems serve to aid, rather
                than replace, human drivers. What is new is a near future potential for fully
                autonomous cars, cars that are capable of full operation without an attending human
                driver.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.12-pjd_hqr_lr">While other vehicles, such as light
            rail and monorail trains, have been capable of fully automatic operation since 1967,
            these vehicles have the luxury of operating in closed environments and only need to be
            able to respond to a defined set of inputs. Autonomous cars do not have this luxury. In
            operating “in the wild,” the systems guiding these cars may be forced to respond to any
            number of unanticipated situations. As the automation system cannot enumerate all
            possible situations, it must instead rely on continuous organization of its operating
            environment.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-jbx_nwy_pw">This is clearly a technical challenge, but it also raises
            ethical and legal issues. As autonomous cars act based on the organization of sensory
            inputs, the organizing systems are necessarily developed relative to ethical
            considerations, whether intentional or not. At the most basic level, the organizing
            system will direct the autonomous car in making decisions analogous to those posited in
            the trolley problem, a famous thought experiment in ethics that forces a choice between
            saving five endangered people or taking the life of an innocent person who had not been
            in danger. Beyond ethics, autonomous cars also raise legal questions: if an autonomous
            car crashes, who is liable for the damages?</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>What is being organized?</title>
            <para>An autonomous car will organize information about the car itself, the objects in
                its vicinity, and environmental conditions. The car must keep track of its
                movements, those of other objects, and the relative positions of itself and the
                other objects. It must organize this information within the environmental framework
                of lane markings, speed limits, road signs, traffic signals, weather and traffic
                conditions, and numerous other constraints. As autonomous cars become common, the
                cars will likely communicate with one another and this information will also need to
                be brought into the organizing system. The car will also need to organize, and
                likely prioritize, inputs from human occupants. Regardless of the exact
                implementation, the organizing system will necessarily limit what is worthy of
                organization: it is likely not possible, or desirable, to keep track of every insect
                in the vicinity of the car.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Why is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The car organizes its surroundings in order to safely navigate to a destination.
                While this is the primary interaction enabled by the organization, countless other
                interactions support this primary interaction. The supporting interactions fall into
                the two categories of prediction and reaction. The systems being developed by Google
                use the information that has been organized to predict what is most likely to happen
                next: <quote>It predicts that the cyclist will ride by and the pedestrian will cross
                    the street.</quote> The systems that have been launched by Tesla tend to be more
                reactionary: <quote>Side Collision Warning further enhances Model S’s active safety
                    capabilities by sensing range and alerting drivers to objects, such as cars,
                    that are too close to the side of Model S.</quote></para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How much is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The extent of organization varies based on the implementation. While Google uses
                on-board sensors and extremely detailed street maps to implement self-driving
                functionality, Tesla’s Autopilot relies on-board sensors and standard GPS data.
                While the exact extent of the organization is not publicly available information,
                Google has publicly stated <quote>the system is engineered to work hardest to avoid
                    vulnerable road users (think pedestrians and cyclists), then other vehicles on
                    the road, and lastly avoid things that don’t move.</quote> Given this, Google’s
                categories, and their hierarchy, appear to be defined by their vulnerability.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>When is it being organized?</title>
            <para>For information gathered by on-board sensors, organization takes place as objects
                enter and leave the vicinity of the autonomous car. The organization is ongoing as
                the car’s surrounding and environment are constantly changing. In addition to the
                sensor data, autonomous cars also rely on map data which is organized in advance.
                Google’s cars rely on specialized, highly detailed maps that are being developed as
                part of the self-driving car project and, as such, are unable to drive on roads that
                have not yet been mapped to the necessary level of detail. While Tesla’s Autopilot
                also relies on maps, it uses standard GPS maps and is not similarly
                restricted.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How or by whom is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The car’s computational processes are responsible for the organization. That said,
                the car is restricted to organizing within the organizing system implemented by the
                manufacturer. While Google and Tesla are two of the main companies in this space,
                many traditional automotive companies are also developing autonomous systems.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Where is it being organized?</title>
            <para xml:id="para-pql_gxy_pw">Except for map data, the organization takes place within
                the car’s onboard systems. The organization must take place in the car itself due to
                the potential catastrophic consequences of a lag in information flow. Additionally,
                ensuring all organization takes place within the car provides greater security: a
                self-contained car is less susceptible to attack than a network dependent
                one.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Other considerations.</title>
            <para>While it is likely that fully autonomous cars will be technologically feasible
                within a few years, the cars may still require human interactions for legal reasons.
                This is clearly seen in Tesla’s press release for Autopilot: <quote>The driver is
                    still responsible for, and ultimately in control of, the car.</quote> This
                human-in-the-loop design principle creates a legal buffer for autonomous car
                manufacturers by treating the <quote>driver</quote> as a <quote>liability
                    sponge</quote> or <quote>moral crumple zone.</quote> As articulated by
                        <personname><firstname>Madeleine</firstname>
                    <surname>Elish</surname></personname> and <personname><firstname>Tim</firstname>
                    <surname>Hwang</surname></personname>, <quote>the human in an autonomous system
                    may become simply a component—accidentally or intentionally—that is intended to
                    bear the brunt of the moral and legal penalties when the overall system
                    fails.</quote></para>
        </formalpara>
        <para xml:id="para-cwz_lxy_pw">While these issues will ultimately play out through a
            combination of court rulings and policy decisions, it is interesting to note that there
            is legal precedent that could either blame, or exonerate, the <quote>driver</quote> of
            an autonomous car. Drawing parallels to aviation automation, precedent suggests that the
            human <quote>driver</quote> will be held responsible for liability claims arising from
            the operation of the car. On the other hand, product liability law offers recourse for
            consumers when a company’s products fail. Many people have argued that this existing
            legal framework is sufficient to handle the liability issues brought up by autonomous
            vehicles.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-snq_mxy_pw">Regardless of the legal complexities that will arise from
            specific incidents, autonomous cars have great potential to reduce car crashes and
            improve overall road safety. The promise of the autonomous technology, even for
            partially autonomous systems, is so great that the National Highway Traffic Safety
            Administration is proposing updates to its safety ratings that will penalize
            manufacturers that don’t include autonomous technologies in their vehicles.</para>
        <!--
        <formalpara role="CORE"><title>Related Readings</title>
          <para>See <ulink
                url="http://DisciplineOfOrganizing.org">
                <uri>DisciplineOfOrganizing.org</uri></ulink></para></formalpara>
-->
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-12.13" label="12.13">
        <title>IP Addressing in the Global Internet</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-12.13" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>case studies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>IP Addressing in the Global Internet</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.13-yjp_3qr_lr">By
                    <personname><firstname>Andrew</firstname>
                <surname>McConachie</surname></personname>, <date>December 2013</date>.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Overview.</title>
            <para>Most people take for granted that the Internet just works. They connect their
                computer to the Internet, it gets an <abbrev>IP</abbrev> address, and they are able
                to communicate with a computer with a different <abbrev>IP</abbrev> address on the
                other side of the planet. How did their computer get the correct <abbrev>IP</abbrev>
                address? How does any computer or router get the correct <abbrev>IP</abbrev>
                address? How did the routers and other computers on the Internet get their
                    <abbrev>IP</abbrev> addresses? Who decides which computers and which routers get
                which <abbrev>IP</abbrev> addresses? </para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>What is being organized?</title>
            <para>At their simplest, an <abbrev>IPv4</abbrev> address is a 32-bit series of 0′s and
                1′s. They are resources that are born-digital, as they have no canonical physical
                representation. Their digital canonical representation, with which we have all
                become familiar, is called the <quote>dotted quad</quote> format and is 4 numbers
                between 0-255 separated with dots. For example, 169.229.216.200 is the
                    <abbrev>IPv4</abbrev> address for <uri>www.berkeley.edu</uri>. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.13-tlp_3qr_lr">Not all <abbrev>IP</abbrev> addresses
            are of equivalent classes. There are unicast, multicast, broadcast, and experimental
            IPv4 addresses, and unicast addresses can be either public or private. There are also
            two different versions of <abbrev>IP</abbrev> addresses currently in use on the
            Internet, <abbrev>IPv4</abbrev> and <abbrev>IPv6</abbrev>. We will focus on IPv4 unicast
            public <abbrev>IP</abbrev> addresses, since these are not only the most common, but also
            the most important. This is roughly the range of <abbrev>IP</abbrev> addresses from
            1.0.0.0 to 223.255.255.255, with some breaks in the middle for private
                <abbrev>IP</abbrev> address space.</para>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Why is it being organized?</title>
            <para><abbrev>IP</abbrev> addresses are the foundation of network connectivity and the
                Internet; they identify each device on a computer network and also serve as its
                address, so that routers and other devices can locate and communicate with it. You
                cannot get online without one. <abbrev>IP</abbrev> addresses can be represented into
                blocks, or subnetworks, using a prefix and a mask. For example, 169.229.216.0/24
                represents all <abbrev>IP</abbrev> addresses in the range of 169.229.216.1 –
                169.229.216.255. Internet routers do not have enough memory to hold routes for every
                individual <abbrev>IP</abbrev> address on the Internet. So by organizing the
                Internet into subnetworks based loosely on a hierarchical model, routers are able to
                determine the correct path for every destination in the network without actually
                storing every address in their memory. If the organization of <abbrev>IP</abbrev>
                addresses is not handled properly, Internet routers would exhaust their memory space
                and parts of the Internet would become unreachable.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How much is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Currently there is too much granularity in the global Internet routing table. For
                a router it takes the same amount of memory to store a subnetwork with 255
                    <abbrev>IP</abbrev> addresses as it does to store a subnetwork with 65536
                addresses. So if our main concern is to minimize memory usage in Internet routers,
                thereby lowering operator costs and increasing stability, we want as little
                granularity as possible in the Internet routing table. The problem is that many
                organizations use non-contiguous <abbrev>IP</abbrev> subnetworks that cannot be
                aggregated into larger subnetworks. This results in routers having to store many
                small subnetworks instead of fewer larger subnetworks, which will eventually lead to
                memory exhaustion in older routers and possible reachability issues. Currently the
                full Internet routing table is approaching 500,000 routes. Most network engineers
                expect problems once the routing table grows past 512,000 entries, since router
                memory limitations are always at bit boundaries.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>When is it being organized?</title>
            <para><abbrev>IP</abbrev> addresses are organized once someone configures one on a
                device or sets up a <citerefentry><refentrytitle>Dynamic Host Configuration
                        Protocol</refentrytitle><manvolnum>DHCP</manvolnum></citerefentry> server.
                If an organization exhausts their supply of free <abbrev>IP</abbrev> addresses. it
                will have to make a request to the upstream provider or
                        <citerefentry><refentrytitle>Regional Internet
                        Registry</refentrytitle><manvolnum>RIR</manvolnum></citerefentry> for more
                address space. In the early days of the Internet, large blocks of
                    <abbrev>IP</abbrev> addresses were given to organizations, but this led to many
                of the addresses in these blocks not being used. We are now reaching a point where
                we no longer have new addresses to assign to organizations. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.13-c4p_3qr_lr">Markets are now emerging for
            organizations to buy and sell <abbrev>IP</abbrev> addresses, and the organizations who
            have held on to large amounts of unused addressing space stand to make significant
            revenue from selling their unused space. When these organizations sell their unused
                <abbrev>IP</abbrev> address space, they will break up large allocations into smaller
            subnetworks, thereby increasing granularity and further accelerating the growth of the
            Internet routing table.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How or by whom is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The <citerefentry><refentrytitle>Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and
                        Numbers</refentrytitle><manvolnum>ICANN</manvolnum></citerefentry> is
                currently responsible for initial allocation of <abbrev>IP</abbrev> addresses. They
                allocate 8 blocks of <abbrev>IP</abbrev> addresses to <abbrev>RIR</abbrev>s, who are
                then responsible for distributing allocations to organizations that request them.
                These organizations can then allocate <abbrev>IP</abbrev> addresses to smaller
                organizations, thus forming a loose hierarchy of organizations, where each level
                lower in the hierarchy receives a subset of the <abbrev>IP</abbrev> address space
                from the organization above it. <abbrev>ICANN</abbrev> no longer has any /8 blocks
                of <abbrev>IP</abbrev> addresses left to allocate to <abbrev>RIR</abbrev>s. Once all
                of the <abbrev>RIR</abbrev>s have exhausted their last allocations from
                    <abbrev>ICANN</abbrev>, organizations will have to rely on secondary markets to
                increase their <abbrev>IP</abbrev> address space.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <note userlevel="Editor" xml:id="note-ch12-Editor-nk2_1cs_lr">
            <title>Editors' Note</title>
            <para xml:id="para-12.13-x4p_3qr_lr">Bob, Ian offers: <quote>is there a role for
                    computational agents that should be discussed here? is an individual user's
                    acquisition of an IP address (e.g., a home user connecting to his ISP) an act of
                    organizing or just an interaction?</quote></para>
            <para xml:id="para-12.13-kpp_3qr_lr">Relates to <quote>responsible for distributing
                    allocations to organizations that request them. These organizations can then
                    allocate</quote></para>
        </note>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Other Considerations.</title>
            <para>The world of <abbrev>IP</abbrev> addressing will soon get a lot more interesting.
                The introduction of <abbrev>IPv6</abbrev> as a replacement for <abbrev>IPv4</abbrev>
                has been slow in coming and, while gathering momentum, continues at a snail’s pace.
                As organizations start purchasing <abbrev>IP</abbrev> addresses from one another, we
                should expect increased granularity and decreased stability in the Internet routing
                infrastructure. Whether or not normal Internet users notice will ultimately be
                determined by how well equipment vendors and engineers expediently address the
                coming problems.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <!--
        <formalpara role="CORE"><title>Related Readings</title>
          <para>See <ulink
                url="http://DisciplineOfOrganizing.org">
                <uri>DisciplineOfOrganizing.org</uri></ulink></para></formalpara>
-->
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-12.14" label="12.14" revision="3.0" revisionflag="added">
        <title>The Art Genome Project</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-12.14" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>case studies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>art genome project</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.14-uym_jqr_lr">By
                    <personname><firstname>David</firstname>
                <surname>Eicke</surname></personname>, <date>December 2014</date>.</para>
        <!--
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Overview.</title>
            <para>xxx</para>
        </formalpara>
-->
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>What is being organized?</title>
            <para>Artsy.net carries the ambitious mission of making <quote>all the world’s
                    art</quote> accessible to anyone with an Internet connection. This is not only
                challenging purely from a scale perspective, with the number of artworks in the
                world daunting even if it were not being incremented constantly, but it is also
                challenging in that <quote>art</quote> is a nebulous term. Creators of music and
                literature often refer to themselves and each other as <quote>artists.</quote> The
                same goes for dancers and other performers. Will their works be included? The
                current collection seems to be mostly visual art, with some architecture and design
                objects included.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para xml:id="para-qkg_pwm_qs">Artsy’s mission is to be carried out by their Art Genome
            Project, which is the organizational engine that powers their search and interactions.
            The name was inspired by Pandora’s project, as was their term for their organizing
            process: <quote>genoming.</quote> Genoming is not yet automated and still costly, so
            Artsy selects the art that is to be <quote>genomed</quote> carefully. Their first
            priority is the works featured in galleries with whom Artsy has contracts. Galleries pay
            to have their work organized and searchable on the site. Those works, then, must be
            genomed quickly in order to keep the company running. Artsy’s engine also takes in works
            from museums and other institutions who do not have contracts with them, but many of
            those institutions have image-rights concerns, and not all their artworks can be
            published. In other cases, the images of the works are simply too low-quality to be
            displayed.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Why is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Why organize art? The simplest answer is to educate. That said, art has been being
                organized into movements and -isms for a very long time. The Getty Foundation even
                created an authoritative art vocabulary called the Categories for the Description of
                Works of Art a few decades ago. At first glance, Artsy seems to be reinventing the
                wheel. However, the organizing system Artsy uses is unique in that it facilitates a
                special kind of interaction with its body of published works.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para xml:id="para-n5q_qwm_qs">The way resources are organized on Artsy is a cross between a
            hierarchical structure and a graph structure. They have over 1,000 characteristics
            (which they call <quote>genes</quote>) to describe their resources. These
            characteristics can have to do with art movements, formal qualities, techniques,
            subject, etc. The emphasis here, however, is on relationships between works of art. For
            example, one of the genes Artsy uses is <quote>eye-contact,</quote> and if you have a
            photo taken last month where the subject is looking directly into the camera and an oil
            painting from hundreds of years ago where the subject’s eyes are looking at the painter,
            those two can be one click away from each other. No other organizing system could
            facilitate that sort of easy link between two such disparate works.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-zmq_rwm_qs">This free-flowing linkage between works enables the
                <quote>berry-picking</quote> model of knowledge seeking, where a user searching for
            something doesn’t necessarily have to know what he or she is searching for. A user could
            begin her exploration with only a vague notion that she enjoys this long-legged
            rhinoceros sculpture by Salvador Dali. She may not know what she likes about it, but she
            will see his other work there. Maybe she finds a painting she likes in the <quote>other
                works by Dali</quote> section, and she clicks on it. Then the characteristics of
            this painting are listed in the interface, and she is free to click on any one of them.
            She might click on <quote>Surrealism</quote> and find more works from that movement. She
            may click on <quote>waterscapes</quote> and find other oceanic imagery. She is free to
            explore and discover art in a self-directed way and free to discover what she likes and
            why she likes it. The director of Artsy’s Art Genome Project says the system was
            intended to parallel a professor who is adept at <quote>riffing</quote> on
            things.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How much is it being organized?</title>
            <para>As mentioned above, Artsy currently uses over 1,000 characteristics
                    (<quote>genes</quote>) to describe its resources. These characteristics can
                describe anything from the art’s form to the art’s subject to the technique used to
                create the art. Experts assign these genes to the artworks and then assign those
                genes a weight from 0 to 100, depending on the salience of the characteristic within
                the work. Aside from the genes, the art is described in terms of physical dimensions
                (how much space it takes up), whether it has been sold or not, its gallery, its
                price (if for sale), its creation date, and, of course, who created it. Having such
                a rich set of descriptions has allowed Artsy to create a public API for developers
                to use all of this information as they see fit.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>When is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Description of Artsy’s resources is an ongoing process. Their ingested collection
                of art is much larger than their published collection. Most of the artworks are
                waiting to be genomed, with some of them waiting for permissions or image-rights
                paperwork to process. Another factor in determining when something is organized is
                the signing of new contracts with galleries. Works from galleries with contracts
                have first priority, and Artsy experts genome those works as they come in.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para xml:id="para-dvt_5wm_qs">While these experts are assigning genes on a rolling basis,
            they are also drawing upon hundreds of years of art history scholarship when assigning
            them. For example, the Arsty experts did not come up with Dadaism as an organizational
            concept. So, in a way, some of these works were organized long ago.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How or by whom is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Artsy has a team of art historians and experts working to describe the resources
                that Artsy has ingested (and those that it will ingest). They have done some
                experiments with image-recognition software, but its descriptions are simply not
                rich enough to facilitate the sorts of interactions the organization is trying to
                facilitate. The strategy of employing experts has its obvious downsides, however. It
                does not scale well, and it is reminiscent of Yahoo’s early strategy of employing
                librarians to describe web content. There will also be inevitable biases in human
                resource description.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Other considerations.</title>
            <para>With such a grand ambition, one thing that may stand in Artsy’s way of becoming an
                authoritative organizing system in the art space is that they are for-profit. Even
                if they are able to avoid too much bias in the interest of revenue generation, the
                perception remains that they are less interested in classifying art for educational
                purposes and more interested in making money.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <!--
        <formalpara role="CORE"><title>Related Readings</title>
          <para>See <ulink
                url="http://DisciplineOfOrganizing.org">
                <uri>DisciplineOfOrganizing.org</uri></ulink></para></formalpara>
-->
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-12.15" label="12.15">
        <title>Making a Documentary Film</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-12.15" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>case studies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>knowledge</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.15-vdl_kqr_lr">By
                    <personname><firstname>Suhaib</firstname>
                <surname>Syed</surname></personname>, <date>December 2013</date>.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Overview.</title>
            <para>As part of a small crew, I was in pursuit of making a documentary film shedding
                light on the problems in the higher education system in India. We had traveled far
                and wide, capturing many thought-provoking stories, illuminating interviews, and
                shocking truths. Due to the relatively small crew and a tight schedule, we ended up
                with our raw footage being labeled in a generic format (MVI_1234 etc.). I, being the
                director, had the task of assisting the editor in renaming and reorganizing the
                files to make our lives easier, do justice to all the efforts that were put into
                capturing all the clips, and incorporate them in an impactful manner.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>What is being organized?</title>
            <para>The primary resources being organized were the video clips (digital, shot on
                    <abbrev>DSLR</abbrev>s) acquired during the shoot. In this context, they could
                be classified as passive resources having no real capability to produce any
                significant value on their own, and which had to be acted upon or interacted with to
                produce any effect. But the key problem here was to formulate usable resource
                descriptions based on the following resource properties:</para>
        </formalpara>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Intrinsic static</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.15-jfl_kqr_lr">Date and time of creation,
                        duration of the clip, type of external lighting used, camera used, lens
                        used, exposure, <abbrev>ISO</abbrev>, white balance, frame rate, compression
                        type</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Extrinsic static</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.15-zfl_kqr_lr">Shot sequence number
                        (assigned to each story element during story-boarding), shot movement type
                        (dolly, follow focus, zoom, macro, etc.)</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.15-hgl_kqr_lr">During this particular stage, the
            intrinsic and extrinsic dynamic properties did not play a large role in the resource
            descriptions. </para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.15-ugl_kqr_lr">We had done a lot of work on
            story-boarding and identified the right level of granularity so that we could capture
            each shot sequence separately, so we directly used the shot sequence number as an
            important part of the resource description. This helped us keeping our descriptions
            short and meaningful. </para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.15-ihl_kqr_lr">Additionally, we realized that the
            corresponding audio clips captured along with the video also had to be organized, but
            since the two were intricately linked to each other we decided to use the same name as
            the corresponding video clip, the only difference being the extension. We relied on the
            editing software to capture the intrinsic static properties of the audio files (e.g.,
            bit rate and compression type).</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Why is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Essentially, we were organizing these digital resources to find, identify, and
                select them so as to weave a powerful narrative enabling us to convey the truth in
                an impactful manner. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para xml:id="para-12.15-g3l_kqr_lr">Hence, the interactions were directly with the primary
            resource. </para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.15-s3l_kqr_lr">The interactions that had to be
            supported by our organization scheme involved:</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.15-z3l_kqr_lr">
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.15-njl_kqr_lr">Finding the clips related
                        to a particular story-board section </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.15-ujl_kqr_lr">Selecting the best set of
                        clips to be included in the film based on relevance to story, progression,
                        continuation and several other inter-connected factors </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.15-gkl_kqr_lr">Manipulating the clip
                        (i.e., color-correcting, white balancing, and stabilizing) to create an
                        aesthetic effect </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.15-tkl_kqr_lr">Matching the video of a
                        clip to corresponding audio recording </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.15-bll_kqr_lr">Adding the right background
                        score based on sentiment being portrayed in the clips and the progression of
                        the story </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.15-nll_kqr_lr">Providing subtitles in case
                        of a foreign language or incoherent speech </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How much is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Since the scope and size of our organizing system was relatively limited and all
                the resources were already available, we were able to make some bold decisions
                without causing a lot of problems. We formed a controlled, vertical vocabulary for
                resource description by deliberately choosing certain resource properties over
                others. Our main objective was to keep the description as short as possible and at
                the same time convey the most valuable information that would help us interact with
                the resources (i.e., the video clips). </para>
        </formalpara>
        <note userlevel="Editor" xml:id="note-ch12-Editor-uk2_1cs_lr">
            <title>Editors' Note</title>
            <para xml:id="para-12.15-iml_kqr_lr">Bob, Ian asks: what is meant by: <quote>We formed a
                    controlled, vertical vocabulary for resource description...</quote></para>
        </note>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.15-wml_kqr_lr">We could have easily opted for a date-
            and time-stamp based id and every resource in a collection (i.e., clips specific to one
            camera) would have a unique identifier, but we realized that our cameras already
            attached this information to the file along with the technical details like frame rate,
            aperture, shutter speed, <abbrev>ISO</abbrev>, and white balance, which our operating
            system and editing software could easily capture, display, and search through, hence, we
            decided not to use these details. </para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.15-dnl_kqr_lr">We also decided not to include
            important lighting condition properties (kino-flo, LeikoLite, etc.) and location,
            because the first frame in most of our clips consisted of the clap-board which contained
            all of this information, and our editing software showed all the video files as
            thumbnails using first frame of the video. </para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.15-qnl_kqr_lr">Thus we leveraged all of these to form
            a controlled vocabulary that placed the shot sequence number first, followed by the take
            number followed by camera identifier (e.g., camA, camB, etc.). For instance: 2A_1_camB. </para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.15-c4l_kqr_lr">However, we did realize that these
            decisions were specific to our OS and video editing software and hence lacked
            interoperability. </para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>When is it being organized?</title>
            <para>In our case, although we intended to organize the resources as soon as they were
                acquired, we failed and then came up with an organizing system after all the
                resources were acquired. We leveraged this fact to our benefit and formed a more
                specific description system.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How or by whom is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Ideally it is the role of the first assistant cinematographer
                (<abbrev>AC</abbrev>), even 2nd or 3rd <abbrev>AC</abbrev> (depending on the
                budget), to make sure all the file names are stored properly and all the cards
                properly backed up. But due to our limitations we (i.e., the director and
                cinematographer) collaborated to organize the set of raw footage.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Other considerations.</title>
            <para>One important consideration that we left out in the discussion was the need for
                certain people appearing in the documentary to have their identity hidden by means
                of facial blurring and voice modulation. Although we could not accommodate this
                interaction of identifying which clips had footage of people who did not want to
                reveal themselves, we could easily add the special effects over an entire sequence
                once all the clips were brought together.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <!--
        <formalpara audience="CORE"><title>Related Readings</title>
          <para>See <ulink
                url="http://DisciplineOfOrganizing.org">
                <uri>DisciplineOfOrganizing.org</uri></ulink></para></formalpara>
-->
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-12.16" label="12.16" revision="3.0" revisionflag="added">
        <title>The Dabbawalas of Mumbai</title>
        <subtitle>Indian Lunch Box System</subtitle>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-12.16" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>case studies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>Indian lunch box system</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.16-hdl_lqr_lr">By
                    <personname><firstname>Pratibha</firstname>
                <surname>Rathore</surname></personname>, <date>December 2014</date>.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Overview.</title>
            <para>The Mumbai dabbawala tiffin service is the source of much fascination from around
                the world, and I am no different: I worked in Mumbai for two years and used the
                services of dabbawalas to get my lunch box (called a <quote>dabba</quote>) delivered
                from home to my office, which was about 44 miles away. Without the use of any
                technology or digital resources, this organizing system has been coordinating the
                delivery of home-cooked lunches to thousands of Indian office workers for over a
                century, charging just a small fee of $3-7 per month. The community of dabbawalas
                has been able to create value for its customers by optimizing and standardizing the
                principles of its operations and devising an organizing system that is down to earth
                and human-centric.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>What is being organized?</title>
            <para>The primary resources in the dabbawala system are the dabbas that are delivered to
                respective customer’s offices and organized using a simple but effective
                color-coding system. The secondary resource is the workforce, consisting of
                5,000–6,000 people known as dabbawalas, who organize themselves and their supporting
                supply chain and logistics operations to deliver the dabbas to the right location
                and at the right time each day without failure. The dabbawala community, called the
                Mumbai Tiffin Box Suppliers Association (MTBSA), follows a flat organization
                structure, meaning the motivation to perform consistently is a matter of personal
                drive and accountability.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Why is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The primary reason people use the service of the dabbawalas is to eat a proper,
                home-prepared meal during lunch, a way to connect with their family while busy at
                work. The interactions supported by the dabbawala organizing system provide two
                significant benefits to the customers: managing their budgets while eating healthy,
                and leveraging time constraints. Most of the office-goers usually leave by 7 a.m. to
                commute from the suburbs of Mumbai, traveling south to the main commercial area of
                Mumbai and returning back home after 7 p.m. The railway network during the peak
                hours is jam-packed with commuters hanging onto the trains with one hand; therefore,
                carrying one’s lunch at that time is not feasible. Most of the commuters cannot
                afford to eat takeout every day, and eating on the roadside is unhealthy and
                unhygienic. In addition, catering to the diverse food habits and taste needs of
                employees is very difficult for office canteens to manage. Thankfully, the dabbawala
                system solves all these problems with 100 percent customer satisfaction by
                delivering to each employee his lunch filled with food prepared at his home.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How much is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The Mumbai lunch box system is a successful and a socially sustainable enterprise.
                The number of dabbas delivered per day to offices and back home is around 300,000;
                that means 600,000 transactions per day. Although the number of transactions is very
                large, each person handles a small subset of transactions at a time. The scope of
                the organizing system and the scale of operations pretty much remain consistent,
                with the addition or deletion of few dabbas every month. Most interestingly, despite
                the lack of computers, mobile technology, or any automated processes, a dabba goes
                astray only once every two months, making less than one mistake in every 6 million
                deliveries. Now that’s efficiency! The system is able to achieve consistency in its
                operations because of successful implementation of several organizing principles.
                Firstly, containers used to house the lunch boxes are of a standard shape and size.
                Second, the color coding done on the dabbas takes advantage of people's visual
                acuity, following a human-centric design approach. Third, the sequence of
                transactions to deliver each dabba from its source to destination and back to source
                is repeatable, predictable, systematic, and iterative in nature, enabling easy
                tracking and monitoring. Finally, governance within the community is achieved by
                instilling ethics, values, and principles in employees and by holding employees
                accountable at all times.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>When is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The interactions between dabbawalas to deliver the dabbas follow a <quote>hub and
                    spoke</quote> process model. During a dabba’s journey from kitchen to consumer,
                it is handled by between three and twelve different deliverymen. The typical day for
                a dabbawala begins at 9:30 a.m., and he spends about an hour collecting all the
                25–30 dabbas from the assigned set of homes in his designated area. The households
                are expected to have the lunch box ready when he arrives for collection. When he is
                done with collection, he goes to the local train station and gathers with the other
                dabbawalas of his area. Next, the dabbas are sorted in the order of stops on that
                rail line and handed off to the dabbawala who is responsible for that particular
                station for delivery to their final destination. At every departure station, the
                dabbas are passed out according to their next destinations. The same process is
                repeated when returning empty dabbas back to homes.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <figure xml:id="Figure-12.16-fig1">
            <title>Dabbawalla Delivery Process</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="Pictures/11.16-indian-lunch-box-1.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase role="ALT descriptive">This figure is a graphical flow chart that shows
                        the journey taken by different workers, called dabbawalas, to pick up
                        lunches, which are called <quote>dabbas,</quote> from the customer's
                        residence or caterer, deliver them to the customer's workplace, pick up the
                        empty lunchbox, and return the lunchbox to its original location. The chart
                        also shows the approximate time of each step, starting with the pickup
                        between 9:30-10:30AM. the delivery between 12:30-1:00 PM, and the return of
                        the lunchbox to the pickup location between 3:30-4:30 PM.</phrase>
                </textobject>
                <caption>
                    <para xml:id="para-b1w_mkn_qs">A model of the dabbawalla delivery process</para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How or by whom is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The key to this successful delivery management system is the color coding done on
                the dabbas. The dabbawalas use simple design measures such as signs, different
                colors, numbers, dashes, dots, letters, and simple symbols to indicate various
                parameters such as origination suburb, route to take, destination station, who is
                responsible, the street, building, floor, etc. As most of the dabbawals are
                illiterate, the choice of syntax for markings is done in such a way to ensure it is
                easy to understand and implement. The vocabulary used to implement and describe
                markings on the dabbas follows a standardized and self-descriptive process, thereby
                eliminating ambiguity and variability and making the organizing system more
                effective. Since only numbers and letters are used, the syntax for description of
                the primary resource (dabbas) is intentionally made to be independent of any local
                language, so that everyone can learn, understand, and process without any confusion,
                bias, or information overload.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <figure xml:id="Figure-12.16-fig2">
            <title>Dabba Routing Codes</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="Pictures/11.16-indian-lunch-box-2.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase role="ALT descriptive">This figure explains the graphical coding system
                        used on each <quote>dabba</quote> or lunchbox. Codes for the pickup station,
                        destination station, and destination addresses consist of simple and
                        standardized combinations of letters and numbers.</phrase>
                </textobject>
                <caption>
                    <para xml:id="para-jdz_pkn_qs">A breakdown of the coding system used to identify
                        and route a dabba.</para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para xml:id="para-y3l_kym_qs">At each stage of the process, only one part of this code
            needs to be read, which works as a signal and thus allows picking up the right dabbas
            very quickly. It is also particularly efficient for traceability, since any dabbawala
            seeing a dabba knows which path it has to take. In case a dabba is lost or forbidden
            somewhere, any dabbawala is able to put it back on the right track. There is no need for
            the structure of color coding to be more granular than described above, as dabbawalas
            know the collection areas by heart. Furthermore, the process of adding a new resource to
            the organizing system is straightforward and structured. If a new resource—that is, a
            new customer—is added to the system, the dabbawala will do the complete journey to check
            the address of delivery and coordinate with other colleagues in the community to see who
            has a free place in his crate to add one more dabba. Once the sequence of delivery has
            been established and all the necessary stops for exchange decided, the address on the
            dabba is marked and it becomes part of the whole system.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Other considerations.</title>
            <para>It would be interesting to know if this delivery model could be used by other
                cities as the problem of longer commute and need for homemade food for lunch by
                office workers is always there in major cities. In my view, standardization of
                operations and understanding cultural and regional biases can provide opportunities
                for other cities to implement this model, at the same time providing jobs to many
                semi-skilled workforces.</para>
        </formalpara>
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-12.17" label="12.17">
        <title>Managing Information About Data Center Resources</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-12.17" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>case studies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>data center</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.17-iwf_mqr_lr">By
                    <personname><firstname>Hassan</firstname>
                <surname>Jannah</surname></personname>, <date>December 2013</date>.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Overview.</title>
            <para>Nowadays, there is an app for almost everything! Yet, we show little or no regard
                to what happens behind our shiny little screen until something breaks down and our
                lives descend to near chaos. That is the conundrum of <abbrev>IT</abbrev> guys. The
                truth is that <abbrev>IT</abbrev> solutions are, in many cases, fragile things that
                need constant care. This is no easy task. In fact, most of the cost and effort
                involved in <abbrev>IT</abbrev> solutions is maintenance. A million things could go
                wrong. Words like <phrase remap="action">preventive maintenance</phrase>, <phrase
                    remap="action">service monitoring</phrase>, <phrase remap="action">business
                    continuity</phrase>, and <phrase remap="action">disaster recovery</phrase> are
                examples of the different activities done to maximize availability, and expedite
                troubleshooting. Everyone involved with these activities needs access to resources.
                Above all, they all need access to information.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>What is being organized?</title>
            <para><abbrev>IT</abbrev> data centers have both physical and digital resources.
                Physical resources include the <hardware>facility</hardware> (i.e.,
                    <hardware>building</hardware>), <hardware>utilities</hardware>,
                    <hardware>computer hardware</hardware> (e.g., <hardware>network
                    switches</hardware>, <hardware>cables</hardware>, <hardware>servers</hardware>,
                    <hardware>storage, </hardware>etc.), and, also <hardware>people</hardware>.
                Digital resources are much fuzzier to define. A simplistic approach could classify
                them into data and applications. Each category can be further sub-classified into an
                entire ontology. The complexity increases when you consider the great number of
                potential resource types that can be created by combining physical and digital
                resources. <phrase remap="action">Capturing, storing, and maintaining
                    information</phrase> about these resources is a big challenge. A lot of
                information can be retrieved from the resources themselves. Usually, each team
                responsible for supporting a certain group of resources would store information in
                spreadsheets and documents. More organized teams would use databases or knowledge
                management systems. More diligent organizations would have a central repository for
                everything. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.17-fyf_mqr_lr">What many fail to capture is the
            information about how all of these different clusters of resources are interconnected.
            That is often a much bigger and complex challenge. That information could be either
            buried deep in these systems (e.g., the user name used to run a certain service), or is
            stored in people’s brains. The added value of an organizing system for data about data
            center resources can be multiplied if effectively organized information about their
            interactions.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Why is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Running an <abbrev>IT</abbrev> data center is complex, resource intensive, and
                risky. Customers require around the clock availability of services with no room for
                failure. The consequences of such failures go beyond financial loss and customer
                dissatisfaction. They could affect people’s safety and, even, national security.
                Cyber threats have become a constant threat for <abbrev>IT</abbrev> service
                providers, especially those that host highly sensitive data or serve critical
                operations. People can survive if their emails were inaccessible for an hour.
                However, what are the ramifications of a total failure of the <abbrev>IT</abbrev>
                infrastructure of the <orgname>New York Stock Exchange</orgname>? What if the
                airport systems of <orgname>Heathrow airport</orgname> failed? These are some of the
                conditions that <abbrev>IT</abbrev> data center managers must work in. Furthermore,
                technology advances have created highly diverse, complex, and integrated solutions.
                New resources are introduced frequently as old resources are retired. These
                activities require careful planning and execution to prevent the intricate
                eco-system from crashing. Having all the information required to plan these
                activities would mitigate that risk. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.17-ozf_mqr_lr">Nevertheless, when something wrong does
            happen, having the required information is equally important to expedite fixing it. In
            fact, availability of information increases with the severity of the problem. How can
            you rebuild a system if you do not know how to connect its parts? How much are the
            resources organized? The granularity of the data required about data center resources
            varies between organizations and also between stakeholders of the same organization. The
            information can be classified into operational, and planning information. </para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How much is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Operational information is required for running day-to-day operations. These
                include information about resources and how they are interconnected. Many
                organizations put most of their focus on organizing operational information with
                high granularity. The granularity could be influenced by economic, political, an
                intellectual factors. Higher granularity means that more time and money are required
                to organize the information. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.17-n1g_mqr_lr">The level of granularity used to
            describe a resource type can be driven by the motives of the team leading the activity.
            For example, a hardware systems support team would invest more in building a robust
            organizing system for hardware systems and not focus on applications running on that
            hardware. Finally, the team’s intellectual abilities and knowledge would influence the
            granularity of the system. As the boundaries between physical and digital resources
            fade, system designers could face some challenging questions. For example, servers are,
            traditionally, considered hardware resources. However, many organization have switched
            to virtual servers running on big machines. In such a case, how would you define a
            server? Is it the big machine or the individual virtual servers? Is it a physical
            resource or a digital resource? If you have a standby clone of a virtual server, would
            you consider both to be the same entity or not? </para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.17-z1g_mqr_lr">Planning information is usually
            required to make business decisions and is usually less granular. This could include
            information about the purchase and maintenance costs, contracts, hardware life-times
            …etc. Managers and planners could use this information to better plan for business
            activities, manage operational and capital costs, and make strategic decisions about the
            services and products the data center offers.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>When is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Many data centers start building an organizing system of data about their
                resources based on existing resources. In such cases, building the system is the
                easy part. The real challenge is maintaining the information up-to-date in an
                ever-changing environment. Clear information life-cycle and change management
                processes are required in parallel with work processes to ensure information is
                updated.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How or by whom is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Based on the scope and level of granularity of the system, the number of resources
                could potentially be gargantuan. The organization must try to maximize the amount of
                information collected automatically using auto discovery <quote>agents</quote> to
                keep update information. Inevitably, other information, especially information
                describing interdependencies, will require human entry. The organization must have a
                clear and comprehensive governance framework that details the roles and
                responsibilities of different parties in adding, and maintaining information.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Other considerations.</title>
            <para>Most big companies in the past operated their own corporate data centers. Their
                organizing system might have a smaller scope. The emergence of global cloud service
                providers has extended the commoditization of <abbrev>IT</abbrev> products and
                services across the entire technology landscape; from the consumers all the way back
                to the servers that provide them. These providers will have a bigger scope due to
                the diversity and dynamic provisioning of their services.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <!--
        <formalpara role="CORE"><title>Related Readings</title>
          <para>See <ulink
                url="http://DisciplineOfOrganizing.org">
                <uri>DisciplineOfOrganizing.org</uri></ulink></para></formalpara>
-->
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-12.18" label="12.18">
        <title>Neuroscience Lab</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-12.18" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>case studies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>neuroscience lab</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.18-okf_nqr_lr">By
                    <personname><firstname>Colin</firstname>
                <surname>Gerber</surname></personname>, <date>December 2013</date>.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Overview.</title>
            <para>A neuroscience lab is doing Parkinson’s disease research in which they do
                experiments with rats. They use different types of rats, surgeries, and drugs for
                experiments and have to keep track of all this information for data analysis,
                publications, and lab inspectors.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.18-slf_nqr_lr">The existing organizing system was
            developed before personal computers were prevalent and has slowly evolved over time.
            However, much of the underlying structure of the system still has its roots in
            pre-computer concepts. In order to update the system to incorporate more modern
            technologies what are the changes to the resources, their descriptions, and the systems
            structure that need to be made?</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>What is being organized?</title>
            <para>Resources in the current organizing system include rats, surgeries, experiments,
                drugs, and data recorded from the experiments. There are some other resources that
                could be incorporated into the organizing system. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <sidebar xml:id="sidebar-12.18-Rats">
            <?dbfo sidebar-width="50%"?>
            <?dbfo float-type="outside"?>
            <title>Neuroscience Research Equipment</title>
            <info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-12.18-Rats">
                        <primary>lab</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>
            <?dbhtml sidebar-width="50%"?>
            <?dbhtml float-type="right"?>
            <informalfigure xml:id="PICTURE-12.18-Rats">
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="Pictures/11.18-Rats.jpg" format="JPG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                        <phrase role="ALT descriptive">Equipment for surgical research on rats in a
                            laboratory, including a frame for securing the animal during surgery and
                            a rack of devices that record and process brainwave signals, is
                            pictured.</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.18-vmf_nqr_lr"><phrase role="caption"
                                >Physical resources in the author's lab are arranged to facilitate
                                the precise accuracy of interactions required in medical research.
                                In this photo, an array of amplifiers and filters for processing and
                                recording rats' brainwave signals (left) is installed in a vertical
                                rack that can be located close to the equipment used to perform
                                surgeries.</phrase></para>
                        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.18-cnf_nqr_lr"><phrase role="credit"
                                >(Photo by <personname><firstname>Colin</firstname>
                                    <surname>Gerber</surname></personname>. Used with
                                permission.)</phrase></para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
        </sidebar>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.18-lnf_nqr_lr">One such new resource is surgery
            techniques. Surgery techniques have historically been passed down by the master
            apprentice method and information was largely tacit knowledge that was held by the
            researchers performing the surgeries and not explicitly in the system. This was done
            because it is inherently difficult to store the intricacies of surgery in text and even
            more difficult for a new researcher to learn how to perform the surgery from textual
            information. The ability to store and annotate multimedia changes this however. It is
            now possible to make instructional videos for each type of surgery, add resource
            descriptions to the video file and store it in the organizing system. </para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.18-c4f_nqr_lr">There is also a resource that is
            treated as one resource through its entire lifetime when it may actually be two. When
            rats are originally brought into the organizing system they are treated as a
            manifestation of the rat resource type. Meaning the rats are interchangeable, you can
            use any rat from that group in your surgery. Once the surgery has been performed the rat
            is modified into a new resource instance. The specific rat the surgery was performed on
            now has a new set of resource descriptions.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Why is it being organized?</title>
            <para>Is the main purpose of the organization system to make sure the correct rats are
                used in each different experiment? Or is it to make sure the records are kept up to
                date for the lab inspectors? It could also be making data analysis and paper writing
                more efficient. These decisions will affect how many different types of resource
                descriptions are required and the granularity needed for those descriptions. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.18-u4f_nqr_lr">This system is just one of many
            organizing systems within a lab so deciding the scope and interactions it will have with
            the other organizing systems is very important. One important decision is if the system
            will support the training of new members of the lab or not. Having resources such as
            video recording of surgeries and experiments could enable teaching interactions for new
            researchers. But there are many other aspects of training a new researcher must go
            through, should these also be included in the organizing system? If so, it would make
            the system much more complex and expand the scope of the organizing system outside of
            surgeries and experiments but would keep all of the teaching resource in one system. </para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.18-npf_nqr_lr">Another option would be to have a
            separate organizing system that is responsible for training material which is able to
            interact with the multimedia in the system that are relevant to training. This does not
            expand the scope of the system but would make the maintenance of it more difficult. Each
            time a surgery technique or experiment is changed two systems would have to be updated
            to take the changes into account.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How much is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The system is accessed by many types of users, each requiring a different type of
                interaction. The researchers need to search for the correct rat and surgery
                technique. The lab inspector needs to check for drug logs and make sure all the
                surgery methods and equipment are up to date. The principal investigator needs to
                see an overview of progress on projects. </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.18-hqf_nqr_lr">Currently the system is organized in
            hierarchical categories where the top-level categories are surgery and experiments. This
            organization makes it easy to retrieve specific resources. However, the interactions
            normally performed with the system use resources from both sub-trees, which makes the
            hierarchical approach less than optimal. </para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-12.18-rqf_nqr_lr">A faceted classification approach could
            work well to enable these interactions. The facets would incorporate the original
            categories of surgery and experiments but also add facets for each common type of
            interaction. In this case different resource descriptions of the same resource will
            often be classified into different facets. These resource descriptions will often act as
            resources themselves. For example, a lab inspector is interested in retrieving the
            expiration date and times a drug was used in surgery, not the drug itself.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>When is it being organized?</title>
            <para>In a neuroscience lab resource descriptions are often lost if they are not
                recorded at the time they are measured. For example, if a rat is weighed to
                calculate the correct dosage of a drug, both the dosage and the weight should be
                entered into the system. If the weight is not entered at the time of measurement it
                would be impossible to weigh the rat later and get the same result (as the rat
                changes weight over time.) This is a common problem, so as a rule all resources and
                descriptions should be entered into the system at the time they are acquired.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How or by whom is it being organized?</title>
            <para>The researchers working in the lab do all of the organizing. They are the ones
                creating new resources, descriptions and have the most knowledge about the resources
                and how they relate to each other.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Other considerations.</title>
            <para>Changing the system and entering all of the data at the time of measurement will
                initially cause more work for the researchers but will result in more accuracy for
                the interactions supported by the system and less retrieval work during data
                analysis and paper writing.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    </section>
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section label="12.19" revision="3.0" revisionflag="added" xml:id="section-12.19">
        <title>A Nonprofit Book Publisher</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-12.19" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>case studies</secondary>
                    <tertiary>nonprofit book publisher</tertiary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-vwp_mxm_qs">By <personname><firstname>Emily</firstname>
                <surname>Paul</surname></personname>, <date>December 2014</date>.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Overview.</title>
            <para xml:id="para-wwp_mxm_qs">The New Press, a nonprofit book publisher with
                approximately 1,000 published titles, roughly 800 of which are actively in print and
                featured on the website, updated its book categories for use on <link
                    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://thenewpress.com"
                    >thenewpress.com</link> as part of a website redesign. Rather than fully
                adhering to an established book classification system, such as BISAC, which is
                commonly used in book retail, The New Press developed its own classification system.
                In addition to the standard goal of allowing readers to browse categories, this
                classification system is designed to represent the press’s focus and mission. The
                New Press classification system employs a mix of principles and levels of
                granularity while incorporating some elements of the institutional categories from
                BISAC.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-xwp_mxm_qs">In order to gain some insight into how these
            dual goals affect usability, I ran user tests on a mockup of the website with the
            proposed categories. I conducted a think-aloud exercise in which the users verbalized
            their thoughts as they browsed through the categories and subcategories. I then asked
            the users to walk through where they would go for a particular book in response to a
            prompt from me that included the book’s title, subtitle, and a brief description.
            Lastly, I asked the users about what their impressions were of The New Press after
            looking at the categories, whether they were confused by the categories, and which
            categories they would be interested in looking at if they visited the site.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>What is being organized?</title>
            <para xml:id="para-zwp_mxm_qs">The resource being organized is the digital presence of
                the books on thenewpress.com. The classification system is only used on The New
                Press website and is stored in a FileMaker database that pushes data to the website.
                There is already a dedicated website classification system that this new system
                builds on. It is worth noting that the book records in the database also contain
                BISAC categories. These are entered so that they can be sent out to distribution and
                bookseller feeds that require the industry-standard categories. The BISAC categories
                are institutional categories created by the Book Industry Standards Group. The BISAC
                system is designed to reflect the interests and understanding of general readers. As
                such, the BISAC categories are informed by cultural categories and also influence
                cultural categories because of their broad adoption in the book industry. In
                addition to using some institutional categories from BISAC and mainstream cultural
                categories, The New Press is using cultural categories from specific groups, namely
                academics and political progressives, to connect with specific readers.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Why is it being organized?</title>
            <para xml:id="para-axp_mxm_qs">The books are being categorized to facilitate browsing by
                readers and supporters on The New Press website. In addition to the primary browsing
                interaction, the categories are also being used as an opportunity to position The
                New Press and to convey a sense of its mission.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How much is it being organized?</title>
            <para xml:id="para-exp_mxm_qs">For the purposes of The New Press website, books can be
                placed in multiple categories and subcategories, but all books will have at least
                one category designation. Because The New Press is not concerned with the physical
                presentation of the resources, the books can be placed in as many categories as are
                relevant. In contrast, library and bookstore classifications need to satisfy the
                uniqueness principle, because the book can only be located in one physical
                location.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para xml:id="para-yfv_gzm_qs">Most of the categories are based on the subject matter of the
            books. A book’s subject matter is an intrinsic static property because it does not
            change once it is published. However, the categories used to describe this subject
            matter may change over time as new categories are added to the classification system and
            retroactively assigned to previously published books. The book subject categories can
            generally be thought of as extrinsic and static because the threshold for changing them
            is higher than it is for more dynamic properties such as Current Season, Next Season,
            and Bestsellers. These categories are also included on the site in a separate section
            and are all extrinsic, dynamic properties because they are based either on time or
            sales, rather than intrinsic properties of the books.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-fpc_3zm_qs">The New Press classification system includes hierarchical
            categories, though only the subjects in which the press publishes more extensively have
            subcategories. In areas for which there are more books, the organization can be more
            granular without creating a subcategory that contains only one or a few books.
            Additionally, the greater institutional knowledge of the subject area enables the staff
            to make more specific distinctions within the broader subject category. One of the
            questions I explored in my user testing was whether these differentiations are necessary
            to support users’ interactions with the books. If the users do not share the same level
            of knowledge in the subject it may not be useful, and may even diminish usability, to
            differentiate at the level of granularity provided by the subcategories.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-flg_3zm_qs">Even at the top category level, there is a range of
            granularity and also a range of principles embodied in the categories. For example,
            History and Immigration are both top-level categories, but Immigration covers a more
            specific group of topics than History does. Most categories are based on the subject of
            the books, but there are several top-level categories based on other principles. These
            include Graphic Nonfiction, which refers to format; Primary Source Documents, which
            refers to the source material; and Biography, which refers to the genre of the book but
            does not express anything about its subject matter beyond the fact that it is about
            someone’s life. Mixing category principles can be useful, particularly in a faceted
            system, which allows users to combine different categories to increase precision. In a
            faceted version of this system, a user could select Biography and Law in order to find
            biographies written about a judge or lawyer. Because books are assigned to all relevant
            categories in this system, this interaction is feasible at the logic level even though
            the current presentation does not allow it. If The New Press wanted to switch to a
            faceted presentation it would likely visually separate the categories into blocks based
            on the principles, so that users knew which facets they could pivot their searches on.
            This might include creating a genre section with Biography, Oral History, and Primary
            Source Documents as well as a geography section with the subcategories from
            World.</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>When is it being organized?</title>
            <para xml:id="para-fxp_mxm_qs">Once the updated categories are finalized, all previously
                published books will be reviewed and assigned to new categories as necessary. Going
                forward, new books will be categorized on a seasonal basis and new categories may
                occasionally be assigned to previously published books on an ad hoc basis (this
                could be due to previous oversight in not assigning the category, or to the creation
                of a new category or subcategory). This system is flexible because books can be
                assigned to all relevant categories, so the introduction of a new category does not
                mean that all previous assignments will need to be changed. The subcategories also
                allow for flexibility because if one of these categories becomes more important over
                time, it can be changed at the presentation layer to a top-level category with
                minimal effort.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>How or by whom is it being organized?</title>
            <para xml:id="para-gxp_mxm_qs">The sales, marketing, and inventory manager assigns the
                categories, with input from the editorial and marketing teams. From time to time
                other departments, such as fundraising or publicity, may suggest a new category or
                category assignment for consideration. The categories are assigned in a FileMaker
                database in which the categories can be selected from a list of existing categories
                and subcategories. The category assignments in the FileMaker database are pushed to
                the website along with other book data.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE">
            <title>Other considerations.</title>
            <para xml:id="para-hxp_mxm_qs">Creating a classification system that can be widely
                understood is difficult to do. In this case, simplifying the system would support
                The New Press’s goal of reaching a broad audience of readers. User testing revealed
                that the current category system may be hindering this because of issues with
                semantics, granularity, and structure. The structural issues are the most important
                to address because the inconsistent use of subcategories generated significant
                confusion during the user testing. By removing the subcategories and instead
                allowing expert users or those who know exactly what they are looking for to use
                search, the press could maximize the categories’ relevance for general readers. This
                could be strengthened by an emphasis on using relevant keywords in the book
                descriptions that support searching. Despite some initial surprise from the test
                users about certain unusual top-level categories, I would argue that after
                simplifying other aspects of the system, the press could successfully keep some of
                these in order to represent its publishing areas and connect with like-minded
                readers. For example, Immigration and Criminal Justice are not top-level BISAC
                categories, but are easily understood by general readers and serve to highlight
                these important areas for The New Press. Biases in classification systems are
                unavoidable. While this can be negative, particularly when the organizers are not
                aware of the biases, it can also be harnessed positively and used to communicate a
                sense of the organization and its values. This needs to be approached thoughtfully
                and carefully and tested on users to understand how people outside the organization
                will interact with the system.</para>
        </formalpara>
    </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- *****************************   TEMPLATE   ************************************ -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!--
    <section  id="section-12.xx" label="12.xx">
        <title>XXX</title>
        <info>
            <itermset><indexterm zone="section-12.xx">
                <primary>organizing system</primary>
                <secondary>case studies</secondary>
                <tertiary>XXX</tertiary>
            </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
        
        <para role="CORE">Contributed by: </para>
        
        <formalpara role="CORE"><title>OVERVIEW</title>
          <para></para></formalpara>
        <formalpara role="CORE"><title>What resources are being used?</title>
          <para></formalpara>
        </para>
        <formalpara role="CORE"><title>Why are the resources organized?</title>
          <para></formalpara>
        </para>
        <formalpara role="CORE"><title>How much are the resources organized?</title>
          <para></para></formalpara>
        <formalpara role="CORE"><title>When are the resources organized?</title>
          <para></para></formalpara>
        <formalpara role="CORE"><title>How or by whom is it being organized?</title>
          <para></para></formalpara>
        <formalpara role="CORE"><title>Other considerations</title>
          <para></para></formalpara>
        
    </section>
    
    -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
</chapter>
