<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.0 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="chapter-2n" label="2"
    audience="CORE">
    <title>Design Decisions in Organizing Systems</title>
    <info>
        <author>
            <personname><firstname>Robert</firstname><othername>J.</othername><surname>Glushko</surname></personname>
        </author>
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>organize</keyword>
            <keyword>organizing system</keyword>
            <keyword>discipline</keyword>
            <keyword>framework</keyword>
            <keyword>resource</keyword>
            <keyword>collection</keyword>
            <keyword>intentional arrangement</keyword>
            <keyword>agent</keyword>
            <keyword>description resource</keyword>
            <keyword>primary resource</keyword>
            <keyword>surrogate resource</keyword>
            <keyword>metadata</keyword>
        </keywordset>
        <itermset>
            <indexterm zone="chapter-2n">
                <primary>organizing system</primary>
                <secondary>design decisions</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm zone="chapter-2n">
                <primary>organizing system</primary>
                <secondary>what, why, where, when, how and by whom?</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm zone="chapter-2n">
                <primary>design decisions</primary>
            </indexterm>
        </itermset>
        
    </info>

    <!--              -->
    <!--              -->
    <section xml:id="section-2n.1" label="2.1">
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-z1d_tnr_lr"><phrase
                xml:id="statement-2n-ResourcesArrangedToEnable" role="statement">A set of resources
                is transformed by an organizing system when the resources are described or arranged
                to enable interactions with them.</phrase> Explicitly or by default, this requires
            many interdependent decisions about the identities of resources; their names,
            descriptions and other properties; the classes, relations, structures and collections in
            which they participate; and the people or technologies interacting with them.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-y2d_tnr_lr"><phrase
                xml:id="statement-2n-ConceptOfResource" role="statement">One important contribution
                of the idea of the organizing system is that it moves beyond the debate about the
                definitions of <quote>things,</quote>
                <quote>documents,</quote> and <quote>information,</quote> with the unifying concept
                of <glossterm linkend="gloss_resource"><quote>resource</quote></glossterm> while
                acknowledging that <quote role="interrogative">what is being organized</quote> is
                just one of the questions or dimensions that need to be considered.</phrase> These
            decisions are deeply intertwined, but it is easier to introduce them as if they were
            independent. </para>
        <?need 5cm ?>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-w3d_tnr_lr">We introduce six groups of design questions,
            itemizing the most important dimensions in each group:</para>
        <para xml:id="list-W5" audience="CORE">
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>What is being organized?</title>
                        <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative principle"
                            xml:id="para-bq4_myv_qv">What is the scope and scale of the domain? What
                            is the mixture of <hardware>physical things</hardware>, digital things,
                            and information about things in the organizing system? Is the organizing
                            system being designed to create a new resource collection, catalog an
                            existing and closed resource collection, or manage a collection in which
                            resources are continually added or deleted? Are the resources unique, or
                            are they interchangeable members of a category? Do they follow a
                            predictable <quote>life cycle</quote> with a <quote>useful life</quote>?
                                <phrase revision="4.0" revisionflag="added" audience="CORE DS">Does
                                the organizing system use the interaction resources created through
                                its use, or are these interaction resources extracted and aggregated
                                for use by another organizing system?</phrase>
                            <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref linkend="section-2n.2"
                                    xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase></para>
                    </formalpara>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Why is it being organized?</title>
                        <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative principle"
                            xml:id="para-cq4_myv_qv">What interactions or services will be
                            supported, and for whom? Are the uses and users known or unknown? Are
                            the users primarily people or computational processes? Does the
                            organizing system need to satisfy personal, social, or institutional
                            goals? <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref linkend="section-2n.3"
                                    xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase></para>
                    </formalpara>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>How much is it being organized?</title>
                        <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative principle"
                            xml:id="para-dq4_myv_qv">What is the extent, granularity, or
                            explicitness of description, classification, or relational structure
                            being imposed? What organizing principles guide the organization? Are
                            all resources organized to the same degree, or is the organization
                            sparse and non-uniform? <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref
                                    linkend="section-2n.4" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase></para>
                    </formalpara>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>When is it being organized?</title>
                        <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative principle"
                            xml:id="para-eq4_myv_qv">Is the organization imposed on resources when
                            they are created, when they become part of the collection, when
                            interactions occur with them, just in case, just in time, all the time?
                            Is any of this organizing mandated by law or shaped by industry
                            practices or cultural tradition? <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref
                                    linkend="section-2n.5" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase></para>
                    </formalpara>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>How or by whom, or by what computational processes, is it being
                            organized?</title>
                        <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative principle"
                            xml:id="para-fq4_myv_qv">Is the organization being performed by
                            individuals, by informal groups, by formal groups, by professionals, by
                            automated methods? Are the organizers also the users? Are there rules or
                            roles that govern the organizing activities of different individuals or
                            groups? <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref linkend="section-2n.6"
                                    xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase></para>
                    </formalpara>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Where is it being organized?</title>
                        <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative principle"
                            xml:id="para-gq4_myv_qv">Is the resource location constrained by design
                            or by regulation? Are the resources positioned in a static location? Are
                            the resources in transit or in motion? Does their location depend on
                            other parameters, such as time? <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref
                                    linkend="section-2n.7" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase></para>
                    </formalpara>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-hg2_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-hg2_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>tradeoffs</primary>
                        <secondary>imposed by requirements</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-hg2_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>constraints</primary>
                        <secondary>contextual</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>How well these decisions coalesce in an organizing system depends on the
            requirements and goals of its human and computational users, and on understanding the
            constraints and tradeoffs that any set of requirements and goals impose. How and when
            these constraints and tradeoffs are handled can depend on the legal, business, and
            technological contexts in which the organizing system is designed and deployed; on the
            relationship between the designers and users of the organizing system (who may be the
            same people or different ones); on the economic or emotional or societal purpose of the
            organizing system; and on numerous other design, deployment, and use factors.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-gk2_tnr_lr"><phrase xml:id="statement-2n-ClassifyByKind"
                role="statement">Classifying organizing systems according to the kind of resources
                they contain is the most obvious and traditional approach.</phrase> We can also
            classify organizing systems by their dominant purposes, by their intended user
            community, or other ways. <phrase xml:id="statement-2n-CategoryMismatch"
                role="statement">No single fixed set of categories is sufficient by itself to
                capture the commonalities and contrasts between organizing systems.</phrase></para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-b42_tnr_lr">We can augment the categorical view of
            organizing systems by thinking of them as existing in a multi-faceted or
            multi-dimensional design space in which we can consider many types of collections at the
            same time.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-fqh_tnr_lr">This <glossterm linkend="gloss_framework"
                >framework</glossterm> for describing and comparing organizing systems overcomes
            some of the biases and conservatism built into familiar categories like libraries,
            museums, and archives, while enabling us to describe them as design patterns that embody
            characteristic configurations of design choices. We can then use these patterns to
            support inter-disciplinary work that cuts across categories and applies knowledge about
            familiar domains to unfamiliar ones. <phrase xml:id="statement-dimensional-perspective"
                >A dimensional perspective makes it easier to translate between category- and
                discipline-specific vocabularies so that people from different disciplines can have
                mutually intelligible discussions about their organizing activities.</phrase> They
            might realize that they have much in common, and they might be working on similar or
            even the same problems.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-pvh_tnr_lr"><phrase>A faceted or dimensional perspective
                acknowledges the diversity of instances of collection types and provides a
                generative, forward-looking framework for describing hybrid types that do not
                cleanly fit into the familiar categories.</phrase>
            <phrase>Even though it might differ from the conventional categories on some dimensions,
                an organizing system can be designed and understood by its <firstterm
                    xml:id="first_family_resemblance" linkend="gloss_family_resemblance">family
                    resemblance</firstterm> on the basis of its similarities on other dimensions to
                a familiar type of resource collection.</phrase></para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ozh_tnr_lr">Thinking of organizing systems as points or
            regions in a design space makes it easier to invent new or more specialized types of
            collections and their associated interactions. If we think metaphorically of this design
            space as a map of organizing systems, the empty regions or <quote>white space</quote>
            between the densely-populated centers of the traditional categories represent organizing
            systems that do not yet exist. We can consider the properties of an organizing system
            that could occupy that white space and analyze the technology, process, or policy
            innovations that might be required to let us build it there. We can reason by analogy to
            identify and apply the principles used in one organizing system to understand or design
            others. <footnote xml:id="endnote-017" label="23" audience="LIS">
                <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-f23_tnr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-017">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>LIS</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-017" userlevel="Professional">
                                <primary>library science</primary>
                                <secondary>citations</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>Depending on which characteristics of <application>Google
                        Books</application> and libraries you think about, you might complete this
                    analogy with an animal theme park like <orgname>Sea World</orgname> (<link
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.seaworld.com/"
                        ><uri>http://www.seaworld.com/</uri></link>) or a private hunting reserve
                    that creates personalized <quote>big game</quote> hunts. Or maybe you can invent
                    something completely new.</para>
            </footnote></para>
    </section>
    <!--              -->
    <?dbfo clear ?>
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section label="2.2" xml:id="section-2n.2">
        <title>What Is Being Organized?</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-2n.2">
                    <primary>organizing</primary>
                    <secondary>what</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm zone="section-2n.2">
                    <primary>organizing</primary>
                    <secondary>identity</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm zone="section-2n.2">
                    <primary>identity</primary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <blockquote>
            <attribution>
                <citation xml:id="cite_Svenonius2000-1.3" linkend="Svenonius2000"> (Svenonius 2000,
                    p. 13) </citation></attribution>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ewj_tnr_lr"><emphasis><quote>What is difficult to
                        identify is difficult to describe and therefore difficult to
                        organize.</quote></emphasis>
            </para>
        </blockquote>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-a1k_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-a1k_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>SKU</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info><phrase xml:id="statement-2n-IdentifyBeforeOrganize" role="statement">Before we
                can begin to organize any resource we often need to identify it.</phrase> It might
            seem straightforward to devise an organizing system around <hardware>tangible
                resources</hardware>, but we must be careful not to assume what a resource is.
                <phrase xml:id="statement-thing" role="statement">In different situations, the same
                    <quote>thing</quote> can be treated as a unique item, one of many equivalent
                members of a broad category, or a component of an item rather than as an item on its
                own.</phrase> For example, in a museum collection, a <hardware>handmade, carved
                chess piece</hardware> might be a separately identified item, identified as part of
            a <hardware>set of carved chess pieces</hardware>, or treated as one of the 33
            unidentified components of an item identified as a chess set (including the board). When
            merchants assign a stock-keeping unit (<abbrev>SKU</abbrev>) to identify the things they
            sell, that <abbrev>SKU</abbrev> can be associated with a unique item, sets of items
            treated as equivalent for inventory or billing purposes, or intangible things like
            warranties.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="principle" xml:id="para-ydk_tnr_lr">You probably do not have
            explicit labels on the cabinets and drawers in your kitchen or clothes closet, but
            department stores and warehouses have <hardware>signs</hardware> in the aisles and on
            the shelves because of the larger number of things a store needs to organize. As a
            collection of resources grows, it often becomes necessary to identify each one
            explicitly; to create surrogates like bibliographic records or descriptions that
            distinguish one resource from another; and to create additional organizational
            mechanisms like <hardware>shelf labels</hardware>, <hardware>store
                directories</hardware>, <hardware>library card catalogs</hardware> and
                <hardware>indexes</hardware> that facilitate understanding the collection and
            locating the resources it contains. These organizational mechanisms often suggest or
            parallel the organizing principles used to organize the collection itself.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-whk_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-whk_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>location</primary>
                        <secondary>physical resource constraints</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>Organization mechanisms like <hardware>aisle signs</hardware>, store directories
            and library card catalogs are embedded in the same physical environment as the resources
            being organized. But when these mechanisms or surrogates are digitized, the new
            capabilities that they enable create design challenges. <phrase
                xml:id="principle-2n-DigitalMoreAbstract" role="statement principle">This is because
                a digital organizing system can be designed and operated according to more abstract
                and less constraining principles than an organizing system that only contains
                physical resources.</phrase>
            <phrase xml:id="statement-2n-PhysicalVsDigital" role="statement">A single physical
                resource can only be in one place at a time, and interactions with it are
                constrained by its size, location, and other properties. In contrast, digital copies
                and surrogates can exist in many places at once and enable searching, sorting, and
                other interactions with an efficiency and scale impossible for tangible
                things.</phrase>
        </para>
        <?need 6cm ?>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-qlk_tnr_lr"><phrase xml:id="statement-2n-UnitOfOrganization" role="statement">When the resources
                being organized consist of information content, deciding on the unit of organization
                is challenging because it might be necessary to look beyond physical properties and
                consider conceptual or intellectual equivalence.</phrase> A high school student told
            to study Shakespeare’s play <citetitle pubwork="manuscript" linkend="Shakespeare1623"
                >Macbeth</citetitle> might treat any printed copy or web version as equivalent, and
            might even try to outwit the teacher by watching a film adaptation of the play. To the
            student, all versions of <citetitle pubwork="manuscript" linkend="Shakespeare1623"
                >Macbeth</citetitle> seem to be the same resource, but librarians and scholars make
            much finer distinctions.<footnote xml:id="endnote-019" label="24" audience="LIS">
                <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-opk_tnr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-019">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>LIS</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-019">
                                <primary>FRBR</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-019">
                                <primary>library science</primary>
                                <secondary>FRBR</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>Organizing systems that follow the rules set forth in the <firstterm
                        xml:id="first_FRBR"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>Functional Requirements for
                                Bibliographic
                            Records</refentrytitle><manvolnum>FRBR</manvolnum></citerefentry></firstterm>
                    <citation xml:id="cite_Tillett2005" linkend="Tillett2005">(Tillett
                        2005)</citation> treat all instances of <citetitle pubwork="manuscript"
                        linkend="Shakespeare1623">Macbeth</citetitle> as the same
                        <quote>work.</quote> However, they also enforce a hierarchical set of
                    distinctions for finer-grained organization. FRBR views books and movies as
                    different <quote>expressions,</quote> different print editions as
                        <quote>manifestations,</quote> and each distinct physical thing in a
                    collection as an <quote>item.</quote> This organizing system thus encodes the
                    degree of intellectual equivalence while enabling separate identities where the
                    physical form is important, which is often the case for scholars.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para audience="Archives" xml:id="para-mtk_tnr_lr" revision="4.0" revisionflag="changed"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm significance="preferred" zone="def_fonds">
                        <primary>fonds</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="def_fonds">
                        <primary>library science</primary>
                        <secondary>fonds</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>Archival organizing systems implement a distinctive answer to the question of
            what is being organized. Archives are a type of collection that focuses on resources
            created by a particular person, organization, or institution, often during a particular
            time period. This means that archives have themselves been previously organized as a
            result of the processes that created and used them. <phrase role="definition"
                xml:id="def_fonds">The <quote>original order</quote> of the resources in an archive
                embodies the implicit or explicit organizing system of the person or entity that
                created the documents; it is treated as an essential part of the meaning of the
                collection. As a result, the unit of organization for archival collections is the
                    <glossterm xml:id="term_fonds">fonds</glossterm><symbol>&#8212;</symbol>the
                original arrangement or grouping, preserving any hierarchy of
                    <hardware>boxes</hardware>, <hardware>folders</hardware>,
                    <hardware>envelopes</hardware>, and individual
                    <hardware>documents</hardware><symbol>&#8212;</symbol>and thus they are not
                re-organized according to other (perhaps more systematic)
                classifications.</phrase><footnote xml:id="endnote-020" label="25"
                audience="Archives">
                <para audience="Archives" xml:id="para-mxk_tnr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-020">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Archives</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-020">
                                <primary>archives</primary>
                                <secondary>respect pour les fonds</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-020">
                                <primary>library science</primary>
                                <secondary>archives</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-020">
                                <primary>library science</primary>
                                <secondary>fonds</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-020">
                                <primary>archives</primary>
                                <secondary>University of California Berkeley</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-020">
                                <primary>fonds</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-020">
                                <primary>respect pour les fonds</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-020" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                                <primary>University of California, Berkeley</primary>
                                <secondary>archives</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-020" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                                <primary>Hearst Castle</primary>
                                <secondary>archives</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-020">
                                <primary>location</primary>
                                <secondary>surveying expedition</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-020">
                                <primary>original order</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>Typical examples of archives might be national or government document
                    collections or the specialized <personname><firstname>Julia</firstname>
                        <surname>Morgan</surname></personname> archive at the <orgname>University of
                        California, Berkeley</orgname> (<link
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/tf7b69n9k9/"
                            ><uri>http://www.oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/tf7b69n9k9/</uri></link>),
                    which houses documents by the famous architect who designed many of the
                    university’s most notable buildings as well as the famous Hearst Castle along
                    the central California coast. <phrase xml:id="principle-2n-RespectPourLesFonds"
                        role="statement principle">The <quote>original order</quote> organizing
                        principle of archival organizing systems was first defined by
                            <date>19th-century</date> French archivists and is often described as
                                <quote><foreignphrase xml:lang="fr">respect pour <hardware>les
                                    fonds</hardware></foreignphrase>.</quote></phrase></para>
                <para xml:id="para-gbl_tnr_lr" audience="Archives">The <link
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/hb1v19p1pv/admin/#descgrp-1.3.3"
                        >William Ashburner collection</link> of historical photos from an
                        <date>1867-1869</date> surveying expedition in the Western United States is
                    kept in the <orgname>University of California, Berkeley</orgname>’s
                        <orgname>Bancroft Library</orgname> in the order in which Ashburner, a
                    member of the survey party, had arranged it when he donated it to the library
                    decades later. The arrangement roughly follows a chronological and geographical
                    progression, with some photos obviously out of order and some whose locations
                    cannot be determined.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para audience="Archives" xml:id="para-cfl_tnr_lr"><phrase
                xml:id="statement-2n-DigitalDescendants" role="statement">Some organizing systems
                contain legal, business or scientific documents or data that are the digital
                descendants of paper reports or records of transactions or observations.</phrase>
            These organizing systems might need to deal with legacy information that still exists in
            paper form or in electronic formats like image scans that are different from the
            structural digital format in which more recent information is likely to be preserved.
            When legacy conversions from printed information artifacts are complete or unnecessary,
            an organizing system no longer deals with any of the traditional <hardware>tangible
                artifacts</hardware>. Digital libraries dispense with these artifacts, replacing
            them with the capability to print copies if needed. This enables libraries of digital
            documents or data collections to be vastly larger and more accessible across space and
            time than any library that stores tangible, physical items could ever be.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ljl_tnr_lr">An increasing number of organizing systems
            handle resources that are born digital. Ideally, digital texts can be encoded with
            explicit markup that captures structural boundaries and content distinctions, which can
            be used to facilitate organization, retrieval, or both. In practice the digital
            representations of texts are often just image scans that do not support much processing
            or interaction. A similar situation exists for the digital representations of music,
            photographs, videos, and other non-text content like sensor data, where the digital
            formats are structurally and semantically opaque.</para>
        <sidebar revision="4.0" revisionflag="changed" xml:id="sidebar-CompDescPeople"
            audience="CORE DS">
            <?dbhtml sidebar-width="66%"?>
            <?dbhtml float-type="right"?>
            <?dbfo sidebar-width="100%"?>
            <?dbfo float-type="outside"?>
            <title>Computational Descriptions of People</title>
            <!-- Moved from 4.3.6.4, left one paragraph behind -->
            <info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-CompDescPeople" condition="print"
                        userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>sidebar</primary>
                        <secondary>Computational Descriptions of People</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-CompDescPeople" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>Computational Descriptions of People</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-CompDescPeople">
                        <primary>description</primary>
                        <secondary>computational</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-CompDescPeople" audience="DS">
                        <primary>data science</primary>
                        <secondary>predictive analytics</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-CompDescPeople">
                        <primary>predictive analytics</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>
            <para audience="CORE DS" revision="4.0" revisionflag="changed" xml:id="para-mnv_y1r_w5"
                >Each of us is associated with a great many computational descriptions, some of
                which are used almost every day to make predictions about our behavior using a
                variety of statistical techniques that are collectively called <quote>predictive
                    analytics.</quote> Whenever you use a credit card, fraud detection algorithms
                use a model derived from your purchase history to decide, in fractions of a second,
                whether the transaction is being initiated by you, or by someone who has stolen your
                card. When you want to buy something expensive on credit, the seller consults your
                credit score—based on what you owe, your payment history, how long you have had
                credit, the kinds of credit you have, and other factors—to predict whether you are a
                good credit risk, and your credit score then gets adjusted if the seller decides to
                give you credit. Then, after you have bought that expensive item, the seller's
                predictive model can use that information to suggest other things you might want to
                buy. </para>
            <para audience="CORE DS" revision="4.0" revisionflag="changed" xml:id="para-nnv_y1r_w5"
                >Philosophers have long debated the extent to which observations of a person’s
                behavior can yield an understanding of their true and unobservable nature. But
                whether or not computational descriptions capture a person's essence, there is no
                escaping them. If you want to get life or car insurance or a mortgage, models
                determine what you have to pay. Predictive models are being used to admit people to
                college, to hire them, to draft or trade them in professional sports, and to decide
                whether to monitor them closely because they might be planning a terrorist act. Some
                companies use <quote>people analytics</quote> software that analyzes every email,
                calendar item, and document created by employees to build a model of what they know,
                what they do, when they do it, and who they work with—the goal being to improve
                communication and collaboration within the firm and with customers. </para>
        </sidebar>
        <para revision="3.0" revisionflag="added" xml:id="para-iq4_myv_qv">This book does not
            emphasize systems that organize people, but it would be remiss not to mention them.
            Businesses organize their employees, schools organize their faculties and students,
            sports leagues and teams organize their players, and governments organize their citizens
            and residents to enable them to vote, drive, attend schools, and receive medical care
            and other benefits. <phrase audience="CORE DS" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added">Data
                scientists in all of these fields increasingly predict how employees, students,
                athletes, voters, drivers - and other categories of people defined by intrinsic or
                derived characteristics - will behave, decide, live, or die. Once people die, it is
                no longer necessary to predict anything about them, but nonetheless cemeteries are
                highly organized.</phrase>
        </para>
        <para revision="3.0" revisionflag="added" xml:id="para-ot1_hrt_ts"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-ot1_hrt_ts">
                        <primary>time</primary>
                        <secondary>as a resource</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-ot1_hrt_ts">
                        <primary>resources</primary>
                        <secondary>time</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>We often think and talk about time as a resource, and time fits the definition of
                <quote>anything of value that supports goal-oriented activity</quote> from <xref
                linkend="section-1.3" xrefstyle="short"/>. Furthermore, we could think of the
            calendar and clock as organizing systems that define time at different levels of
            granularity to support different kinds of interactions. However, it is probably more
            useful to think of time as a constraint that influences how and how much to organize. </para>
        <para revision="3.0" revisionflag="added" xml:id="para-jq4_myv_qv">If you're sorting your
            own mail, you can question whether the time you spend on sorting is worth the time you
            save on searching. But at scale—imagine 10 million books in a library—the considerable
            effort required to organize resources saves vastly more time for the many users of the
            system over its lifetime. Note the inherent tradeoff between time spent on organizing
            versus retrieval; this will be a recurring theme throughout this book. In a personal
            context the tradeoff is a matter of individual need or preference, but in social or
            institutional contexts organization and retrieval are generally done by different
            people, and their time is likely valued in different ways by the system owner. </para>
        <!--              -->
    </section>
    <section label="2.3" xml:id="section-2n.3">
        <title>Why Is It Being Organized?</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-2n.3">
                    <primary>organizing</primary>
                    <secondary>why</secondary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <blockquote>
            <attribution><citation xml:id="cite_Svenonius2000-1.4" linkend="Svenonius2000"
                    >(Svenonius 2000 p. xi)</citation></attribution>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-o4l_tnr_lr"><emphasis><quote>The central purpose of
                        systems for organizing information [is] bringing like things together and
                        differentiating among them.</quote></emphasis></para>
        </blockquote>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-dtl_tnr_lr"><phrase
                xml:id="principle-2n-EssentialPurpose" role="principle statement">Almost by
                definition, the essential purpose of any organizing system is to describe or arrange
                resources so they can be located and accessed later. The organizing principles
                needed to achieve this goal depend on the types of resources or domains being
                organized, and in the personal, social, or institutional setting in which
                organization takes place.</phrase>
        </para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-aw2_tnr_lr">Organizing systems can be
            distinguished by their dominant purposes or the priority of their common purposes.
                <phrase xml:id="statement-2n-PrimaryEmphasis">Libraries, museums, and archives are
                often classified as <glossterm linkend="gloss_memory_institution">memory
                    institutions</glossterm> to emphasize their primary emphasis on resource
                preservation.</phrase> In contrast, <quote>management information systems</quote> or
                <quote>business systems</quote> are categories that include the great variety of
            software applications that implement the organizing systems needed to carry out
            day-to-day business operations.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-kq4_myv_qv"><phrase xml:id="principle-2n-LikeThings"
                role="statement principle"><quote>Bringing like things together</quote> is an
                informal organizing principle for many organizing systems. Almost as soon as
                libraries were invented over two thousand years ago, the earliest librarians saw the
                need to develop systematic methods for arranging and inventorying their
                    collections.<footnote xml:id="endnote-024" label="26" audience="LIS">
                    <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-yfn_tnr_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-024">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>LIS</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-024" userlevel="Professional">
                                    <primary>library science</primary>
                                    <secondary>citations</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info><citation xml:id="cite_Casson2002" linkend="Casson2002">(Casson
                            2002)</citation>.</para>
                </footnote> The invention of mechanized printing in the <date>fifteenth
                    century</date>, which radically increased the number of
                    <hardware>books</hardware> and <hardware>periodicals</hardware>, forced
                libraries to begin progressively more refined efforts to state the functional
                requirements for their organizing systems and to be explicit about how they met
                those requirements.</phrase></para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="comparative" xml:id="para-sjn_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-sjn_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>location</primary>
                        <secondary>collection resources</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-sjn_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>library science</primary>
                        <secondary>organizing systems</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-sjn_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>business</primary>
                        <secondary>organizing systems</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info><phrase revision="4.0" revisionflag="added">Today, any information-driven
                enterprise must have systematic processes and technologies in place that govern
                information creation or capture and then manage its entire life cycle. Commercial
                firms need processes for transacting with customers or other firms to carry out
                business operations, to support research and innovation, marketing, and to develop
                business strategy and tactics in compliance with laws and regulations for
                accounting, taxes, human resources, data retention, and so on. In large firms these
                functions are so highly specialized and complex that the different types of
                organizing systems have distinct names: <firstterm xml:id="first_ERP"
                        ><application>Enterprise Resource Planning (<phrase remap="abbrev"
                            >ERP</phrase>)</application></firstterm>, <firstterm xml:id="first_ECM"
                        ><application>Enterprise Content Management (<phrase remap="abbrev"
                            >ECM</phrase>)</application></firstterm>, <firstterm xml:id="first_EDM"
                        ><application>Enterprise Data Management (<phrase remap="abbrev"
                            >EDM</phrase>)</application></firstterm>
                <firstterm xml:id="first_SCM"><application>Supply Chain Management (<phrase
                            remap="abbrev">SCM</phrase>)</application></firstterm>, <firstterm
                    xml:id="first_RM"><application>Records Management</application></firstterm>,
                    <firstterm xml:id="first_CRM"><application>Customer Relationship Management
                            (<phrase remap="abbrev">CRM</phrase>)</application></firstterm>,
                    <firstterm xml:id="first_BI"><application>Business Intelligence (<phrase
                            remap="abbrev">BI</phrase>)</application></firstterm>, <firstterm
                    xml:id="first_KM"><application>Knowledge Management (<phrase remap="abbrev"
                            >KM</phrase>)</application></firstterm>, and so on. And even though the
                most important functions in the organizing systems of large enterprises are those
                that manage the information resources needed for its business operation, these firms
                might also need to maintain corporate libraries and archives.</phrase></para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="comparative" xml:id="para-srn_tnr_lr">Preserving documents in
            their physical or original form is the primary purpose of <hardware>archives</hardware>
            and similar organizing systems that contain culturally, historically, or economically
            significant documents that have value as long-term <hardware>evidence</hardware>.
            Preservation is also an important motivation for the organizing systems of information-
            and knowledge-intensive firms<phrase revision="4.0" revisionflag="added">, where
                information is primarily in digital formats</phrase>. <phrase
                xml:id="statement-RequiredRecords">Businesses and governmental agencies are usually
                required by law to keep records of financial transactions, decision-making,
                personnel matters, and other information essential to business continuity,
                compliance with regulations and legal procedures, and transparency.</phrase>
            <phrase revision="4.0" revisionflag="changed" audience="Law">As with archives, it is
                sometimes critical that these business knowledge or records management systems can
                retrieve the original documents, although digital copies that can be authenticated
                are increasingly being accepted as legally equivalent.</phrase></para>
        <para revision="3.0" revisionflag="added" xml:id="para-lq4_myv_qv">This discussion of the
            requirements for organizing resources in memory institutions and businesses might convey
            the impression that storing and retrieving resources efficiently are paramount goals,
            and indeed they are in many contexts. But there are many other reasons for organizing
            resources, as is easily seen when we look at personal organizing systems. And there are
            many other ways to compare organizing systems than just how efficiently they enable
            storing and retrieval functions. </para>
        <para revision="3.0" revisionflag="added" xml:id="para-mq4_myv_qv">An overarching goal when
            people are organizing their personal resources is to minimize the effort needed to find
            the resources. But unlike the finding task in institutional organizing systems, which is
            generally facilitated with external resource descriptions, finding aids,
            classifications, search engines, and orientation and navigation mechanisms, the finding
            task in personal organizing systems is primarily a cognitive one: you need to remember
            where the resources are and how they are arranged. Because each person has unique
            experiences and preferences, it is not surprising that people often organize the same
            types of resources in different ways to make the organization easier to perceive and
            remember. The resulting resource arrangements often emphasize aesthetic or emotional
            goals, as when books or clothes are arranged by color or preference, or behavioral
            goals, as when most frequently used condiments and spices are kept on the kitchen
            counter rather than stored in a pantry.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-fjm_tnr_lr">When individuals manage their
                <hardware>papers</hardware>, <hardware>books</hardware>,
                <hardware>documents</hardware>, <hardware>record albums</hardware>,
                <hardware>compact discs</hardware>, <hardware>DVDs</hardware>, and other information
            resources, their organizing systems can vary greatly. This is in part because the
            content of the resources being organized becomes a consideration. Furthermore, many of
            the organizing systems used by individuals are implemented by web applications, and this
            makes them more accessible <phrase revision="4.0" revisionflag="added">than physical
                resources</phrase>.<footnote xml:id="endnote-022" label="27" audience="Web">
                <para audience="Web" xml:id="para-dnm_tnr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-022">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Web</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-022">
                                <primary>Web</primary>
                                <secondary>tagging</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>For example, many people manage their digital photos with
                        <application>Flickr</application>, their home libraries with
                        <application>Library Thing</application>, and their preferences for dining
                    and shopping with <application>Yelp</application>. It is possible to use these
                        <quote>tagging</quote> sites solely in support of individual goals, as tags
                    like <quote>my family,</quote>
                    <quote>to read,</quote> or <quote>buy this</quote> clearly demonstrate. But
                    maintaining a personal organizing system with these web applications potentially
                    augments the individual’s purpose with social goals like conveying information
                    to others, developing a community, or promoting a reputation. Furthermore,
                    because these community or collaborative applications aggregate and share the
                    tags applied by individuals, they shape the individual organizing systems
                    embedded within them when they suggest the most frequent tags for a particular
                    resource.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-vqm_tnr_lr">Put another way, an information resource
            inherently has more potential uses than resources like <hardware>forks</hardware> or
                <hardware>frying pans</hardware>, so it is not surprising that the organizing
            systems in offices are even more diverse than those in
            <hardware>kitchens</hardware>.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="principle" xml:id="para-m5m_tnr_lr">When the scale of the
            collection or the number of intended users increases, <phrase revision="4.0"
                revisionflag="added" audience="CORE DS">two things can happen. The first is that if
                the system can turn its interaction traces into interaction resources, additional
                value can be created by analyzing these resources to enhance the interactions, to
                suggest new ones, or make predictions about how individual users or groups of them
                will behave. Every business that has a high volume of customer transactions does
                this; for example, a fast-food restaurant would analyze time-stamped sales data, and
                might introduce a quick pickup line for items that sell the most, or create product
                bundles that increase sales while optimizing kitchen and counter work. Amazon.com
                and other retailers that can capture detailed browsing traces can augment the sales
                data they collect by treating items that were looked at but not purchased as
                potential transactions, making them additional inputs to their sophisticated pricing
                and recommendation systems.</phrase></para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="principle" xml:id="para-o24_nwr_5v"><phrase revision="4.0"
                revisionflag="added" audience="CORE DS">A second likely outcome of increased scale
                or use is that</phrase> not everyone is likely to share the same goals and design
            preferences for the organizing system. If you share a kitchen with housemates, you might
            have to negotiate and compromise on some of the decisions about how the kitchen is
            organized so you can all get along. In more formal or institutional organizing systems
            conflicts between stakeholders can be much more severe, and the organizing principles
                <phrase audience="CORE DS" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added">and policies or
                permissions for the kinds of interactions available to different users</phrase>
            might even be specified in commercial contracts or governed by laws or standards. For
            example, Bowker and Star note that physicians view the creation of patient records as
            central to diagnosis and treatment, insurance companies think of them as evidence needed
            for payment and reimbursement, and researchers think of them as primary data. These
            groups do not agree on the priority and quality requirements they assign to different
            information in the patient record, and physicians understandably resist doing work that
            has no direct benefit for them. Not surprisingly, policy making and regulations about
            patient records are highly contentious.<footnote xml:id="endnote-023" label="28"
                audience="LIS">
                <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-eym_tnr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-023">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>LIS</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-023" userlevel="Professional">
                                <primary>library science</primary>
                                <secondary>citations</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><citation xml:id="cite_Bowker2000" linkend="Bowker2000">(Bowker and Star
                        2000)</citation>.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para revision="3.0" revisionflag="added" xml:id="para-nq4_myv_qv">Once we acknowledge that
            stakeholders might not share the same goals, it is clear that efficiency is too narrow a
            measure for evaluating organizing systems. The ways that resources are organized <phrase
                revision="4.0" revisionflag="added" audience="CORE DS">and interacted with</phrase>
            embody the priorities and values of those <phrase revision="4.0" revisionflag="added"
                >designing the organizing system</phrase>, yielding arrangements and interactions
            designed to control or change the behaviors of the users. Put more bluntly, resources
            are always organized in ways that are designed to allocate value for some people (e.g.,
            the owners of the resources, or the most frequent users of them) and not for others.
            From the perspective of the other types of user trying to interact with the system, this
            organization will likely seem unfair. In this way, organizing resources can often be
            seen as creating winners and losers, providing benefits to the former and imposing costs
            or constraints on the latter. <phrase audience="CORE DS" revision="4.0"
                revisionflag="added">For example, search engines analyze interaction resources to
                adjust search results and choose an ad that is related to your latest query. These
                are considered improved interactions from the perspective of the search engine, but
                you might consider it a violation of your privacy and a bit creepy to have the
                targeted ad follow you around the web until you click on it.</phrase></para>
        <para revision="3.0" revisionflag="added" xml:id="para-xmh_ctt_ts"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-xmh_ctt_ts">
                        <primary>cafeteria</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-xmh_ctt_ts">
                        <primary>behavioral economics</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-xmh_ctt_ts">
                        <primary>science of shopping</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>The emerging field of applied behavioral economics, popularized in books like
                <citetitle linkend="Levitt2005">Freakonomics</citetitle> and <citetitle
                linkend="Thaler2008">Nudge,</citetitle> explains how subtle differences in resource
            arrangement, the number and framing of choices, and default values can have substantial
            effects on the decisions people make. Consider the arrangement of salads, pasta dishes,
            bread, fish, meat, desserts and other types of food in a self-serve cafeteria buffet. In
            a school setting, the food might be organized and presented to encourage healthier
            eating, perhaps by making the fatty french fries and high-calorie desserts hard to reach
            or by providing smaller trays and plates. The same foods would likely be organized
            differently in an all-you-can-eat restaurant, where the goal is to minimize food costs,
            with less expensive items like salads at the front of the line to ensure that trays and
            plates will already be full when the customer gets to the more expensive items at the
            end of the line.<footnote audience="Business" xml:id="endnote-023b" revision="3.0"
                revisionflag="added" label="29">
                <para audience="Business" xml:id="para-e2y_hcw_ps" revision="3.0"
                    revisionflag="added"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-023b">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Business</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-023b" userlevel="Professional">
                                <primary>business</primary>
                                <secondary>citations</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><citation xml:id="cite_Levitt2005" linkend="Levitt2005">(Levitt
                        2005)</citation> and <citation xml:id="cite_Thaler2008" linkend="Thaler2008"
                        >(Thaler 2008)</citation></para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para revision="3.0" revisionflag="added" xml:id="para-pr5_sst_ts"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-pr5_sst_ts">
                        <primary>cafeteria</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>The organization of cafeteria buffets to shape user behavior might not seem
            sinister. However, organizing systems can control behavior in ways that create or
            perpetuate inequities among their users. This unfairness is a matter of degree: a person
            who does not own a computer who goes to the public library to check out a popular book
            loses out when the library enables patrons with computer access to check out books
            online and assumes that everyone has an equal shot at accessing books via the Internet. </para>
        <para revision="3.0" revisionflag="added" xml:id="para-pqh_tjt_ts"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-pqh_tjt_ts">
                        <primary>apartheid</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>Looking to a much more insidious organizing system, when the South African
            government adopted Apartheid policies to classify and segregate people by race, it
            systematized economic and political discrimination and great suffering for the nonwhite
            population. <phrase role="parenthetical">(See the sidebar, <xref
                    linkend="sidebar-Power_and_Politics"/>.)</phrase></para>
        <sidebar xml:id="sidebar-Power_and_Politics" revision="3.0" revisionflag="added">
            <title>Power and Politics in Organizing</title>
            <info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-Power_and_Politics" condition="print" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>sidebar</primary>
                        <secondary>Power and Politics in Organizing</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-Power_and_Politics" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>Power and Politics in Organizing</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-Power_and_Politics">
                        <primary>organizing</primary>
                        <secondary>power and politics</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-Power_and_Politics">
                        <primary>cafeteria</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-Power_and_Politics">
                        <primary>apartheid</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>
            <para xml:id="para-oq4_myv_qv">It is tempting to think of organizing systems and the
                technologies used to implement them as neutral or objective in their goals and
                impacts, but it is impossible to argue that the use of racial classification in
                apartheid South Africa was not a conscious manifestation of prejudice. And even if
                making it hard for school kids to find the junk food in the cafeteria buffet has
                health benefits, it nevertheless reflects a paternalistic point of view that
                restricts individual choices. </para>
            <para xml:id="para-pq4_myv_qv">Organizing systems and technology are not developed in a
                vacuum, unencumbered by politics or social context. As
                        <personname><firstname>Langdon</firstname>
                    <surname>Winner</surname></personname> underscores in <citetitle
                    linkend="Winner1980" xml:id="cite_Winner1980">Do Artifacts Have
                    Politics?</citetitle>, systems and technologies can be conscious manifestations
                of the personal (and often political) biases of their creators. Because all people
                have different experiences and biases, even when they are not conscious of them they
                influence the design and implementation of organizing systems in ways that can
                create or perpetuate inequalities.<footnote revision="3.0" revisionflag="added"
                    label="30" xml:id="endnote-023c" audience="Philosophy">
                    <para xml:id="para-hvm_kcw_ps" audience="Philosophy" revision="3.0"
                        revisionflag="added"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-023c">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Philosophy</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-023c">
                                    <primary>philosophy</primary>
                                    <secondary>Winner, Langdon</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info><citation xml:id="cite2_Winner1980" linkend="Winner1980">(Winner 1980
                            p 121-136)</citation></para>
                </footnote></para>
            <para xml:id="para-qq4_myv_qv">Technology innovators whose expressed goals are to make
                something faster, smaller, or cheaper are ignoring the potential for their
                innovations and automation to render certain types of work less viable and
                discriminate against people who lack the technology or skills to use it. For
                example, Winner describes the inadvertent social and political consequences of the
                introduction of mechanical tomato harvesters in California agriculture in the 1960s.
                Their industry-wide adoption favored larger farms with more resources to buy the
                expensive machines, resulting in the disappearance of small tomato farms and
                large-scale changes to many rural communities whose economies had relied on them. </para>
            <para xml:id="para-rq4_myv_qv">Some may argue that the mechanical tomato harvester
                created massive benefits by increasing productivity, but the determination that more
                efficient tomato production is worth its consequences could be debated. In any case,
                the debate cannot be answered with a definite yes or no, just as it cannot be with
                whether the Internet is bad because it has eroded the need for librarians, or
                whether <orgname>Uber</orgname>'s clever technologies for matching drivers and
                riders unfairly avoid the regulations imposed on the taxi industry. Affirming the
                introduction of the mechanical tomato harvester, search engines, and
                    <orgname>Uber</orgname> in the name of productivity, progress, and efficiency is
                a political point of view.</para>
            <para xml:id="para-sq4_myv_qv"><phrase role="parenthetical">(See also <xref
                        linkend="section-8.2.3"/> and <xref linkend="chapter-11"/>.)</phrase></para>
        </sidebar>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-lvn_tnr_lr"><xref linkend="chapter-8"/> more fully
            explains the different purposes for organizing systems, the organizing principles they
            embody, and the methods for assigning resources to categories.</para>
        <!--              -->
    </section>
    <!--              -->
    <section xml:id="section-2n.4" label="2.4">
        <title>How Much Is It Being Organized?</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-2n.4">
                    <primary>organizing</primary>
                    <secondary>degree</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm zone="section-2n.4">
                    <primary>organizing</primary>
                    <secondary>how much</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm zone="section-2n.4">
                    <primary>degree</primary>
                    <secondary>of organizing systems</secondary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <blockquote>
            <attribution><citation xml:id="cite_Svenonius2000-1.5" linkend="Svenonius2000"
                    >(Svenonius 2000, p. 24)</citation></attribution>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-jzn_tnr_lr"><emphasis><quote>It is a general
                        bibliographic truth that not all documents should be accorded the same
                        degree of organization.</quote></emphasis></para>
        </blockquote>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-cd4_tnr_lr"><phrase xml:id="statement-2n-ToWhatDegree"
                role="statement">Not all resources should be accorded the same degree of
                organization.</phrase> In this section we will briefly unpack this notion of degree
            of organization into three important and related dimensions: the amount of description
            detail or organization applied to each resource, the amount of organization of resources
            into classes or categories, and the overall extent to which interactions in and between
            organizing systems are shaped by resource description and arrangement. </para>
        <para revision="3.0" revisionflag="added" xml:id="para-tq4_myv_qv">It is important to note
            that this section is <emphasis role="bold">not</emphasis> asking the question <quote>how
                much stuff is being organized?</quote> but rather to what degree is the stuff being
            organized. Another way to ask the same question is <quote>how many organizing principles
                are at work?</quote> in this organizing system. Your closet might be arranged only
            by body part covered and season; an online music store will organize resources by genre,
            artist name, band name, album name, popularity, date released, and maybe others. So we
            would say that the online music store is organized much more than the closet, because
            more organizing principles are at work.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-zkg_y11_vw" userlevel="Professional Graduate"><phrase
                role="parenthetical">(<xref linkend="chapter-5" xrefstyle="short"/> and <xref
                    linkend="chapter-7" xrefstyle="short"/>, more thoroughly address these questions
                about the nature and extent of description in organizing systems.)</phrase></para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-lk4_tnr_lr">Not all resources in a
            collection require the same degree of description for the simple reason<phrase
                role="parenthetical"> we discussed in <xref linkend="section-2n.3"/></phrase>:
            Organizing systems exist for different purposes and to support different kinds of
            interactions or functions. Let us contrast two ends of the <quote>degree of
                description</quote> continuum. Many people use <quote>current events
                awareness</quote> or <quote>news feed</quote> applications that select news stories
            whose titles or abstracts contain one or more keywords (Google Alert is a good example).
            This exact match algorithm is easy to implement, but its all-or-none and
            one-item-at-a-time comparison misses any stories that use synonyms of the keyword, that
            are written in languages different from that of the keyword, or that are otherwise
            relevant but do not contain the exact keyword in the limited part of the document that
            is scanned. However, users with current events awareness goals do not need to see every
            news story about some event, and this limited amount of description for each story and
            the simple method of comparing descriptions are sufficient.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-g44_tnr_lr">On the other hand, this
            simple organizing system is inadequate for the purpose of comprehensive retrieval of all
            documents that relate to some concept, event, or problem. This is a critical task for
            scholars, scientists, inventors, physicians, attorneys and similar professionals who
            might need to discover every relevant document in some domain. Instead, this type of
            organizing system needs rich bibliographic and semantic description of each document,
            most likely assigned by professional catalogers, and probably using terms from a
                <firstterm linkend="gloss_controlled_vocabulary">controlled vocabulary</firstterm>
            to enforce consistency in what descriptions mean.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-wr4_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-wr4_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>SKU</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>Similarly, different merchants or firms might make different decisions about the
            extent or granularity of description when they assign <abbrev>SKU</abbrev>s because of
            differences in suppliers, targeted customers, or other business strategies. If you take
            your car to the repair shop because windshield wiper fluid is leaking, you might be
            dismayed to find that the broken <hardware>rubber seal</hardware> that is causing the
            leak cannot be ordered separately and you have to pay to replace the
                    <quote><hardware>wiper fluid reservoir</hardware></quote> for which the seal is
            a minor but vital part. Likewise, when two business applications try to exchange and
            merge customer information, integration problems arise if one describes a customer as a
            single <quote>NAME</quote> component while the other separates the customer’s name into
                <quote>TITLE,</quote>
            <quote>FIRSTNAME,</quote> and <quote>LASTNAME.</quote></para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-ov4_tnr_lr"><phrase
                xml:id="statement-2n-TolerateDisorganization" role="statement">Even when faced with
                the same collection of resources, people differ in how much organization they prefer
                or how much disorganization they can tolerate.</phrase> A classic study by
                    <personname><firstname>Tom</firstname>
                <surname>Malone</surname></personname> of how people organize their office
            workspaces and desks contrasted the strategies and methods of <quote>filers</quote> and
                <quote>pilers.</quote> Filers maintain clean desktops and systematically organize
            their papers into categories, while pilers have messy work areas and make few attempts
            at organization. This contrast has analogues in other organizing systems and we can
            easily imagine what happens if a <quote>neat freak</quote> and <quote>slob</quote>
            become roommates.<footnote xml:id="endnote-025" label="31" audience="CogSci">
                <para audience="CogSci" xml:id="para-iz4_tnr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-025">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>CogSci</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-025">
                                <primary>cognitive science</primary>
                                <secondary>Odd Couple</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><citation xml:id="cite_Malone1983" linkend="Malone1983">(Malone
                        1983)</citation> is the seminal research study, but individual differences
                    in organizing preferences were the basis of
                            <personname><firstname>Neil</firstname>
                        <surname>Simon</surname></personname>’s Broadway play <citetitle
                        pubwork="manuscript">The Odd Couple</citetitle> in <date>1965</date>, which
                    then spawned numerous films and TV series.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para revision="3.0" revisionflag="added" xml:id="para-uq4_myv_qv">An equally wide range,
            from a little organization to a lot, can be seen in the organizing systems for
            businesses, armies, governments, or any other institutional organizing systems for
            people. Organizations with broad scope and many people usually have deep hierarchies and
            explicit reporting relationships with the CEO, general, or president at the top with
            numerous layers of vice presidents, directors, department heads, and managers (or
            colonels, majors, captains, lieutenants, and sergeants). Smaller organizations are more
            varied, with some embodying multi-layered management, and some embracing a flatter
            arrangement with fewer management levels, wider spans of authority, and more autonomy
            for individual workers. Many start-up firms try to grow without any management structure
            at all in the belief that it makes them more innovative and nimble, but evidence
            suggests that when no one is responsible for making decisions, the lack of
            accountability results in poor decisions, or in no decisions at all even when some were
            sorely needed.<footnote label="32" revision="3.0" revisionflag="added"
                audience="Business" xml:id="endnote-025a">
                <para xml:id="para-zy3_mcw_ps" audience="Business" revision="3.0"
                    revisionflag="added"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-025a">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Business</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-025a">
                                <primary>business</primary>
                                <secondary>Silverman</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><citation linkend="Silverman2013" xml:id="cite_Silverman2013">(Silverman
                        2013)</citation></para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-zcp_tnr_lr"><phrase
                xml:id="statement-2n-MoreWork" role="statement">In any case, when people have to do
                it, describing and organizing resources is work. Stakeholders in an organizing
                system often have disagreements among about how much organization is necessary
                because of the implications for who performs the work and who derives the benefits,
                especially the economic ones.</phrase> Physicians prefer narrative descriptions and
            broad classification systems because they make it easier to create patient notes. In
            contrast, insurance companies and researchers want fine-grained
                <quote>form-filling</quote> descriptions and detailed classifications that would
            make the physician’s work more onerous.<footnote xml:id="endnote-026" label="33"
                audience="Computing">
                <para audience="Computing" xml:id="para-fhp_tnr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-026">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Computing</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-026">
                                <primary>computing</primary>
                                <secondary>Grudin</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>See Grudin’s classic work on non-technological barriers to the successful
                    adoption of collaboration technology <citation xml:id="cite_Grudin1994"
                        linkend="Grudin1994">(Grudin 1994)</citation>.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-alp_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-alp_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>costs</primary>
                        <secondary>accounting</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
        </info><phrase xml:id="statement-2n-Panizzi" role="statement">The cost-effectiveness of creating systematic and
                comprehensive descriptions of the resources in an information collection has been
                debated for nearly two centuries, beginning in <date>1841</date> when Sir Anthony
                Panizzi proposed rules for cataloguing the British Library. In the last half
                century, the scope of the debate grew to consider the role of computer-generated
                resource descriptions.</phrase><footnote xml:id="endnote-027" label="34"
                audience="LIS">
                <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-w4p_tnr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-027">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>LIS</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-027">
                                <primary>cataloging</primary>
                                <secondary>Panizzi</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-027">
                                <primary>library science</primary>
                                <secondary>cataloging rules</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>Panizzi is most often associated with the origins of modern library
                    cataloging. He <citation xml:id="cite_Panizzi1841" linkend="Panizzi1841"
                        >(Panizzi 1841)</citation> published 91 cataloging rules for the British
                    Library that defined authoritative forms for titles and author names, but the
                    complexity of the rules and the resulting resource descriptions were widely
                    criticized. For example, the famous author and historian Thomas Carlyle argued
                    that a library catalog should be nothing more than a list of the names of the
                    books in it. Standards for bibliographic description are essential if resources
                    are to be shared between libraries. See <citation xml:id="cite_Denton2007-1.1"
                        linkend="Denton2007">(Denton 2007)</citation>, <citation
                        xml:id="cite_Anderson2001a" linkend="Anderson2001a">(Anderson and
                        Perez-Carballo 2001a</citation>, <citation xml:id="cite_Anderson2001b"
                        linkend="Anderson2001b">2001b</citation>).</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para xml:id="para-vq4_myv_qv">The amount of resource description is always shaped by the
            currently available technology for capturing, storing, and making use of it. Nineteenth
            century geologists and paleontologists typically recorded only general information about
            the depth and surrounding geological features when they found fossils because they had
            no technology for making more precise measurements and everything they noted they had to
            record by hand. Today, vastly more detailed information is recorded by instruments and
            exploited by sophisticated techniques for carbon dating and 3D reconstruction.<footnote 
                label="35" audience="LIS" xml:id="endnote-027a">
                <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-wq4_myv_qv"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-027a">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>LIS</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-027a" userlevel="Professional">
                                <primary>library science</primary>
                                <secondary>citations</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><citation linkend="Bowker2000" xml:id="cite_Bowker2000-1.3.4">(Bowker and
                        Star 2000 p. 69.)</citation></para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="comparative" xml:id="para-tsp_tnr_lr"><phrase role="statement"
                xml:id="statement-2n-GeneratedDescriptions">Automatically generated descriptions are
                increasingly an alternative or complement to those created by people.</phrase>
            <quote>Smart</quote> resources use sensors to capture information about themselves and
            their environments <phrase role="parenthetical">(see <xref linkend="section-4.3.4"
                    xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>. Our own computers and phones record information
            about our keystrokes, clicks, communications, and locations. Business and government
            computers analyze and index most of the text and speech content that flows through and
            between our personal phones and computers. These indexes typically assign weights to the
            terms according to calculations that consider the frequency and distribution of the
            terms in both individual documents and in the collection as a whole to create a
            description of what the documents are about. These descriptions of the documents in the
            collection are more consistent than those created by human organizers. They allow for
            more complex query processing and comparison operations by the retrieval functions in
            the organizing system. For example, query expansion mechanisms can automatically add
            synonyms and related terms to the search. Additionally, retrieved documents can be
            arranged by relevance, while <quote>citing</quote> and <quote>cited-by</quote> links can
            be analyzed to find related relevant documents.</para>
        <para revision="3.0" revisionflag="added" xml:id="para-xq4_myv_qv">It is important to
            recognize the potential downside to automated resource description. A detailed
            description produced by sensors or computers can seem more accurate or authoritative
            than a simpler one created by a human observer, even if the latter would be more useful
            for the intended purposes. Moreover, the more detailed the description, the greater the
            opportunity to use it for new purposes. This might be desirable, as when a company
            realizes that it can cross- and up-sell because it has been tracking every click in a
            web store <phrase revision="4.0" revisionflag="added" audience="CORE DS">to create a
                collection of interaction resources</phrase>. But it could be undesirable, because
            detailed transaction data can be used to violate privacy and civil rights. It depends on
            who controls the collected information and their incentives for using it or not using
            it.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-pwp_tnr_lr">A second constraint on the
            degree of organization comes from the size of the collection within the scope of the
            organizing system. <phrase xml:id="statement-2n-MoreResourcesMoreConstraints"
                role="statement">Organizing more resources requires more descriptions to distinguish
                any particular resource from the rest, and more constraining organizing
                principles.</phrase> Similar resources need to be grouped or classified to emphasize
            the most important distinctions among the complete set of resources in the collection. A
            small neighborhood restaurant might have a short wine list with just ten wines, arranged
            in two categories for <quote>red</quote> and <quote>white</quote> and described only by
            the wine’s name and price. In contrast, a gourmet restaurant might have hundreds of
            wines in its wine list, which would subdivide its <quote>red</quote> and
                <quote>white</quote> high-level categories into subcategories for country, region of
            origin, and grape varietal. The description for each wine might in addition include a
            specific vineyard from which the grapes were sourced, the vintage year, ratings of the
            wine, and tasting notes.</para>
        <sidebar audience="Computing IA" revisionflag="added" revision="3.0"
            xml:id="sidebar-MeasureInfo">
            <title>Using <quote>Information Theory</quote> to Quantify Organization</title>
            <info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-MeasureInfo" condition="print"
                        userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>sidebar</primary>
                        <secondary>Using <quote>Information Theory</quote> to Quantify
                            Organization</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-MeasureInfo" condition="print"
                        userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>Using <quote>Information Theory</quote> to Quantify
                            Organization</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-MeasureInfo">
                        <primary>information theory</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-MeasureInfo">
                        <primary>organization</primary>
                        <secondary>quantify</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-MeasureInfo">
                        <primary>entropy</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>
            <para xml:id="para-yq4_myv_qv">We often hear news stories hyping <quote>how much
                    information</quote> there is in the information society with breathless
                exuberance about the creation of peta-, exa-, whatever-bytes of content. A much more
                important and intellectually deeper question than absolute size in bytes is
                measuring how much information is encoded in the structure or organization of a
                system. For this we can turn to <quote>Information Theory,</quote> a formal approach
                to understanding the theoretical maximum amount of information that can be carried
                by a communications system by using efficient coding, data compression, and error
                correction. It was developed by <personname><firstname>Claude</firstname>
                    <surname>Shannon</surname></personname>, a researcher at <orgname>Bell
                    Laboratories</orgname>, and first published as <quote>a mathematical theory of
                    communication</quote> in 1948. We can apply it in the discipline of organizing
                to compare the amount of structure in different ways of organizing the same
                    resources.<footnote label="36" audience="IA" revision="3.0"
                    revisionflag="added" xml:id="endnote-027b">
                    <para xml:id="para-tfx_mcw_ps" audience="IA" revision="4.0"
                        revisionflag="changed"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-027b">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>IA</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-027b">
                                    <primary>information architecture</primary>
                                    <secondary>information theory</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>Information theory was developed to attack the technical problem of
                        packing the maximum amount of data into the signal carrying telephone calls,
                        but it quickly provided an essential statistical foundation in language
                        analysis and computational linguistics. <citation xml:id="cite_Shannon1948"
                            linkend="Shannon1948">(Shannon 1948)</citation>. Company organization
                        and other examples applying information theory to the analysis of organizing
                        systems can be found in <citation xml:id="cite_Levitin2014"
                            linkend="Levitin2014">(Levitin 2014, Chapter 7)</citation>. </para>
                </footnote></para>
            <para xml:id="para-zq4_myv_qv">Information theory quantifies the amount of organization
                in terms of the number of bits, binary decisions, or rules needed to describe some
                structure or pattern: the more complex or arbitrary a structure is, the more
                information it takes to describe it. For example, the organization of a company with
                a four-level hierarchy and a highly regular reporting structure where everyone
                supervises five people, can be described quite succinctly. In contrast, a company in
                which the number of direct reports at any management level is highly variable
                requires many more rules to describe.</para>
            <para xml:id="para-ar4_myv_qv">Using measures from information theory to assess the
                amount of organization yields the somewhat counter-intuitive result that there is
                less information in the organization of a highly structured system than in a less
                structured one. It might help to flip this around and describe the amount of
                organization in terms of the reciprocal of the information measure. A system that is
                    <quote>highly organized</quote> can be modeled or codified with relatively few
                rules or organizing principles, compared to a less organized system with many
                exceptions, corner cases, or one-off rules.</para>
            <para xml:id="para-gfv_pkv_gv" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added">The
                    <quote>entropy</quote> measure is often used to create predictive models of the
                    <quote>decision tree</quote> variety, which is an algorithm that classifies or
                predicts by making a sequence of logical tests. Each test divides a collection of
                data into sets with less entropy (more predictability). <phrase role="parenthetical"
                    >(See <xref linkend="section-7.5" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase></para>
        </sidebar>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-l1q_tnr_lr"><phrase xml:id="statement-2n-Crowdsourcing"
                role="statement">At some point a collection grows so large that it is not
                economically feasible for people to create bibliographic descriptions or to classify
                each separate resource, unless there are so many users of the collection that their
                aggregated effort is comparably large; this is organizing by
                    <quote>crowdsourcing.</quote></phrase> This leaves two approaches that can be
            done separately or in tandem. <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para xml:id="para-efq_tnr_lr">The simpler approach is to describe sets of
                        resources or documents as a set or group<phrase audience="Archives"
                            revision="4.0" revisionflag="changed">, which is especially sensible for
                            archives with its emphasis on the <glossterm linkend="gloss_fonds"
                                xreflabel="fonds">fonds</glossterm>
                            <phrase role="parenthetical">(see <xref linkend="section-2n.2"
                                />)</phrase></phrase>. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para xml:id="para-ljq_tnr_lr">The second approach is to rely on automated and
                        more general-purpose organizing technologies that organize resources through
                        computational means. Search engines are familiar examples of computational
                        organizing technology, and <xref linkend="section-8.6"/> describes other
                        common techniques in machine learning, clustering, and discriminant analysis
                        that can be used to create a system of categories and to assign resources to
                        them.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para audience="Business" role="contrast" xml:id="para-gnq_tnr_lr" revision="4.0"
            revisionflag="changed"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-gnq_tnr_lr" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>Coase, Ronald</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-gnq_tnr_lr" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>Smith, Adam</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-gnq_tnr_lr" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>Williamson, Oliver</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-gnq_tnr_lr" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>Chandler, Alfred</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-gnq_tnr_lr" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>Simon, Herbert</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-gnq_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>transaction costs</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-gnq_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>costs</primary>
                        <secondary>transaction</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>Finally, we must acknowledge the ways in which information processing and
            telecommunications technologies have transformed and will continue to transform
            organizing systems in every sphere of economic and intellectual activity. A century ago,
            when the telegraph and telephone enabled rapid communication and business coordination
            across large distances, these new technologies enabled the creation of massive
            vertically integrated industrial firms. In the <date>1920s</date>, the Ford Motor
            Company owned coal and iron mines, rubber plantations, railroads, and steel mills so it
            could manage every resource needed in automobile production and reduce the costs and
            uncertainties of finding suppliers, negotiating with them, and ensuring their
            contractual compliance. Adam’s Smith’s invisible hand of the market as an organizing
            mechanism had been replaced by the visible hand of hierarchical management to control
            what Ronald Coase in <date>1937</date> termed <quote>transaction costs</quote> in
                <citetitle pubwork="book" linkend="Coase1937">The Nature of the
            Firm.</citetitle></para>
        <para audience="Business" role="contrast" xml:id="para-arq_tnr_lr" revision="4.0"
            revisionflag="changed"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-arq_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>costs</primary>
                        <secondary>Moore’s law</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-arq_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>Moore’s law</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>In recent decades, a new set of information and computing technologies enabled by
            Moore’s law<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>unlimited computing power, effectively free
            bandwidth, and the Internet<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>have turned Coase upside down,
            leading to entirely new forms of industrial organization made possible as transaction
            costs plummet. When computation and coordination costs drop dramatically, it becomes
            possible for small firms and networks of services (provided by people or by
            computational processes) to out-compete large corporations through more efficient use of
            information resources and services, and through more effective information exchange with
            suppliers and customers, much of it automated. <phrase xml:id="principle-2n-AI-HCI"
                role="principle statement">Herbert Simon, a pioneer in artificial intelligence,
                decision making, and human-computer interaction, recognized the similarities between
                the design of computing systems and human organizations and developed principles and
                mechanisms applicable to both.</phrase><footnote xml:id="endnote-028" label="37"
                audience="Business">
                <para audience="Business" xml:id="para-v5q_tnr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-028">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Business</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-028">
                                <primary>business</primary>
                                <secondary>transaction costs</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-028">
                                <primary>costs</primary>
                                <secondary>transaction</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>Coase won the <date>1991</date> Nobel Prize in economics for his work on
                    transaction costs, which he first published as a graduate student <citation
                        xml:id="cite_Coase1937" linkend="Coase1937">(Coase 1937)</citation>.
                    Berkeley business professor Oliver Williamson received the prize in
                        <date>2009</date> for work that extended Coase’s framework to explain the
                    shift from the hierarchical firm to the network firm <citation
                        xml:id="cite_Williamson1975" linkend="Williamson1975">(Williamson
                        1975</citation>, <citation xml:id="cite_Williamson1998"
                        linkend="Williamson1998">1998)</citation>. The notion of the <quote>visible
                        hand</quote> comes from <citation xml:id="cite_Chandler1977"
                        linkend="Chandler1977">(Chandler 1977)</citation>. Simon won the Nobel Prize
                    in economics in <date>1978</date>, but if there were Nobel Prizes in computer
                    science or management theory he surely would have won them as well. Simon was
                    the author or co-author of four books that have each been cited over 10,000
                    times, including <citation xml:id="cite_Simon1997" linkend="Simon1997">(Simon
                        1997</citation>, <citation xml:id="cite_Simon1996" linkend="Simon1996"
                        >1996)</citation> and <citation xml:id="cite_Newell1972"
                        linkend="Newell1972">(Newell and Simon 1972)</citation>.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-qyq_tnr_lr"><xref linkend="chapter-9" xrefstyle="short"
            />, focuses on the representation of resource descriptions, taking a more technological
            or implementation perspective. <xref linkend="chapter-10" xrefstyle="short"/>, discusses
            how the nature and extent of descriptions determines the capabilities of the
            interactions that locate, compare, combine, or otherwise use resources in
            information-intensive domains.</para>
    </section>
    <?dbfo clear ?>
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-2n.5" label="2.5">
        <title>When Is It Being Organized?</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-2n.5">
                    <primary>organizing</primary>
                    <secondary>when</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm zone="section-2n.5">
                    <primary>temporal</primary>
                    <secondary>parameters</secondary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <blockquote>
            <attribution><citation xml:id="cite_Svenonius2000-1.6" linkend="Svenonius2000"
                    >(Svenonius 2000, p. 194-195)</citation></attribution>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-dcr_tnr_lr"><emphasis><quote>Because bibliographic
                        description, when manually performed, is expensive, it seems likely that the
                            <quote>pre</quote> organizing of information will continue to shift
                        incrementally toward <quote>post</quote>
                organizing.</quote></emphasis></para>
        </blockquote>
        <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-vfr_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-vfr_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>tradeoffs</primary>
                        <secondary>organization versus retrieval</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info><phrase xml:id="statement-2n-ProcessEarlyOrLate" role="statement">The organizing
                system framework recasts the traditional tradeoff between information organization
                and information retrieval as the decision about <emphasis>when</emphasis> the
                organization is imposed.</phrase> We can contrast organization imposed on resources
                <quote>on the way in</quote> when they are created or made part of a collection with
                <quote>on the way out</quote> organization imposed when an interaction with
            resources takes place.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-pjr_tnr_lr">When an author writes a document, he or she
            gives it some internal organization via title, section headings, typographic
            conventions, page numbers, and other mechanisms that identify its parts and relationship
            to each other. The document could also have some external organization implied by the
            context of its publication, such as the name of its author and publisher, its web
            address, and citations or links to other documents or web pages.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-knr_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-knr_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>location</primary>
                        <secondary>digital media metadata</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>Digital photos, videos, and documents are generally organized to some minimal
            degree when they are created because some descriptions, notably time and location, are
            assigned automatically to these types of resources by the technology used to create
            them. At a minimum, these descriptions include the resource’s creation time, storage
            format, and chronologically ordered, auto-assigned filename
                (<filename>IMG00001.JPG</filename>, <filename>IMG00002.JPG</filename>, etc.), but
            often are much more detailed.<footnote xml:id="endnote-029" label="38"
                audience="Computing">
                <para audience="Computing" xml:id="para-brr_tnr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-029">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Computing</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-029">
                                <primary>computing</primary>
                                <secondary>EXIF</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-029">
                                <primary>EXIF</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-029">
                                <primary>computing</primary>
                                <secondary>EXIF</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-029">
                                <primary>chronological ordering</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-029">
                                <primary>numerical ordering</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>Most digital cameras annotate each photo with detailed information about
                    the camera and its settings in the <firstterm xml:id="first_EXIF"><citerefentry
                            xreflabel="Exchangeable Image File Format (EXIF)"
                                ><refentrytitle>Exchangeable Image File
                                Format</refentrytitle><manvolnum>EXIF</manvolnum></citerefentry></firstterm>,
                    and many mobile phones can associate their location along with any digital
                    object they create.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-v5r_tnr_lr"><phrase
                xml:id="statement-2n-BusinessDocumentStructure" role="statement">Digital resources
                created by automated processes generally exhibit a high degree of organization and
                structure because they are generated automatically in conformance with data or
                document schemas.</phrase> These schemas implement the business rules and
            information models for the orders, invoices, payments, and the numerous other document
            types created and managed in business organizing systems.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-vyr_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-vyr_tnr_lr" audience="LIS">
                        <primary>LOC-CN</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-vyr_tnr_lr" audience="LIS">
                        <primary>LOC-SH</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-vyr_tnr_lr" audience="LIS">
                        <primary>ISBN</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>Before a resource becomes part of a library collection, its author-created
            organization is often supplemented by additional information supplied by the publisher
            or other human intermediaries, such as an <firstterm xml:id="first_ISBN"><citerefentry
                    xreflabel="International Standard Book Number (ISBN)"
                        ><refentrytitle>International Standard Book
                        Number</refentrytitle><manvolnum>ISBN</manvolnum></citerefentry></firstterm>
            or <firstterm xml:id="first_LOC-CN"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>Library of Congress
                        Call
                Number</refentrytitle><manvolnum>LOC-CN</manvolnum></citerefentry></firstterm> or
                <firstterm xml:id="first_LOC-SH"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>Library of Congress
                        Subject
                Headings</refentrytitle><manvolnum>LOC-SH</manvolnum></citerefentry></firstterm>. </para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-ncs_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-ncs_tnr_lr" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>Nunberg, Geoff</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>In contrast, <orgname>Google</orgname> and other search engines apply massive
            computational power to analyze the contents and associated structures (like links
            between web pages) to impose organization on resources that have already been published
            or made available so that they can be retrieved in response to a user’s query <quote>on
                the way out.</quote> Google makes use of existing organization within and between
            information resources when it can, but its unparalleled technological capabilities and
            scale yield competitive advantage in imposing organization on information that was not
            previously organized digitally.<footnote xml:id="endnote-030" label="39"
                audience="Computing">
                <para audience="Computing" xml:id="para-lgs_tnr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-030">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Computing</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-030">
                                <primary>library science</primary>
                                <secondary>metadata train wreck</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-030">
                                <primary>computing</primary>
                                <secondary>metadata train wreck</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info> Indeed, <personname><firstname>Geoff</firstname>
                        <surname>Nunberg</surname></personname> criticized <orgname>Google</orgname>
                    for ignoring or undervaluing the descriptive metadata and classifications
                    previously assigned by people and replacing them with algorithmically assigned
                    descriptors, many of which are incorrect or inappropriate.  Calling
                        <application>Google’s Book Search</application> a <quote>disaster for
                        scholars</quote> and a <quote>metadata train wreck,</quote> he lists scores
                    of errors in titles, publication dates, and classifications. For example, he
                    reports that a search on <quote>Internet</quote> in books published before
                        <date>1950</date> yields 527 results. The first 10 hits for Whitman’s
                        <citetitle pubwork="book">Leaves of Grass</citetitle> are variously
                    classified as Poetry, Juvenile Nonfiction, Fiction, Literary Criticism,
                    Biography <symbol>&#38;</symbol> Autobiography, and Counterfeits and
                    Counterfeiting. <citation xml:id="cite_Nunberg2009" linkend="Nunberg2009"
                        >(Nunberg 2009)</citation></para>
            </footnote>
            <phrase xml:id="statement-2n-LinkedDataMovement" role="statement">One reaction to the
                poor quality of some computational description has been the call for libraries to
                put their authoritative bibliographic resources on the open web, which would enable
                reuse of reliable information about books, authors, publishers, places, and subject
                classifications.</phrase> This <quote>linked data</quote> movement is slowly
            gathering momentum.<footnote xml:id="endnote-031" label="40" audience="Web">
                <para audience="Web" xml:id="para-fks_tnr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-031">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Web</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-031" userlevel="Professional">
                                <primary>Web</primary>
                                <secondary>citations</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><citation xml:id="cite_Byrne2010" linkend="Byrne2010">(Byrne and Goddard
                        2010)</citation>.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-qns_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-qns_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>Google</primary>
                        <secondary>personalized ad placement</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-qns_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>search results</primary>
                        <secondary>selection and ranking</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-qns_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>ranking</primary>
                        <secondary>search results</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-qns_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>selection</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info><orgname>Google</orgname> makes almost all of its money through personalized ad
            placement, so much of the selection and ranking of search results is determined
                <quote>on the way out</quote> in the fraction of a second after the user submits a
            query by using information about the user’s search history and current context. Of
            course, this <quote>on the way out</quote> organization is only possible because of the
            more generic organization that Google’s algorithms have imposed <quote>on the way
                in.</quote></para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-prs_tnr_lr"><phrase
                xml:id="statement-2n-FrequentlyUsedThings" role="statement">In many organizing
                systems the nature and extent of organization changes over time as the resources are
                used.</phrase> The arrangement of resources in a kitchen or office changes
            incrementally as <hardware>frequently used things</hardware> end up in the front of the
            pantry, drawer, shelf or filing cabinet or on the top of a pile of papers. Printed books
            or documents acquire margin notes, underlining, turned down pages or coffee cup stains
            that differentiate the most important or most frequently used parts. Digital documents
            do not take on coffee cup stains, but when they are edited, their new revision dates put
            them at the top of directory listings.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-hvs_tnr_lr">The scale of emergent organization of
            websites, photos on <orgname>Flickr</orgname>, blog posts, and other resources that can
            be accessed and used online dwarfs the incremental evolution of individual organizing
            systems. This organization is clearly visible in the pattern of links, tags, or ratings
            that are explicitly associated with these resources, but search engines and advertisers
            also exploit the less visible organization created over time by <phrase
                audience="CORE DS" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added">analyzing interaction
                resources, the recorded</phrase> information about which resources were viewed and
            which links were followed.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-izs_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="def_curation_governance">
                        <primary>governance</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="def_curation_governance">
                        <primary>activities</primary>
                        <secondary>governance</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm significance="preferred" zone="def_curation_governance">
                        <primary>institutional</primary>
                        <secondary>governance</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>The sort of organic or emergent change in organizing systems that takes place
            over time contrasts with the planned and systematic maintenance of organizing systems
            described as <firstterm linkend="gloss_curation" xml:id="first_curation"
                >curation</firstterm> or <firstterm linkend="gloss_governance"
                xml:id="first_governance">governance</firstterm>, two related but distinct
            activities. <phrase role="definition" xml:id="def_curation_governance"><glossterm
                    xml:id="term_curation">Curation</glossterm> usually refers to the methods or
                systems that add value to and preserve resources, while the concept of <glossterm
                    xreflabel="governance" xml:id="term_governance">governance</glossterm> more
                often emphasizes the institutions or organizations that carry out those activities.
                The former is most often used for libraries, museums, or archives and the latter for
                enterprise or inter-enterprise contexts.</phrase>
            <phrase role="parenthetical">(For more discussion, see <xref linkend="section-3.5.4"
                    xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase></para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-edt_tnr_lr">The organizing systems for businesses and
            industries often change because of the development of <foreignphrase xml:lang="Latn">de
                facto</foreignphrase> or <foreignphrase>de jure</foreignphrase> standards, or
            because of regulations, court decisions, or other events or mandates.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-wpy_t5s_sv" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added">We should always consider
            the extent to which people or technology in an organizing system are able to adapt when
            new resources, data, or people enter the picture. When and how much an organizing system
            can be changed depends on the extent of architectural thinking that went into its design
            (see <xref linkend="chapter-1-sidebar-4"/>), because it should be possible to make a
            change to a component without having to rethink the system entirely.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-wbt_y5s_sv" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added">Sometimes what prevents
            adaptation are physical or technological constraints in the implementation of an
            organizing system, as with a desk or closet with fixed <quote>pigeon holes,</quote>
            unmovable shelves, or with a music player with limited allowable formats and/or fixed
            storage capacity. </para>
        <?need 2.5cm ?>
        <para xml:id="para-mnf_bvs_sv" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added">Machine learning
            algorithms use different techniques from those of human organizers; one of the important
            differences is that they're designed to adapt to new inputs—which is why they’re known
            to be <quote>learning.</quote> In contrast, humans differ in how willing we are to
            re-organize to accommodate a different number or a different mix of resources. Without
            procedures in place to support or trigger adaptation, it may be quite difficult for us
            to change how we think or how we organize when our world changes, or even to realize
            that it has changed.</para>
    </section>
    <!--              -->
    <section xml:id="section-2n.6" label="2.6">
        <title>How (or by Whom) Is It Organized?</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-2n.6">
                    <primary>organizing</primary>
                    <secondary>how</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm zone="section-2n.6">
                    <primary>organizing</primary>
                    <secondary>by whom</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm zone="section-2n.6">
                    <primary>organizing</primary>
                    <secondary>professionals</secondary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <blockquote>
            <attribution><citation xml:id="cite_Svenonius2000-1.7" linkend="Svenonius2000"
                    >(Svenonius 2000, p. 26)</citation></attribution>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-zgt_tnr_lr"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-zgt_tnr_lr">
                            <primary>bibliographic</primary>
                            <secondary>universe</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info><emphasis><quote>The rise of the Internet is affecting the actual work of
                        organizing information by shifting it from a relatively few professional
                        indexers and catalogers to the populace at large. An important question
                        today is whether the bibliographic universe can be organized both
                        intelligently (that is, to meet the traditional bibliographic objectives)
                        and automatically.</quote></emphasis></para>
        </blockquote>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-qkt_tnr_lr">In the preceding quote, Svenonius identifies
            three different ways for the <quote>work of organizing information</quote> to be
            performed: by professional indexers and catalogers, by the populace at large, and by
            automated (computerized) processes. Our notion of the organizing system is broader than
            her <quote>bibliographic universe,</quote> making it necessary to extend her taxonomy.
            Authors are increasingly organizing the content they create, and it is important to
            distinguish users in informal and formal or institutional contexts. We have also
            introduced the concept of an organizing <glossterm linkend="gloss_agent"
                xreflabel="agent">agent</glossterm>
            <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref linkend="section-1.6" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>
            to unify organizing done by people and by computer algorithms.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-g4t_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-g4t_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>costs</primary>
                        <secondary>human factors</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info><phrase xml:id="statement-2n-ProfessionalIndexers" role="statement">Professional
                    <jobtitle>indexers</jobtitle> and <jobtitle>catalogers</jobtitle> undergo
                extensive training to learn the concepts, controlled descriptive vocabularies, and
                standard classifications in the particular domains in which they work. Their goal is
                not only to describe individual resources, but to position them in the larger
                collection in which they reside.</phrase><footnote xml:id="endnote-032" label="41"
                audience="LIS">
                <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-zrt_tnr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-032">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>LIS</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-032">
                                <primary>cataloging</primary>
                                <secondary>formal</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-032">
                                <primary>library science</primary>
                                <secondary>education vs practice</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>This is an important distinction in library science education and library
                    practice. Individual resources are described (<quote>formal</quote> cataloging)
                    using <quote>bibliographic languages</quote> and their classification in the
                    larger collection is done using <quote>subject languages</quote>
                    <citation xml:id="cite_Svenonius2000-1.8" linkend="Svenonius2000">(Svenonius
                        2000, Ch. 4 and Ch. 8, respectively)</citation>. These two practices are
                    generally taught in different library school courses because they use different
                    languages, methods and rules and are generally carried out by different people
                    in the library. In other organizations, the resource description (both formal
                    and subject) is created in the same step and by the same person.</para>
            </footnote> They can create and maintain organizing systems with consistent high
            quality, but their work often requires additional research, which is costly.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-tvt_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-tvt_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>NSPO</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>The class of <jobtitle>professional organizers</jobtitle> also includes the
                <jobtitle>employees of commercial information services</jobtitle> like
                <orgname>Westlaw</orgname> and <orgname>LexisNexis</orgname>, who add controlled
            and, often, proprietary metadata to legal and government documents and other news
            sources. <jobtitle>Scientists</jobtitle> and <jobtitle>scholars</jobtitle> with deep
            expertise in a domain often function as the <jobtitle>professional organizers</jobtitle>
            for data collections, scholarly publications and proceedings, and other specialized
            information resources in their respective disciplines. The <firstterm
                xml:id="first_NAPO"><citerefentry xml:id="ref_NAPO">
                    <refentrytitle><orgname>National Association of Professional
                            Organizers</orgname></refentrytitle><manvolnum>NAPO</manvolnum></citerefentry></firstterm>
            claims several thousand members who will organize your <hardware>media
                collection</hardware>, kitchen, closet, garage or entire house or help you downsize
            to a smaller living space.<footnote xml:id="endnote-033" label="42" audience="Business">
                <para audience="Business" xml:id="para-kzt_tnr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-033">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Business</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-033">
                                <primary>business</primary>
                                <secondary>NAPO</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>NAPO: <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.napo.net"><uri>http://www.napo.net</uri></link> The
                    name and scope of this organization seems a bit odd given how much professional
                    organizing takes place in business, science, government, medicine, education,
                    and other domains where closets and garages are not the most important
                    focus.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-cd5_tnr_lr">Many of today’s
                <hardware>content creators</hardware> are unlikely to be <jobtitle>professional
                organizers</jobtitle>, but presumably the <jobtitle>author</jobtitle> best
            understands why something was created and the purposes for which it can be used. To the
            extent that <jobtitle>authors</jobtitle> want to help others find a resource, they will
            assign descriptions or classifications that they expect will be useful to those users.
            But unlike <phrase remap="action"><hardware>professional organizers</hardware></phrase>,
            most <jobtitle>authors</jobtitle> are unfamiliar with controlled vocabularies and
            standard classifications, and as a result their descriptions will be more subjective and
            less consistent.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-wg5_tnr_lr">Similarly, most of us do not
            hire professionals to organize the resources we collect and use in our personal lives,
            and thus our organizing systems reflect our individual preferences and
            idiosyncrasies.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-nk5_tnr_lr">Non-author users in the
                <quote>populace at large</quote> are most often creating organization for their own
            benefit. These <hardware>ordinary users</hardware> are unlikely to use standard
            descriptors and classifications, and the organization they impose sometimes so closely
            reflects their own perspective and goals that it is not useful for others. <phrase
                xml:id="statement-2n-CommunityContent"  role="statement">Fortunately most users of  <quote>Web 2.0</quote> or
                    <quote>community content</quote> applications at least partly recognize that the
                organization of resources emerges from the aggregated contributions of all users,
                which provides incentive to use less egocentric <firstterm
                    linkend="gloss_descriptor">descriptors</firstterm> and <firstterm
                    linkend="gloss_classifications">classifications</firstterm>.</phrase> The
            staggering number of users and resources on the most popular applications inevitably
            leads to <quote>tag convergence</quote> simply because of the statistics of large sample
            sizes.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ovv_tnr_lr">Finally, the vast size of the web and the
            even greater size of the <quote>deep</quote> or invisible web, composed of the
            information stores of business and proprietary information services, makes it impossible
            to imagine today that it could be organized by anything other than the massive
            computational power of search engine providers like <orgname>Google</orgname> and
                <orgname>Microsoft</orgname>.<phrase revision="4.0" revisionflag="added"
                audience="CORE DS"> Likewise, data mining, predictive analytics, recommendation
                systems, and many other application areas that involve computational modeling and
                classification simply could not be done any other way.</phrase><footnote 
                xml:id="endnote-035" label="43" audience="Web">
                <para audience="Web" xml:id="para-mzv_tnr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-035">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Web</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-035">
                                <primary>Web</primary>
                                <secondary>hidden web</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><citation xml:id="cite_He2007" linkend="He2007">(He et al.
                        2007)</citation> estimate that there are hundreds of thousands of websites
                    and databases whose content is accessible only through query forms and web
                    services, and there are over a million of those. The amount of content in this
                    hidden web is many hundreds of times larger than that accessible in the surface
                    or visible web.</para>
                <para audience="Web" xml:id="para-ddw_tnr_lr">See <link
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.worldwidewebsize.com/"
                            ><uri>http://www.worldwidewebsize.com/</uri></link> for estimates of the
                    size of the visible web calculated from comparisons of results from search
                    engines.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para xml:id="para-yahoo-wang-filo" audience="Business" revision="4.0"
            revisionflag="changed"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-yahoo-wang-filo" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>Yahoo!</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-yahoo-wang-filo" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>Yang, Jerry</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-yahoo-wang-filo" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>Filo, David</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>Nevertheless, in the earliest days of the web, significant <phrase remap="action"
                    ><hardware>human effort</hardware></phrase> was applied to organize it. Most
            notable is <orgname>Yahoo!</orgname>, founded by
                    <personname><firstname>Jerry</firstname>
                <surname>Yang</surname></personname> and <personname><firstname>David</firstname>
                <surname>Filo</surname></personname> in <date>1994</date> as a directory of favorite
            websites. For many years the Yahoo! homepage was the best way to find relevant websites
            by browsing the extensive system of classification. Today’s Yahoo! homepage emphasizes a
            search engine that makes it appear more like <application>Google</application> or
                <application>Microsoft Bing</application>, but the <application>Yahoo!</application>
            directory can still be found if you search for it.</para>
    </section>
    <!--              -->
    <?dbfo clear ?>
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-2n.7" label="2.7" revision="3.0" revisionflag="added">
        <title>Where is it being Organized?</title>
        <blockquote>
            <attribution>
                <citation xml:id="cite_Svenonius2000-1.3.7" linkend="Svenonius2000">(Svenonius 2000,
                    p. 120)</citation></attribution>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ewj_tnr_where"><emphasis><quote>Bibliographic control
                        requires fixing a document in the bibliographic universe by its space-time
                        coordinates.</quote></emphasis>
            </para>
        </blockquote>
        <para xml:id="para-br4_myv_qv">Having identified the resources, reasoned about our
            motivations, limited the scope and scale, and determined when and by whom the
            organization will occur, we come finally to the question of where the resources are
            being organized. </para>
        <para xml:id="para-cr4_myv_qv">In ordinary use, <quote>Where</quote> refers to a physical
            location. But the answer to <quote>where?</quote> often depends on whether we are asking
            about the current location, a past location, or an intended destination for resources
            that are in transit or in process. The answer to the question <quote>where?</quote> can
            take a lot of different forms. We can talk about an abstract space like <quote>a library
                shelf</quote> or we can talk about <quote>the hidden compartment in Section XY at
                the Library of Congress,</quote> as depicted in the 2004 movie <quote>National
                Treasure.</quote> We can answer <quote>where?</quote> with a description of a set of
            environmental conditions that best suit a class of wildlife, or a tire, or a sleeping
            bag. We can answer <quote>where?</quote> with <quote>Renaissance Europe</quote> or
                <quote>Colonial Williamsburg.</quote>
            <quote>Where?</quote> can be a place in a mental construct, or even a place in an
            imagined location.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-dr4_myv_qv">In the architectural design of an organizing system, its
            physical location is usually not a primary concern. In most organizing systems, the
            matter of where the organizing system and the resources are located can be abstracted
            away. So, in practice, resource location often is not as important as the other
            questions here. Physical constraints of the storage location should generally be
            relegated to an implementation concern rather than an architectural one. The
            construction of a special display structure for a valuable resource is not an
            independent design dimension; it is just the implementation of the user interface.
                <phrase role="parenthetical">(See <xref linkend="section-6.7"/>)</phrase></para>
        <para xml:id="para-er4_myv_qv">Physical resources are often stored where it is convenient
            and efficient to do so, whether in ordinary warehouses, offices, storerooms, shelves,
            cabinets, and closets. It can be necessary to adapt an organizing system to
            characteristics of its physical environment, but this could undermine architectural
            thinking and make it harder to maintain the organization over time, as the collection
            evolves in scope and scale. <phrase role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                    linkend="section-3.3.1"/>)</phrase></para>
        <para xml:id="para-fr4_myv_qv">Digital resources, on the other hand, are increasingly
            organized and stored <quote>in the cloud</quote> and their actual locations are
            invisible, indeterminate, and generally irrelevant, except in situations where the
            servers and the information they hold may be subject to laws or practices of their
            physical location. For example, a controversy arose in Canada in 2013 when researchers
            discovered that Internet service providers were, for various technical and business
            reasons, routinely routing trans-Canada web traffic through the United States. Because
            Canada has no jurisdiction over data traveling through cables and servers in another
            country, there was considerable outcry among Canadians who were concerned that their
            personal information was being subjected to the privacy laws and practices of another
            country without their knowledge or consent.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-gr4_myv_qv">Sometimes location functions as an organizing principle in
            its own right, which in practice essentially collapses many of these architectural
            distinctions. This is frequently the case in our personal organizing systems, where we
            may exploit the innate human capability for spatial memory by always putting specific
            things like keys, eyeglasses, and cell phones in the same place, which makes them easy
            to find. But we can also see this happening in systems as complex and varied as: real
            estate information systems; wayfinding systems, such as road signage or mile markers;
            standardized international customs forms with position-specific data fields; geographic
            information systems; air, ground, sea, and space traffic control systems; and historic
            landmark preservation.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-hr4_myv_qv">In<phrase role="parenthetical">
                <xref linkend="section-3.3.2"/> we consider the organization of the land, built
                environments, and wayfinding systems.</phrase>
            <xref linkend="section-6.5"/> discusses the structural perspective on resource
            relationships, and in some systems, it may be very significant where resources are
            located in relation to one another. In <xref linkend="sidebar_Barnes_Collection"/>, for
            example, works of art are physically grouped to enunciate common characteristics.
            Conversely, zoos do not mix the kangaroos with the wild dogs, and the military does not
            mix the ingredients for chemical weapons (at least, not until they plan to use them).
            There are also circumstances where resources can only exist in (or are particularly
            suited to) particular environments, such as the conditions required to grow wine grapes
            or mushrooms, or store spent nuclear fuel. UPS advises companies on where to put their
            warehouses and shipment centers. These are more substantial than questions of
            presentation, but it is debatable whether it falls under the storage or logic tier (you
            could have the principle of <quote>keep the mushrooms somewhere moist</quote> while not
            dictating where particularly).</para>
        <para xml:id="para-ir4_myv_qv">Sometimes the location of an organizing system seems
            particularly salient, as in the design of cities where the street plan can be essential
            for orientation and navigation, and is embodied in zoning, voting, and other explicit
            organization, as well as in informal organization like neighborhood identity. But even
            here, it is really the people who live in the city who are being organized and whose
            interactions with the city and with each other are being encouraged or discouraged, not
            the physical location on which they live.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-jr4_myv_qv">Indeed, in designing an organizing system you will often find
            that questions about location tumble naturally out of the other five design dimensions.
            For instance, questions about <quote>when,</quote>
            <quote>what,</quote> and <quote>where</quote> are often inseparable, particularly when
            an organizing system is subject to outside regulations, which tend to have geographical
            jurisdictions. <quote>Where</quote> is also commonly bound up with <quote>who</quote>
            and <quote>why,</quote> when locational challenges or opportunities faced by a system's
            creators or users necessitate special design consideration. <phrase role="parenthetical"
                >(See <xref linkend="section-4.5.2"/>)</phrase></para>
        <para xml:id="para-kr4_myv_qv">Location can be critically important to an organizing
            system—too important, in fact, to be considered alone. The question of
                <quote>where?</quote> is best considered in context of the other five design
            dimensions as a whole; a narrow focus on where the resources are being organized too
            often privileges past convention over architectural thinking and perpetuates legacy
            issues and poorly organized systems.</para>
        <!-- When location is a constraint, it will be identified as such in the other questions. 
                Surely in describing many resources and to enable interaction 
                it is essential to say where the resource is located. Location, 
                and the ability to describe location, is very important. 
                But the location, while a grounded fact, is a mere contingent fact, 
                and the fact that many resources and interactions have spatial locations 
                should not force us to ask explicitly about location at the top-level 
                when designing or describing the design of an Organizing System. 
                
                In designing an Organizing System, the location for the resources, or for where
                interactions can occur, tumbles out of the other five design questions. It is not
                that location is unimportant, it is that location is determined by those other
                concerns. If location is not constrained by the other questions then it is a wider
                space for flexibility in implementation. If there are constraints, the other
                questions will highlight the tradeoffs worth considering. Location should only be
                considered in the whole. For those Organizing Systems where location matters, it is
                too important to be asked alone. Doing so will privilege past convention and
                perpetuate poorly organized systems.
                
                When we represent information, whether with ink on paper, with Braille dots, or
                with pixels on a screen, the precise or relative position of text and images can be
                a factor in cognition, or it can be a design constraint imposed by regulation.
                International shipping and customs agencies still use archaic paper-based forms
                whose interpretation rely upon physical masks that expose only the data that is
                found at designated locations on the underlying page. 
            -->
    </section>
    <!-- ###################### SECTION ########################################### -->
    
    <section xml:id="section-2n.8" label="2.8">
        <title>Key Points in Chapter Two</title>
        <qandaset role="quiz">
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative">How does a <quote>design
                            questions</quote> or <quote>dimensional</quote> perspective on the
                        design of organizing systems complement the familiar use of categories like
                        library and museum?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para audience="CORE"><xref endterm="statement-dimensional-perspective"
                            linkend="statement-dimensional-perspective" role="transclusion"/></para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-2n.1"/>)</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            
            <qandaentry>
                <question><para>Why is the question <quote>What is a thing?</quote> so fundamental and challenging?</para></question>
                <answer><para><xref linkend="statement-thing" endterm="statement-thing" role="transclusion"/></para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-2n.2"/>)</para></answer>
            </qandaentry>
            
            <qandaentry>
                <question><para>How are organizing systems for physical resources and those for digital resources
                        fundamentally different?</para></question>
                <answer><para><xref linkend="statement-2n-PhysicalVsDigital" endterm="statement-2n-PhysicalVsDigital"
                            role="transclusion"/></para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-2n.2"/>)</para></answer>
            </qandaentry>
            
            <qandaentry>
                <question><para>Why is it challenging to decide on the unit of organization for information content?</para></question>
                <answer><para><xref linkend="statement-2n-UnitOfOrganization" endterm="statement-2n-UnitOfOrganization"
                            role="transclusion"/></para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-2n.2"/>)</para></answer>
            </qandaentry>
            
            <qandaentry audience="Archives">
                <question><para>What is the essential purpose of any organizing system?</para></question>
                <answer><para><xref linkend="principle-2n-EssentialPurpose" endterm="principle-2n-EssentialPurpose"
                            role="transclusion"/></para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-2n.3"/>)</para></answer>
            </qandaentry>
            
            <qandaentry>
                <question><para>What are the primary purposes for the organizing systems in libraries, museums, and
                        archives?</para></question>
                <answer><para><xref linkend="statement-2n-PrimaryEmphasis" endterm="statement-2n-PrimaryEmphasis"
                            role="transclusion"/></para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-2n.3"/>)</para></answer>
            </qandaentry>
            
            <qandaentry>
                <question><para>What kinds of documents are businesses and governmental agencies required to keep?</para></question>
                <answer><para><xref linkend="statement-RequiredRecords" endterm="statement-RequiredRecords"
                            role="transclusion"/></para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-2n.3"/>)</para></answer>
            </qandaentry>
            
            
            <qandaentry>
                <question><para>What is the value created if interaction traces can be turned into interaction
                        resources?</para></question>
                <answer><para>If a system can turn its interaction traces into interaction resources, additional value can
                        be created by analyzing these resources to enhance the interactions, to
                        suggest new ones, or make predictions about how individual users or groups
                        of them will behave.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical" >(See <xref
                            linkend="section-2n.3"/>)</para></answer>
            </qandaentry>
            
            <qandaentry>
                <question><para>Why is efficiency too narrow a measure for evaluating organizing systems?</para></question>
                <answer><para>Resources are always organized in ways that are designed to allocate value for some people
                        (e.g., the owners of the resources, or the most frequent users of them) and
                        not for others.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical" >(See <xref
                            linkend="section-2n.3"/>)</para></answer>
            </qandaentry>
            
            <qandaentry>
                <question><para>What lessons from applied behavioral economics about how people make decisions have
                        implications for the design of organizing systems?</para></question>
                <answer><para>Subtle differences in resource arrangement, the number and framing of choices, and default
                        values can have substantial effects on the decisions people make.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical" >(See <xref
                            linkend="section-2n.3"/>)</para></answer>
            </qandaentry>
            
            <qandaentry>
                <question><para>Why might merchants or firms differ in the extent or granularity of their product
                        descriptions?</para></question>
                <answer><para>Different merchants or firms might make different decisions about the extent or granularity of
                        description when they assign SKUs because of differences in suppliers,
                        targeted customers, or other business strategies.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical" >(See <xref
                            linkend="section-2n.4"/>)</para></answer>
            </qandaentry>
            
            <qandaentry>
                <question><para>What are some of the potential downsides to automated resource description?</para></question>
                <answer><para>A detailed description produced by sensors or computers can seem more accurate or
                        authoritative than a simpler one created by a human observer, even if the
                        latter would be more useful for the intended purposes. Detailed transaction
                        data can be used to violate privacy and civil rights.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical" >(See <xref
                            linkend="section-2n.4"/>)</para></answer>
            </qandaentry>
            
            <qandaentry>
                <question><para>How does the number of resources in a collection affect the amount of resource description and
                        organization required?</para></question>
                <answer><para>Organizing more resources requires more descriptions to distinguish any particular resource
                        from the rest, and more constraining organizing principles. Similar
                        resources need to be grouped or classified to emphasize the most important
                        distinctions among the complete set of resources in the collection.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical" >(See <xref
                            linkend="section-2n.4"/>)</para></answer>
            </qandaentry>
            
            <qandaentry>
                <question><para>How is organizing <quote>on the way in</quote> different from organizing <quote>on the way
                            out</quote>?</para></question>
                <answer><para>We can contrast organization imposed on resources <quote>on the way in</quote> when they are
                        created or made part of a collection with <quote>on the way out</quote>
                        organization imposed when an interaction with resources takes place.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical" >(See <xref
                            linkend="section-2n.5"/>)</para></answer>
            </qandaentry>
            
            <qandaentry>
                <question><para>Why do digital resources created by automated processes exhibit a high degree of organization
                        and structure?</para></question>
                <answer><para>Digital resources created by automated processes generally exhibit a high degree of
                        organization and structure because they are generated automatically in
                        conformance with data or document schemas.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical" >(See <xref
                            linkend="section-2n.5"/>)</para></answer>
            </qandaentry>
            
            <qandaentry userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                <question>
                    <para>What kinds of organizing systems would be impossible to create without the
                        use of massive computational power?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para>The vast size of the web and the even greater size of the
                            <quote>deep</quote> or invisible web makes it impossible to imagine
                        today that it could be organized by anything other than the massive
                        computational power of search engine providers like Google and Microsoft.
                        Likewise, data mining, predictive analytics, recommendation systems, and
                        many other application areas that involve computational modeling and
                        classification simply could not be done any other way.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref linkend="section-2n.6"
                        />)</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            
            
        </qandaset>
    </section>
    <!--              -->
</chapter>
