<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.0 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="chapter-11" label="11"><title>The Organizing System Roadmap</title>
    <info>
        <author><personname><firstname>Robert</firstname><othername>J.</othername><surname>Glushko</surname></personname></author>
    </info>
    
    <!--              -->
    <section xml:id="section-11.1" label="11.1"><title>Introduction</title>
        <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.1">
                <primary>organizing system</primary>
                <secondary>roadmap</secondary>
            </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
        
        <note userlevel="Editor" xml:id="note-ch10-Editor-isf_ybs_lr">
            <title>Editors' Note</title>
            <para xml:id="para-ish_54r_lr">With 9 and 10, I think an emphasis on the <quote>how to
                    think about/address/confront challenges in organization in novel terms</quote>
                (the aforementioned 9.5.2, 10.5.2) is important. More?</para>
            <para xml:id="para-awh_54r_lr">And I think 10 could use an extended conclusion. This is
                your opportunity to deliver a polemic, expound a philosophy, incite
                revolution!</para>
            <para>More on infrastructure, inertia, more STO stuff.</para>
        </note>
        
        <sidebar xml:id="ch10-stats" userlevel="Editor" condition="epub3 print" role="statistics">
            <?dbhtml sidebar-width="60%"?>
            <?dbhtml float-type="right"?>
            <?dbfo sidebar-width="60%"?>
            <?dbfo float-type="inside"?>
            <informalfigure xml:id="inf-fig-ch10-stats">
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="Visualisations/ch10-stats.png" format="JPG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                        <phrase role="ALT descriptive">This graphic describes the content breakdown
                            of the chapter. A wheel with colored segments depicts core content
                            versus disciplinary content in this chapter, and a bar chart illustrates
                            the disciplinary content distribution. In this chapter, Business notes
                            predominate, then Computing, then LIS, and some Museums. There are no
                            Archives, CogSci, IA, Law, Linguistics, Philosophy, or Web notes in this
                            chapter.</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
        </sidebar>
        
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-gzh_54r_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-gzh_54r_lr">
                        <primary>tradeoffs</primary>
                        <secondary>what, why, when, by whom</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info><xref linkend="chapter-1" xrefstyle="short"/> defined an organizing system as
                <quote>an intentionally arranged collection of resources and the interactions they
                support.</quote> An organizing system emerges as the result of decisions about
                <emphasis role="bold">what</emphasis> is organized, <emphasis role="bold"
                >why</emphasis> it is organized, <emphasis role="bold">how much</emphasis> it is
            organized, <emphasis role="bold">when</emphasis> it is organized, and <emphasis
                role="bold">how or by whom</emphasis> it is organized. These decisions and the
            tradeoffs they embody are manifested in the four common activities of organizing
                systems<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>selecting resources, organizing them, designing and
            supporting interactions with them, and maintaining them<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>which we
            described in Chapter 2. Chapters 4-10 progressively explained each of the parts of the
            organizing system: resources, resource descriptions, resource categories and
            collections, and interactions with resources<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>introducing
            additional concepts and methods associated with each of these parts.</para>
        <note userlevel="Editor">
            <para xml:id="para-hwz_jvg_hv">Chapter 11 on the lifecycle and especially 11.6,
                Operating and Maintaining an Organizing System does a decent job but we need to get
                more of it into 2. 10 also takes an institutional perspective; maybe 2 can do more
                of it from an individual one. </para>
            <para xml:id="para-sgz_nvg_hv">11.5.2 architectural thinking should be revisited in the
                light of "need to be ready to learn"</para>
        </note>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-bd3_54r_lr">Along the way we described many types of
            organizing systems. Sometimes we discussed broad categories of organizing systems, like
            those for libraries, museums, business information systems, and compositions of
            web-based services. At other times we described specific instances of organizing
            systems, like those in the <application>Seed Library</application>, the
                <application>Flickr photo sharing site</application>, <orgname>Amazon’s drop
                shipment store</orgname>, and your home kitchen or closet.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-oh3_54r_lr">We can now build on the foundation created by
            Chapters 1-10 to create a <quote>roadmap</quote> that organizes and summarizes the
            design issues and choices that emerge during an organizing system’s lifecycle. These
            design choices follow patterns that help us understand existing organizing systems
            better, while also suggesting how to invent new ones by making a different set of design
            choices.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-fm3_54r_lr"><phrase role="parenthetical">The roadmap is
                extensively annotated with references to the preceding chapters where the issues and
                choices mentioned in the roadmap were introduced and discussed in detail.
            </phrase>We will use this roadmap to analyze a variety of case study examples in <xref
                linkend="chapter-12" xrefstyle="short"/>, and to explore the <quote>design
                neighborhood</quote> around each of them. The design questions from <xref
                linkend="chapter-1" xrefstyle="short"/> serve as a template to give each case study
            the same structure, which we hope enables instructors, students, and others who read
            this book to add to this collection of case studies by contributing their own at <link
                xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xlink:href="http://DisciplineOfOrganizing.org"
                ><uri>DisciplineOfOrganizing.org</uri></link>.</para>
        <important role="editorial" xml:id="nav-ch10">
            <title>Navigating This Chapter</title>
            <para xml:id="para-vq3_54r_lr">We begin with a look at <xref linkend="section-11.2"/>
                which proposes four phases, each of which is discussed in its own section. The first
                phase, which largely determines the extent and complexity of the resource
                descriptions needed for organizing and interactions, is  <xref
                    linkend="section-11.3"/>. The second phase, which is highly shaped by economic
                factors and technology constraints or choices, is <xref linkend="section-11.4"/>.
                    <xref linkend="section-11.5"/>, emphasizes the need for clearly separating
                requirements from implementation, a principle we call architectural thinking. The
                final phase is discussed in <xref linkend="section-11.6"/>, where we distinguish the
                maintenance of specific resources and descriptions from the maintenance of the
                system as a whole. </para>
        </important>
    </section>
    <!--              -->
    <?dbfo clear ?>
    <?need 7.5cm ?>
    
    <section xml:id="section-11.2" label="11.2"><title>The Organizing System Lifecycle</title>
        <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.2">
                <primary>organizing system</primary>
                <secondary>lifecycle</secondary>
            </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
        
        
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-lw3_54r_lr">System lifecycle models exhibit great
            variety; for our purposes it suffices to use a generic four-phase model that
            distinguishes a domain definition and scoping phase, a requirements phase, a design and
            implementation phase, and an operational and maintenance phase. These phases are brief
            and mostly inseparable for some simple organizing systems, more sequential for others,
            and more systematic and iterative for complex organizing systems.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-t1j_54r_lr" revision="3.0" revisionflag="changed">Most of
            the specific decisions that must be made for an organizing system are strongly shaped by
            the initial decisions about its domain, scope (the breadth or variety of the resources),
            and scale (the number of resource instances). In organizing systems with limited scope
            and scale, most of these decisions are made in an informal, unanalyzed, and holistic
            manner. For example, when we arrange our bookshelves or closets it is not necessary to
            think explicitly about scoping, requirements, design, implementation, and operational
            phases. For complex organizing systems, however, especially those in
            information-intensive domains, it is important to follow a more systematic
            methodology.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-ffj_54r_lr" audience="CORE" revision="3.0" revisionflag="added">Initial
            decisions about scope and requirements can create lasting technology and process
            legacies that impact operational efficiency and flexibility. They can also have profound
            and unforeseen ramifications for the users of the system and other people affected by
            the work the system enables. A rigorous, well-documented planning process can help
            organizers minimize unfair and ineffective outcomes, justify their difficult tradeoffs
            and decisions, and figure out what went wrong so they can learn from their
            mistakes.</para>
        <para revision="3.0" revisionflag="added">The consequences of releasing technical systems
            and tools into the world always include social, business, political, and legal
            dimensions in addition to technical ones. Some of these implications are due to the
            context in which the system will operate <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref
                    linkend="section-10.4"/>)</phrase>. Others are due to the fact that the work of
            organizing system designers, architects, and developers is shaped by their experiences,
            values, beliefs, and circumstances—the often hidden constraints and influences of their
            social position, education, cultural context, and mental models of the world.
            Inevitably, the work of information professionals involves <quote>carving up the world
                at its joints,</quote> creating classifications, models, and architectures that
            support interactions with resources. In practice this often translates to creating
            artificial <quote>joints</quote> where none truly exist, which will always favor some
            and injure others. No modeling is ever completely faithful to reality for all people
            with all experiences (nor is it intended to be), so those people not considered target
            users for a system, or who have unique circumstances, may end up feeling slighted or
            ignored and may actually suffer as a result.</para>
    </section>
    <!--              -->
    <?dbfo clear ?>
    <?need 7.5cm ?>
    
    <section xml:id="section-11.3" label="11.3"><title>Defining and Scoping the Organizing System Domain</title>
        <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.3">
                <primary>organizing system</primary>
                <secondary>domain</secondary>
                <tertiary>defining and scoping</tertiary>
            </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
        
        
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-yjj_54r_lr"><phrase role="statement">The most fundamental
                decision for an organizing system is defining its <glossterm linkend="gloss_domain"
                    >domain</glossterm>, the set or type of resources that are being
                organized.</phrase> This is why <quote>What is Being Organized?</quote>
            <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref linkend="section-2n.2" xrefstyle="short"
                />)</phrase> was the first of the design decisions we introduced in <xref
                linkend="chapter-1" xrefstyle="short"/>.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-z4j_54r_lr">We refine how we think about an organizing
            system domain by breaking it down into five interrelated aspects: <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para xml:id="para-ctj_54r_lr">the scope and scale of the collection</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para xml:id="para-qwj_54r_lr">the number and nature of users</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para xml:id="para-d1k_54r_lr">the time span or lifetime over which the
                        organizing system will operate</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para xml:id="para-pdk_54r_lr">the physical or technological environment in
                        which the organizing system is situated</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para xml:id="para-bhk_54r_lr">the relationship of the organizing system to
                        other ones that overlap with it in domain or scope</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <phrase>Addressing these issues is a prerequisite for prioritizing requirements for the
                organizing system, proposing the principles of its design, and implementing the
                organizing system.</phrase></para>
        <!--              -->
        <section xml:id="section-11.3.1" label="11.3.1"><title>Scope and Scale of the Collection</title>
            <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.3.1">
                    <primary>collection</primary>
                    <secondary>scope and scale</secondary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="section-11.3.1">
                    <primary>scope</primary>
                    <secondary>of collection</secondary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="section-11.3.1">
                    <primary>scale</primary>
                    <secondary>of collection</secondary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
            
            
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-alk_54r_lr"><phrase role="principle statement">The
                        <glossterm linkend="gloss_scope">scope</glossterm> of a collection is the
                    dominant factor in the design of an organizing system, because it largely
                    determines the extent and complexity of the resource descriptions needed by
                    organizing principles and interactions<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref
                            linkend="section-5.3.1.3" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>. The impact of
                    broad scope arises more from the heterogeneity of the resources in a collection
                    than its absolute scale.</phrase>
                <phrase role="principle statement">It takes more effort to manage a broad and large
                    collection than a narrow and small one; it takes less effort to manage a large
                    collection if it has a narrow scope.</phrase> A cattle ranch can get by with
                just one worker for every thousand cows, unlike zoos, which typically have a small
                number of instances of many types of animals. A zoo needs many more workers because
                each animal type and sometimes even individual animals can have distinct
                requirements for their arrangement and care.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-gqk_54r_lr"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-gqk_54r_lr">
                            <primary>data science</primary>
                            <secondary>in resource description</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                        
                    </itermset>
                </info>Consider a business information system being designed to contain millions of
                highly structured and similar instances of a small number of related resource types,
                such as purchase orders and their corresponding invoices.<footnote
                    xml:id="endnote-543" label="623" audience="Computing">
                    <para audience="Computing" xml:id="para-u5k_54r_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-543">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Computing</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-543">
                                    <primary>computing</primary>
                                    <secondary>transactional document</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>For some kinds of resources with highly regular structure, the
                        distinction between the resource and its description is a bit arbitrary. A
                        transactional document like a payment contains at its core a specification
                        of the amount paid, which we could consider the payment resource.
                        Information about the payer, the payee, the reason for the payment, and
                        other essential information might be viewed as descriptions of the payment
                        resource. In a payment or financial management system, the entire document
                        might be treated as the resource.</para>
                </footnote> The analysis to determine the appropriate properties and principles for
                resource description and organization is straightforward, and any order or invoice
                is an equally good instance to study.<footnote xml:id="endnote-544" label="624"
                    audience="Computing">
                    <para audience="Computing" xml:id="para-nzk_54r_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-544">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Computing</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-544">
                                    <primary>model-driven</primary>
                                    <secondary>architectures</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-544">
                                    <primary>computing</primary>
                                    <secondary>model-driven architecture</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>The results of this analysis can be represented in a conceptual model
                        or document /database schema that can guide the automated creation of the
                        resource instances and their descriptions<phrase role="parenthetical">
                                (<xref linkend="section-5.3.1.2" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>.
                        Furthermore, these models or schemas can also be used in
                            <quote>model-based</quote> or <quote>model-driven</quote> architectures
                        to generate much of the software that implements the functionality to store
                        the instances and interchange them with other information systems;
                            <quote>imagine if the construction worker could take his blueprint,
                            crank it through a machine, and have the foundation for the building
                            simply appear.</quote> Quote comes from <citation
                            xml:id="cite_Miller2003" linkend="Miller2003">(Miller and Mukerji
                            2003)</citation>. See also <citation xml:id="cite_Kleppe2003"
                            linkend="Kleppe2003">(Kleppe, Warmer, and Bast 2003)</citation>.</para>
                </footnote></para>
           
            <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-b2l_54r_lr">Contrast this large but
                very narrow collection with a small but very broad one that contains a thousand
                highly variable instances of dozens of different resource types. This heterogeneity
                makes it difficult to determine if an instance is representative of its resource
                type, and every resource might need to be analyzed. This variability implies a large
                and diverse set of resource descriptions where individual resource instances might
                not be described with much precision because it costs too much to do it
                    manually<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref linkend="section-5.3.6.1"
                        xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>. We can extrapolate to understand why
                organizing systems whose resource collections are both broad and deep, like those of
                    <application>Amazon</application> or <application>eBay</application>, have come
                to rely on machine learning techniques to identify description properties and
                construct resource taxonomies<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref
                        linkend="section-5.3.6.4" xrefstyle="short"/>, <xref
                        linkend="section-7.5.3.3" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>.<footnote
                    xml:id="endnote-545" label="625" audience="Computing">
                    <para audience="Computing" xml:id="para-ljl_54r_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-545">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Computing</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-545" userlevel="Professional">
                                    <primary>computing</primary>
                                    <secondary>citations</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>See <citation xml:id="cite_Chen2010" linkend="Chen2010">(Chen, Li,
                            Liang, and Zhang 2010)</citation>, <citation xml:id="cite_Pohs2013"
                            linkend="Pohs2013">(Pohs 2013)</citation>.</para>
                </footnote></para>
            <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-znl_54r_lr"><info><itermset>
                <indexterm zone="para-znl_54r_lr">
                    <primary>abstraction</primary>
                    <secondary>level</secondary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="para-znl_54r_lr">
                <primary>costs</primary>
                <secondary>imprecision</secondary>
            </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>A partial remedy or compromise when the resource instances are highly
                dissimilar is to define resource types more broadly or abstractly, reducing the
                overall number of types. We illustrated this approach in <xref
                    linkend="section-8.2.2.1" xrefstyle="short"/> when we contrasted how kitchen
                goods might be categorized broadly in a department store but much more precisely in
                a wholesale kitchen supply store. The broader categories in the department store blur many of the
                differences between instances, but in doing so yield a small set of common
                properties that can be used to describe them. Because these common properties will
                be at a higher level of abstraction, using them to describe resources will require
                less expertise and probably less effort<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref
                        linkend="section-5.3.1.3" xrefstyle="short"/>, <xref linkend="section-7.4.1"
                        xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>. However, this comes at a cost: <phrase
                    role="statement">Poets, painters, composers, sculptors, technical writers, and
                    programmers all create resources, but describing all of them with a
                        <quote>creator</quote> property, as the <glossterm linkend="gloss_DC">Dublin
                        Core</glossterm> requires, loses a great deal of precision.</phrase>
            </para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ksl_54r_lr"><info><itermset>
                <indexterm zone="para-ksl_54r_lr">
                    <primary>constraints</primary>
                    <secondary>environment</secondary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info><phrase role="statement">Challenges caused by the scale of a collection
                    are often related to constraints imposed by the physical or technological
                    environment in which the collection exists that limit how large the collection
                    can be or how it can be organized.</phrase>
                <phrase role="parenthetical">(See <xref linkend="section-3.3.1" xrefstyle="short"
                    />)</phrase> Only a few dozen books can fit on a small bookshelf but thousands
                of books can fit in your two-car garage, which is a typical size because most people
                and families do not have more than two cars. On the other hand, if you are a
                Hollywood mogul, superstar athlete, or sultan with a collection of hundreds of cars,
                a two-car garage is orders of magnitudes too small to store your
                    collection.<footnote xml:id="endnote-546" label="626" audience="Business">
                    <para audience="Business" xml:id="para-xwl_54r_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-546">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Business</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-546">
                                    <primary>business</primary>
                                    <secondary>auto collectors</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>See <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="http://autos.ca.msn.com/editors-picks/the-worlds-biggest-car-collectors"
                                ><uri>http://autos.ca.msn.com/editors-picks/the-worlds-biggest-car-collectors</uri></link>.</para>
                </footnote>
                <phrase role="statement">Even collections of digital things can be limited in size
                    by their technological environment, which you might have discovered when you ran
                    out of space for your songs and photos on your portable media
                player.</phrase></para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-hbm_54r_lr">Estimating the ultimate size of a
                collection at the beginning of an organizing system’s lifecycle can reduce scaling
                issues related to storage space for the resources or for their descriptions. Other
                problems of scale are more fundamental. Larger collections need more people to
                organize and maintain them, creating communication and coordination problems that
                grow much faster than the collection, especially when the collection is distributed
                in different locations.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-fgm_54r_lr"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-fgm_54r_lr">
                            <primary>standardization</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info><phrase role="statement">The best way to prevent problems of scope and scale
                    is through standardization.</phrase> Standardization of resources can take place
                if they are created by automated means so that every instance conforms to a schema
                or model<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref linkend="section-7.5.2"
                        xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>.<footnote xml:id="endnote-547" label="627"
                    audience="Computing">
                    <para audience="Computing" xml:id="para-zkm_54r_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-547">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Computing</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-547">
                                    <primary>model-driven</primary>
                                    <secondary>software generation</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-547">
                                    <primary>computing</primary>
                                    <secondary>software generation</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>Model-driven software generation can be simple—an XFORM specification
                        that creates an input form on a web page. Or it can be complex—a detailed
                        architectural specification in UML sufficient to generate a complete
                        application.</para>
                </footnote>
                <phrase role="statement">Standards for describing bibliographic resources enable
                    libraries to centralize and share much resource description, and using the same
                    standards for resources of diverse types helps address the challenge of broad
                    scope by reducing the need for close monitoring and coordination.</phrase>
                Analogous standards for describing information resources, services, or economic
                activities business, governmental, or scientific information systems to
                systematically manage hundreds of millions or even billions of transactional records
                or pieces of data<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref linkend="section-5.3.1.3"
                        xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>.</para>
        </section>
        <!--              -->
        <section xml:id="section-11.3.2" label="11.3.2"><title>Number and Nature of Users</title>
            <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.3.2">
                    <primary>users</primary>
                    <secondary>number and nature of</secondary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
            
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-q4m_54r_lr"><phrase role="statement">An organizing
                    system might have only one user, as when an individual creates and operates an
                    organizing system for a clothes closet, a home bookcase or file cabinet, or for
                    digital files and applications on a personal computer or smart phone.</phrase>
                Collections of personal resources are often organized for highly individualized
                interactions using <foreignphrase>ad hoc</foreignphrase> categories that are hard to
                understand for any other user<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref
                        linkend="section-7.2.2" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>. Personal collections
                or collections used by only a small number of people typically contain resources
                that they themselves selected, which makes the most typical interaction with the
                organizing system searching for a familiar known resource<phrase
                    role="parenthetical"> (<xref linkend="section-10.2.1" xrefstyle="short"
                    />)</phrase>.</para>
            <note userlevel="Editor" xml:id="note-ch10-Editor-kyf_ybs_lr">
                <title>Editors' Note</title>
                <para xml:id="para-nsm_54r_lr">Bob, Isabelle suggests: </para>
                <para xml:id="para-cwm_54r_lr"><info><itermset>
                    <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="note-ch10-Editor-kyf_ybs_lr"><primary>endnote</primary><secondary>IA</secondary></indexterm>
</itermset></info>Stuff on the user. Case ? Literacy level ? ...
                </para>
            </note>
            <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-g1n_54r_lr">At the other extreme, an
                organizing system can have national or even global scope and have millions or more
                users like the Library of Congress classification system, the United Nations
                Standard Products and Services Code, or the Internet Domain Name System. These
                organizing systems employ systems of institutional categories <phrase
                    role="parenthetical">(<xref linkend="section-7.2.3" xrefstyle="short"
                    />)</phrase> that are designed to support systematically specified and
                purposeful interactions, often to search for previously unknown resources. In
                between these extremes are the many kinds of organizing systems created by informal
                and formal groups, by firms of every size, and by sets of cooperating enterprises
                like those that carry out supply chains and other information-intensive business
                processes.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-q2n_54r_lr"><phrase role="statement">The nature and
                    number of users strongly shapes the contents of an organizing system and the
                    interactions it must be designed to support.</phrase>
                <phrase role="parenthetical">(See <xref xrefstyle="short" linkend="section-10.2.1"
                    />)</phrase> Some generic categories of users that apply in many domains are
                customers, clients, visitors, operators, and managers. We can adapt the generic
                interactions supported by most organizing systems <phrase role="parenthetical"
                        >(<xref xrefstyle="short" linkend="section-5.3.2"/>)</phrase> to satisfy
                these generic user types. For example, while most organizing systems allow any type
                of user to browse or search the collection to discover its content, only operators
                or managers are likely to have access to information about the browsing and
                searching activities of customers, clients, or visitors.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-x3n_54r_lr">Once we have identified the organizing
                system’s domain more precisely we can refine these generic user categories,
                classifying users and interactions with more precision. For example, the customers
                of university libraries are mostly professors and students, while the customers of
                online stores are mostly shoppers seeking to find something to purchase. Library
                customers borrow and return resources, often according to different policies for
                professors and students, whereas online stores might only allow resources to be
                returned for refunds or exchanges under limited circumstances.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-mnn_54r_lr"><phrase role="statement"
                    >Just as it is with collection scope, the heterogeneity of the user base is more
                    critical than its absolute size.</phrase> An airport bookstore typically has a
                narrowly focused collection and treats its customers as generic travelers browsing
                imprecisely for something to fill their time in the terminal or on the airplane. In
                contrast, the local public library will have a much broader collection because it
                has to meet the needs of a more diverse user base than the airport bookstore, and it
                will support a range of interactions and services targeted to children learning to
                read, school students, local businesses, retirees, and other categories of users. A
                company library will focus its collection on its industry segment, making it
                narrower in coverage than a local or university research library, but it might
                provide specialized services for marketing, engineering, research, legal, or other
                departments of the firm.</para>
            
            <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-xrn_54r_lr"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-xrn_54r_lr" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                            <primary>Centers for Disease Control</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="para-xrn_54r_lr">
                            <primary>WebMD</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info><phrase role="statement">Each category of users, and indeed each individual
                    user, brings different experiences, goals, and biases into interactions with the
                    organizing system. As a result, organizing systems in the same domain and with
                    nominally the same scope can differ substantially in the resources they contain
                    and the interactions they support for different categories of users.</phrase>
                The library for the <orgname>Centers for Disease Control</orgname> and the
                    <application>WebMD</application> website both contain information about diseases
                and symptoms, but the former is primarily organized to support research in public
                health and the latter is organized for consumers trying to figure out why they are
                sick and how to get well. These contrasting purposes and targeted users are
                manifested in different classification systems and descriptive
                    vocabularies.<footnote xml:id="endnote-548" label="628" audience="LIS">
                    <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-fwn_54r_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-548">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>LIS</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-548">
                                    <primary>library science</primary>
                                    <secondary>CDC</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-548">
                                    <primary>library science</primary>
                                    <secondary>WebMD</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>Compare <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/philc">www.cdc.gov/philc</link> and <link
                            xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="http://www.webmd.com">www.webmd.com</link>.</para>
                </footnote></para>
            <para revision="3.0" revisionflag="added">The designers of these systems do not
                necessarily share the same biases as their users, and more importantly, they may not
                always understand them completely or correctly. This is precisely why good design is
                iterative: successive cycles of evaluation and revision can shape crude,
                provisional, and misguided ideas into wildly successful ones. But such nimbleness is
                not always feasible in highly complex, political, or bureaucratic institutional
                contexts. Even then, as Bowker and Star conclude, transparency is the best
                corrective for these sorts of design failures. Designers who recognize that their
                systems have real consequences for real people should commit to an ongoing process
                of negotiation that enables those affected by the technology to voice and push back
                against any detrimental effect it might have on them and their communities. This
                helps set the stage for effective operation and maintenance of the system <phrase
                    role="parenthetical">(<xref linkend="section-11.6.2" xrefstyle="short"
                    />).</phrase></para>
              
        </section>
        <!--              -->
        <section xml:id="section-11.3.3" label="11.3.3"><title>Expected Lifetime</title>
            <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.3.3">
                    <primary>resource</primary>
                    <secondary>expected lifetime</secondary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
            
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-p14_54r_lr"><phrase role="statement">The scope and
                    scale of a collection and the size of its user population are often correlated
                    with the expected lifetime of its organizing system.</phrase> Because small
                personal organizing systems are often created in response to a specific situation or
                to accomplish a specific task, they generally have short lifetimes<phrase
                    role="parenthetical"> (<xref xrefstyle="short" linkend="section-7.2.2"
                    />)</phrase>.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-vf4_54r_lr"><phrase role="statement">The expected
                    lifetime of the organizing system is not the same as the expected lifetime of
                    the resources it contains because motivations for maintaining resources differ a
                    great deal.</phrase>
                <phrase role="parenthetical">(See <xref xrefstyle="short" linkend="section-3.5.1"
                    />)</phrase> As we have just noted, some organizing systems created by
                individuals are tied to specific short-term tasks, and when the task is completed or
                changes, the organizing system is no longer needed or must be superseded by a new
                one. At the other extreme are libraries, museums, archives, and other memory
                institutions designed to last indefinitely because they exist to preserve valuable
                and often irreplaceable resources.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-yk4_54r_lr">However, most business
                organizing systems contain relatively short-lived resources that arise from and
                support day-to-day operations, in which case the organizing system has a long
                expected lifetime with impermanent resources. Finally, just to complete our 2 x 2
                matrix, the auction catalog that organizes valuable paintings or other collectibles
                is a short-lived single-purpose organizing system whose contents are descriptions of
                resources with long expected lifetimes.</para>
        </section>
        <!--              -->
        <section xml:id="section-11.3.4" label="11.3.4"><title>Physical or Technological Environment</title>
            <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.3.4">
                    <primary>environment</primary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="section-11.3.4">
                    <primary>physical environment</primary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="section-11.3.4">
                    <primary>technological environment</primary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
            
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-lp4_54r_lr"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-lp4_54r_lr">
                            <primary>constraints</primary>
                            <secondary>environment</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info><phrase role="statement">An organizing system is often tied to a particular
                    physical or technological environment.</phrase> A kitchen, closet, card cabinet,
                airplane cockpit, handheld computer or smartphone, and any other physical
                environment in which resources are organized provides affordances to be taken
                advantage of and constraints that must be accommodated by an organizing
                    system<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref linkend="section-3.4.1"
                        xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>.<footnote xml:id="endnote-549" label="629"
                    audience="Business">
                    <para audience="Business" xml:id="para-f54_54r_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-549">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Business</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-549">
                                    <primary>business</primary>
                                    <secondary>built environment</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-549">
                                    <primary>built environment</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-549">
                                    <primary>queue</primary>
                                    <secondary>configuration</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>Service design, architecture, and user interaction design are the
                        primary disciplines that care about the influence of layout and spatial
                        arrangement on user interaction behavior and satisfaction. One type of
                        physical framework is the <quote>Servicescape</quote>
                        <citation xml:id="cite_Bitner1992" linkend="Bitner1992">(Bitner
                            1992)</citation>, the man-made physical context in which services are
                        delivered. For example, the arrangement of waiting lines in banks,
                        supermarkets, and post offices or the use of centrally-visible <quote>take a
                            number</quote> systems strongly influence the encounters in service
                        systems <citation xml:id="cite_Zhou2003" linkend="Zhou2003">(Zhou and Soman
                            2003)</citation>. Related concepts for describing the use of features
                        and orienting mechanisms in <quote>the built environment</quote> come from
                        the <quote>Wayfinding</quote>
                        <citation xml:id="cite_Arthur1992-11.3.4" linkend="Arthur1992">(Arthur and
                            Passini 1992)</citation> literature in urban planning and
                        architecture.</para>
                </footnote></para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-e3p_54r_lr"><info><itermset>
                <indexterm zone="para-e3p_54r_lr">
                    <primary>constraints</primary>
                    <secondary>environment</secondary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info><phrase role="statement">The extent of these physical and technological
                    constraints affects the lifetime of an organizing system because they make it
                    more difficult to adapt to changes in the set of resources being organized or
                    the reasons for their organization.</phrase> A desk or cabinet with fixed
                    <quote>pigeon holes</quote> or drawers affords less flexible organization than a
                file cabinet or open shelves. A building with hard-walled offices constrains how
                people interact and collaborate more than an open floor plan with modular cubicles
                does. Business processes implemented in a monolithic enterprise software application
                are tightly coupled; those implemented as a choreography of loosely-coupled web
                services can often transparently substitute one service provider for another.</para>
        </section>
        <!--              -->
        <?dbfo clear ?>
        <?need 6cm ?>
        <section xml:id="section-11.3.5" label="11.3.5"><title>Relationship to Other Organizing Systems</title>
            <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.3.5">
                    <primary>relationship</primary>
                    <secondary>to other organizing systems</secondary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="section-11.3.5">
                    <primary>DDC</primary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="section-11.3.5">
                    <primary>LCC</primary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="section-11.3.5">
                    <primary>BISAC</primary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
            
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-pmp_54r_lr"><phrase role="statement">The same domain
                    or set of resources can have more than one organizing system, and one organizing
                    system can contain multiple others.</phrase> The organizing system for books in
                a library arranges books about cooking according to the Library of Congress or Dewey
                Decimal classifications and bookstores use the <abbrev>BISAC</abbrev> ones, mostly
                using cuisine as the primary factor<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref
                        xrefstyle="short" linkend="section-8.3"/>)</phrase>. In turn, cookbooks
                employ an organizing system for their recipes that arranges them by type of dish,
                main ingredient, or method of preparation. Within a cookbook, recipes might follow
                an organizing system that standardizes the order of their component parts like the
                description, ingredients, and preparation steps.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-mrp_54r_lr"><info><itermset>
                <indexterm zone="para-mrp_54r_lr">
                    <primary>abstraction</primary>
                    <secondary>level</secondary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>Sometimes these multiple organizing systems can be designed in
                coordination so they can function as a single hierarchical, or nested, organizing
                system in which it is possible to emphasize different levels depending on the user’s
                task or application. Most books and many documents have an internal structure with
                chapters and hierarchical headings that enable readers to understand smaller units
                of content in the context of larger ones<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref
                        xrefstyle="short" linkend="section-6.5.2"/>)</phrase>. Similarly, a
                collection of songs can be treated as an album and organized using that level of
                abstraction for the item, but each of those songs can also be treated as the unit of
                organization, especially when they are embodied in separate digital files.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ewp_54r_lr"><info><itermset>
                <indexterm zone="para-ewp_54r_lr">
                    <primary>CRM</primary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="para-ewp_54r_lr">
                    <primary>ERP</primary>
               </indexterm></itermset>
        </info><phrase role="statement">Organizing systems overlap and intersect. 
                People and enterprises routinely interact with
                many different organizing systems because what they do requires them to use
                resources in ways that cut across context, device, or application boundaries.
                Just consider how many different organizing systems we use as individuals for
                managing personal information like contacts, appointments, and
                messages.</phrase>
                As company employees we create and organize information in email,
                document repositories, spreadsheets, and <abbrev>CRM</abbrev> and
                    <abbrev>ERP</abbrev> systems. Now consider this at an institutional scale in the
                inter-enterprise interactions among the organizing systems of physicians, hospitals,
                medical labs, insurance companies, government agencies, and other parties involved
                in healthcare. Consider how many of these are <quote>mash-ups</quote> and composite services that combine information and resources from independently designed systems. </para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-y1q_54r_lr"><phrase role="statement">We have come to
                    expect that the boundaries between organizing systems are often arbitrary and
                    that we should be able to merge or combine them when that would create
                    additional value. It is surely impossible to anticipate all of these
                        <foreignphrase>ad hoc</foreignphrase> or dynamic intersections of organizing
                    systems, but it is surely necessary to recognize their inevitability, especially
                    when the organizing systems contain digital information and are implemented
                    using web architectures.</phrase></para>
        </section>
        
        <!-- ###################### SECTION ########################################### -->
    </section>
    <!--              -->
    <?dbfo clear ?>
    <?need 7.5cm ?>
    
    <section xml:id="section-11.4" label="11.4"><title>Identifying Requirements for an Organizing System</title>
        <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.4">
                <primary>organizing system</primary>
                <secondary>requirements</secondary>
                <tertiary>identifying</tertiary>
            </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
        
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-bcr_54r_lr"><phrase role="statement">The two parts of the
                definition of an organizing system explicitly suggest two categories of
                requirements, those that specify the intentional arrangement of the resources and
                those that specify the interactions with the resources.</phrase> These categories of
            requirements both depend on resource descriptions, which are implied by but not
            explicitly called out in the definition of an organizing system.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-dhr_54r_lr"><phrase role="statement">Because description,
                arrangement, and interaction are interrelated it is impossible to describe them
                separately without some redundancy.</phrase> Nevertheless, in this book we have done
            that on purpose because taking different perspectives on organizing systems in Chapters
            2-10 has enabled us to introduce a broad range of concepts, issues, and methods:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-mlr_54r_lr"><phrase role="statement">Every
                        organizing system must enable users to interact with its collection of
                        resources (Chapters 3 and 10);</phrase></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-aqr_54r_lr"><phrase role="statement">The possible
                        interactions depend primarily on the nature and extent of the descriptions
                        associated with the resources (Chapters 4, 5 and 6);</phrase></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-m5r_54r_lr"><phrase role="principle statement"
                        >Intentional arrangement emerges when one or more resource descriptions are
                        used by organizing principles (Chapters 7 and 8);</phrase></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-zyr_54r_lr"><phrase role="principle statement"
                        >Different implementations of the same organizing principle can determine
                        the efficiency or effectiveness of the interactions it enables.</phrase>
                    <phrase role="parenthetical">(Chapter 10).</phrase></para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-jds_54r_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-jds_54r_lr">
                        <primary>traceability</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-jds_54r_lr">
                        <primary>interactions</primary>
                        <secondary>traceability</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-jds_54r_lr">
                        <primary>feature traceability</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-jds_54r_lr">
                        <primary>requirements</primary>
                        <secondary>traceability</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>If you are creating a personal organizing system or otherwise small-scale one
            with only a small number of users, you might think there is little reason to think
            explicitly about requirements. However, any project benefits from the discipline of
            being more systematic about its purposes and their priorities. In addition, being
            explicit about requirements enables traceability and impact analysis. <phrase
                role="statement">Traceability means being able to relate an interaction or feature
                of a system to the requirement it satisfies; impact analysis runs the causal link
                between requirements and features in the opposite direction to assess what or who
                will be affected if requirements change.</phrase><footnote xml:id="endnote-550"
                label="630" audience="Business">
                <para audience="Business" xml:id="para-rhs_54r_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-550">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Business</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-550">
                                <primary>business</primary>
                                <secondary>traceability</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-550">
                                <primary>traceability</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>An easy to remember framework for prioritizing requirements is MoSCoW,
                    which classifies them as Must, Should, Could, and Won’t <citation
                        xml:id="cite_Desoky2010" linkend="Desoky2010">(Desoky 2010)</citation>.
                        <citation xml:id="cite_Winkler2010" linkend="Winkler2010">(Winkler and
                        Pilgrim 2010)</citation> is a comprehensive review of academic research and
                    best practices for requirements traceability.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <!--              -->
        <section xml:id="section-11.4.1" label="11.4.1"><title>Requirements for Interactions</title>
            <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.4.1">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>requirements</secondary>
                    <tertiary>for interactions</tertiary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
            
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ems_54r_lr">When we describe interactions in a
                generic or broad way as we did in <xref linkend="chapter-3"/> we see that all
                organizing systems have some common interactions, but most of the time we want to
                pay attention to the more specific interactions that are designed to create value in
                a particular organizing system because of the kind of resources it contains<phrase
                    role="parenthetical"> (<xref xrefstyle="short" linkend="section-3.4.2"
                    />)</phrase>. <phrase role="statement">The domain, scope, and scale of the
                    organizing system determines which interactions are possible and which ones must
                    be explicitly supported, but the priorities of different interactions are more
                    often determined by decisions about intended users.</phrase>
                <phrase role="parenthetical">(See <xref xrefstyle="short" linkend="section-11.3.2"
                    />.)</phrase></para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-irs_54r_lr"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-irs_54r_lr">
                            <primary>business</primary>
                            <secondary>interactions</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="para-irs_54r_lr">
                            <primary>constraints</primary>
                            <secondary>funding</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info><phrase role="statement">For most organizing systems other than personal
                    ones, the set of interactions that are implemented in an organizing system is
                    strongly determined by business model considerations, funding levels, or other
                    economic factors.</phrase> For-profit firms often differentiate themselves by
                the number and quality of the interactions they support with their resources, some
                by supporting many of them and some by supporting a minimal number. This
                differentiation is strongly shaped by and also shapes user preferences; some people
                prefer self-service or unmediated interactions, while others prefer full service and
                mediated interactions.<footnote xml:id="endnote-551" label="631" audience="Business">
                    <para audience="Business" xml:id="para-aws_54r_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-551">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Business</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-551">
                                    <primary>customer segments</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-551">
                                    <primary>business</primary>
                                    <secondary>customer segments</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info><quote>Customer segments</quote> or <quote>customer models</quote>
                        are well-established constructs in product and service marketing and
                        operations <citation xml:id="cite_Batt2000" linkend="Batt2000">(Batt
                            2000)</citation>
                        <citation xml:id="cite_Zeithami2001" linkend="Zeithami2001">(Zeithami, Rust,
                            and Lemon 2001)</citation>. They are key parts of strategies for
                        acquiring customers, increasing market share, and retaining customers.
                        Customer segments can be identified using numerous overlapping criteria,
                        including demographic variables, product or behavior choices, and preferred
                        interaction locations or channels. For example, an airline might segment its
                        customers according to their age, gender, home airport, ticketing class, and
                        travel frequency.</para>
                </footnote>
                <phrase role="statement">Non-profit institutions like public libraries and museums
                    are also subject to these constraints, but unfortunately they have fewer options
                    for adjusting service levels or changing their targeted user populations when
                    their funding is reduced.</phrase><footnote xml:id="endnote-552" label="632"
                    audience="LIS">
                    <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-k1t_54r_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-552">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>LIS</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-552">
                                    <primary>funding cuts</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-552">
                                    <primary>library science</primary>
                                    <secondary>funding</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>Funding cuts for public libraries lead to reduced staffing, reduced
                        hours, and reduced acquisitions and many of them serve populations facing
                        economic challenges of their own. <citation xml:id="cite_Johnson2010"
                            linkend="Johnson2010">(Johnson 2010)</citation>.</para>
                </footnote></para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-s2t_54r_lr">Some requirements for interactions come
                along with technology requirements, to have resources in a particular format, to
                conform to a particular specification or standard in order to operate in some
                technology environment, or to interoperate with other parties or their organizing
                systems.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-bjt_54r_lr"><info><itermset>
                <indexterm zone="para-bjt_54r_lr">
                    <primary>user interface</primary>
                    <secondary>designing interactions</secondary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="para-bjt_54r_lr">
                    <primary>interactions</primary>
                    <secondary>and user interface design</secondary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info><phrase role="statement">An essential requirement in every organizing
                    system is ensuring that the supported interactions can be discovered and invoked
                    by their intended users.</phrase> In organizing systems with physical resources,
                good designers enhance the inherent affordances of resources with navigation and
                orientation aids that direct users to points of interactions<phrase
                    role="parenthetical"> (<xref linkend="section-3.4.1" xrefstyle="short"
                    />)</phrase>. With digital resources and information-intensive organizing
                systems, interactions are not immediately perceivable, and poor design can create
                overly complicated user interfaces in which many interactions are never discovered
                and thus never used.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-jnt_54r_lr"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-jnt_54r_lr">
                            <primary>location</primary>
                            <secondary>smartphone applications</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info><phrase role="statement">It is tricky to compare the overall capabilities of
                    organizing systems in terms of the number or variety of their interactions
                    because what matters more is how much value they create.</phrase> Organizing
                systems with active resources can create value on their own without an explicit user
                    interaction<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref linkend="section-4.2.3.2"
                        xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>. Other organizing systems exploit stored,
                computed, or <glossterm linkend="gloss_contextual_properties">contextual
                    information</glossterm> to create value by eliminating the need for user
                interactions, such as location-based smartphone apps that push information to you
                when you are near some particular location or some person you know<phrase
                    role="parenthetical"> (<xref linkend="section-3.4.1" xrefstyle="short"
                    />)</phrase>.<footnote xml:id="endnote-553" label="633" audience="Business">
                    <para audience="Business" xml:id="para-zrt_54r_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-553">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Business</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-553">
                                    <primary>activity records</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-553">
                                    <primary>business</primary>
                                    <secondary>activity records</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>Organizing systems differ in the extent they can initiate
                        interactions or use information to make them unnecessary. In libraries the
                        organizing systems are typically designed not to preserve user activity
                        records longer than absolutely necessary; in commercial organizing systems,
                        user activity records are the basis of business processes that create highly
                        detailed user models (called <quote>microsegments</quote> or
                            <quote>microcategories</quote>) that enable personalized product and
                        service offerings See <citation xml:id="cite_Taylor2007"
                            linkend="Taylor2007">(Taylor and Raden 2007)</citation>, <citation
                            xml:id="cite_Rosen2012" linkend="Rosen2012">(Rosen
                        2012)</citation>.</para>
                </footnote></para>
        
        </section>
        <!--              -->
        <section xml:id="section-11.4.2" label="11.4.2"><title>About the Nature and Extent of Resource Description</title>
            <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.4.2">
                    <primary>resource description</primary>
                    <secondary>requirements</secondary>
                    <tertiary>nature and extent</tertiary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
            
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-kwt_54r_lr"><phrase role="statement">Interactions
                    with resources within an organizing system often depend on descriptions of
                    individual resources or descriptions of the collections that contain
                    them.</phrase> In the bibliographic domain, generic or common interactions make
                use of descriptions that can be associated with almost any type of resource, such as
                the name, creator, and creation date.<footnote xml:id="endnote-554" label="634"
                    audience="LIS">
                    <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-x15_54r_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-554">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>LIS</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-554">
                                    <primary>library science</primary>
                                    <secondary>DC</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>The Dublin Core was proposed in <date>1995</date> as a small
                        vocabulary with 15 common elements that could be broadly applied. The
                        emergence of many specialized derivatives of the Dublin Core since then
                        illustrates the inherent tension between the simplicity of using a small set
                        of common descriptive elements and the precision enabled by a large or more
                        domain specific vocabulary.</para>
                </footnote></para>
            <para xml:id="para-Ch10-ordering"><info><itermset>
                <indexterm zone="para-Ch10-ordering">
                    <primary>alphabetical ordering</primary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="para-Ch10-ordering">
                    <primary>chronological ordering</primary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>For example, any resource with a sortable name or identifier can be
                arranged alphabetically to enable it to be easily found, and any resource with a
                creation date can be discovered by a <quote>what’s new</quote> query to a resource
                collection.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-hf5_54r_lr"><info><itermset>
                <indexterm zone="para-hf5_54r_lr">
                     <primary>ISBN</primary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="para-hf5_54r_lr">
                     <primary>tradeoffs</primary>
                     <secondary>imposed by extent and timing</secondary>
                 </indexterm></itermset>
        </info><phrase role="statement">Different types
                of resources must have differentiating properties, otherwise there would be no
                reason to distinguish them as different types.</phrase> These resource
                properties can be recorded in the terms of a description language to support one or
                more interactions or to answer one or more questions. Simply put, choices about the
                nature and extent of resource description depend on which interactions or questions
                are most frequent or important<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref xrefstyle="short"
                        linkend="section-5.3.1.1"/>)</phrase>. <phrase role="statement">If a
                    particular property of a resource has no interactions that depend on it, there
                    is no need to describe it. However, if an interaction depends on a description
                    of a particular resource property, a missing description or one of inadequate
                    precision and granularity means that the interaction will be impossible or
                    inefficient to carry out because the resource will need to be further analyzed
                    to create or extract the required description.</phrase>
                <phrase role="statement">An <abbrev>ISBN</abbrev> is a sufficient
                    description to find a book in a directory, but if the <abbrev>ISBN</abbrev> is
                    the only description associated with the book you will not be able to tell who
                    wrote it.</phrase>
                 The tradeoffs imposed by the extent and timing of resource description
                have been a recurring theme in this book, with the tradeoff between recall and
                precision being the most salient<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref
                        xrefstyle="short" linkend="section-2n.5"/>, <xref xrefstyle="short"
                        linkend="section-3.4.1"/>, <xref xrefstyle="short" linkend="section-7.4.1"
                    />, <xref linkend="section-7.4.3" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-vj5_54r_lr"><phrase role="statement">The properties
                    of resources that are easiest to describe are not always the most useful ones,
                    especially for information resources. Anyone can determine the number of pages
                    in a book, but often only a skilled cataloger can accurately describe what the
                    book is about, a far more important property. </phrase>
                <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref linkend="section-5.2.2"/> and <xref
                        linkend="section-7.3.4"/>)</phrase> For non-text information resources this
                problem is magnified because the content is often in a semantically opaque format
                that it optimized for the devices that creates and processes it but which cannot
                usefully be analyzed by people. <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref
                        linkend="section-4.4.2.5"/> and <xref linkend="section-5.4"/>)</phrase>
            </para>
            <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-i45_54r_lr"><phrase role="statement"
                    >Business strategy and economics strongly influence the extent of resource
                    description.</phrase> In many museums and archives there are not enough trained
                people and time to describe every pottery fragment or document, and many resources
                are described only at an aggregate level. In contrast, some people argue that the
                explosion of content in physical and digital form mandates significant investment in
                descriptions that facilitate resource discovery in a crowded marketplace.<footnote
                    xml:id="endnote-555" label="635" audience="LIS">
                    <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-rs5_54r_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-555">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>LIS</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-555" userlevel="Professional">
                                    <primary>library science</primary>
                                    <secondary>citations</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info><citation xml:id="cite_Register2012" linkend="Register2012">(Register
                            and McIlroy 2012)</citation>
                        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="http://themetadatahandbook.com/"
                                ><uri>http://themetadatahandbook.com/</uri></link>.</para>
                </footnote></para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ax5_54r_lr"><info><itermset>
                <indexterm zone="para-ax5_54r_lr">
                    <primary>location</primary>
                    <secondary>smartphone applications</secondary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info><phrase role="statement">Automated and computerized processes can create
                    the resource descriptions in an organizing system and their use is primarily
                    driven by scale<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref linkend="section-5.3.6.4"
                            xrefstyle="short"/>).</phrase></phrase> Search engines index web pages
                and analyze their link structures because it would be impossible to treat the web as
                a traditional library and organize it by human effort. The benefits of digital
                cameras, video recorders, and similar devices would be far fewer if people had to
                manually identify and describe each resource when creating it. Instead, these
                devices can automatically assign some contextual metadata. Similarly, competitive
                pressures on vendors to provide real-time and context-sensitive information services
                mandate automated collection of contextual information like location from mobile
                phones, portable book readers and tablet computers.</para>

            <sidebar xml:id="sidebar-ColorCodedLibrary"><title>Color Coded Library</title>
                <info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-ColorCodedLibrary" condition="print"
                            userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                            <primary>sidebar</primary>
                            <secondary>Color Coded Library</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-ColorCodedLibrary" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                            <primary>Color Coded Library</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-ColorCodedLibrary">
                            <primary>library</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info>
                
                <?dbhtml sidebar-width="50%"?>
                <?dbhtml float-type="right"?>
                
                <informalfigure xml:id="PICTURE-ColorCodedLibrary" xreflabel="Color Coded Library">
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="Pictures/10.4.2-ColorCodedLibrary-OK.jpg" format="JPG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <textobject>
                            <phrase role="ALT descriptive">Books, arranged by color, on shelves.</phrase>
                        </textobject>
                        <caption><para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-mbv_54r_lr"><phrase role="caption">Because he is presumably
                                    familiar with the contents of all of his books, interaction
                                    designer Juhan Sonin organized his library according to their
                                    spine colors. This organizing principle is a highly individual
                                    and aesthetic one, but it would probably not appeal to people
                                    unfamiliar with the collection and would bring chaos to a
                                    library of larger size.</phrase></para>
                            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-bgv_54r_lr"><phrase role="credit"
                                        >(<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                        xlink:href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/seeminglee/4556156477"
                                        >Photo by See-ming Lee.</link> Creative Commons CC-BY-SA-2.0
                                    license.)</phrase></para></caption>
                    </mediaobject>
                </informalfigure>

            </sidebar>

            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-kkv_54r_lr">We might seek some optimal degree of
                description given some set of requirements or purposes for an organizing system and
                some estimate of the organizing effort that could be applied; in practice this is
                elusive for two reasons, both relating to scope and scale. First, as the number of
                users of an organizing system increases, it becomes more difficult to identify and
                anticipate all its possible purposes and constraints it must satisfy. Even if most
                users share the goals for the organizing system, any particular user might have some
                additional specialized use for some attributes or relationships that would require
                more description to satisfy.<footnote xml:id="endnote-556" label="636"
                    audience="Business">
                    <para audience="Business" xml:id="para-u4v_54r_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-556">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Business</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-556">
                                    <primary>business</primary>
                                    <secondary>set design</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>For example, we have often used a home kitchen as a setting for
                        organizing systems. Suppose the home kitchen is to be used as the set for a
                        cooking show and the designers want to arrange cookbooks to make the
                        background visually pleasing. The designers would like to search for
                        cookbooks on the basis of size and spine color, but these descriptive
                        elements would be of little value to other users.</para>
                </footnote></para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ftv_54r_lr">Second, even if it were possible to
                implement some optimal degree of description in a particular organizing system, we
                would still encounter problems when multiple organizing systems exist in the same
                domain or in domains that intersect across context, device, or application
                boundaries. Since organizing systems are designed and evolve to satisfy the specific
                requirements of their particular context, companies will often describe the same
                resources differently, which creates integration and interoperability problems when
                companies need to exchange and combine information resources<phrase
                    role="parenthetical"> (<xref xrefstyle="short" linkend="section-10.3.2"
                    />)</phrase>.</para>
        </section>
        <!--              -->
        <?need 3cm ?>
        <section xml:id="section-11.4.3" label="11.4.3"><title>About Intentional Arrangement</title>
            <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.4.3">
                    <primary>intentional arrangement</primary>
                    <secondary>requirements</secondary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="section-11.4.3">
                    <primary>requirements</primary>
                    <secondary>intentional arrangement</secondary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
            
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-sxv_54r_lr"><phrase role="principle statement"
                    >Organizing principles depend on resource descriptions, so requirements for the
                    former are always intertwined with those for the latter.</phrase> Specifying
                requirements for the intentional arrangement of resources is analogous to specifying
                why and how resource categories can be created<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref
                        xrefstyle="short" linkend="section-7.3"/>)</phrase>. In turn, the creation
                of resource categories often becomes a question about the number and kind of
                resource properties that might be analyzed and exploited by organizing
                principles.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" role="principle" xml:id="para-dcw_54r_lr"><info><itermset>
                <indexterm zone="para-dcw_54r_lr">
                    <primary>location</primary>
                    <secondary>collocation</secondary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="para-dcw_54r_lr">
                    <primary>categorization</primary>
                    <secondary>continuum</secondary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="para-dcw_54r_lr">
                    <primary>principle</primary>
                    <secondary>enumeration</secondary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="para-dcw_54r_lr">
                    <primary>principle</primary>
                    <secondary>collocation</secondary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="para-dcw_54r_lr">
                    <primary>principle</primary>
                    <secondary>intentional arrangement</secondary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>We noted that there is a continuum of category formation that ranges
                from minimal use of resource properties to more rigorous use of multiple properties,
                and finally to statistical or composite use of multiple properties, some of which
                are induced or inferred rather than explicit. <phrase role="principle statement">The
                    simplest principle for defining a category is by enumeration, just putting the
                    resources into a set without any specification of any properties they might
                    share. The enumerated resources might very well have common properties, but the
                    principle of enumeration ignores them; the only property that matters for that
                    principle is that the resources are in the same set. This corresponds to the
                    simplest principle of intentional arrangement, that of <glossterm
                        linkend="gloss_collocation">collocation</glossterm>, just putting the
                    resources in the same location without any additional organization.</phrase>
            </para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-qgw_54r_lr">Collocated resources often acquire some
                additional arrangement as a result of their use; consider how the books, papers, or
                other resources gathered for some writing project often end up in piles in your
                office or on your desk close to your work area. <phrase role="principle statement"
                    >For a small collection, the proximity-to-use organizing principle is the
                    easiest way to satisfy a requirement to minimize the time to find frequently
                    used resources.</phrase></para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-wkw_54r_lr">As we have often seen, the scope and
                scale of the organizing system is a dominant design consideration and it applies to
                principles of resource arrangement too. <phrase role="principle statement">The
                        <glossterm linkend="gloss_collocation">collocation</glossterm> principle of
                    arrangement is sufficient for small resource collections because it is not
                    necessary to define the optimal organization if the time to find any particular
                    resource is short even for an inefficient search method of scanning the entire
                    collection.</phrase>
                <phrase role="statement">Using the extrinsic property of frequency of use makes
                    search slightly more efficient, but only in organizing systems where the user
                    population is small or interacts with the resources in similar ways. Otherwise,
                    arranging resources to facilitate their frequent access for some users would
                    hinder other users who never use them.</phrase> Imagine if you shared your
                office desk with someone who works all night on other writing projects and leaves
                his frequently used resources in piles close to his work area—which becomes your
                work area in the morning.</para>
                 
            <para audience="CORE" role="principle" xml:id="para-opw_54r_lr"><phrase
                    role="principle statement">Larger resource collections usually require multiple
                    organizing principles to manage the complexity that emerges when more users and
                    more varied interactions must be supported. A valet parking lot might organize
                    cars only by size to make optimal use of limited space when parking and fetching
                    them, but when cars are organized for sale they would be organized by price,
                    performance, seating capacity, manufacturer, and many other properties. It is
                    essential to establish the priority of users and interactions because these
                    requirements determine the order in which the principles are applied to arrange
                    the resources. This ordering creates a logical resource hierarchy that affects
                    the efficiency of interactions and the maintenance of the organizing system over
                    time.</phrase></para>
            <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-xtw_54r_lr"><phrase role="statement"
                    >Information resources are invariably challenging to arrange because their
                    aboutness is not an easily perceived property and because of the open-ended
                    purposes they can serve.</phrase> Information collections with broad scope most
                often use a standard system of bibliographic classification<phrase
                    role="parenthetical"> (<xref xrefstyle="short" linkend="section-8.3"
                />)</phrase>. In contrast, special libraries have narrower collections that need to
                support domain-specific interactions for a relatively small set of users, and as a
                result they require more specialized organizational schemes.<footnote
                    xml:id="endnote-557" label="637" audience="LIS">
                    <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-jyw_54r_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-557">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>LIS</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-557">
                                    <primary>special libraries</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-557">
                                    <primary>law</primary>
                                    <secondary>libraries</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-557">
                                    <primary>corporate libraries</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-557">
                                    <primary>research libraries</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-557">
                                    <primary>support libraries</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-557">
                                    <primary>medical libraries</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-557">
                                    <primary>military libraries</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-557">
                                    <primary>museum</primary>
                                    <secondary>libraries</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-557">
                                    <primary>prison libraries</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-557">
                                    <primary>software libraries</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-557">
                                    <primary>media libraries</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-557">
                                    <primary>library science</primary>
                                    <secondary>special libraries</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>The category of special libraries includes law libraries, corporate
                        libraries—both those that support the head office and the research
                        organization—medical libraries, military libraries, museum libraries, prison
                        libraries, and might even be stretched to include libraries of software
                        components.</para>
                </footnote>
                <phrase role="principle statement">The principles for resource arrangement in large
                    firms of every type are often required to conform with laws and regulations for
                    accounting, taxes, human resources, data retention and non retention, access
                    control, and other functions.</phrase>
                <phrase role="parenthetical">(See <xref xrefstyle="short" linkend="section-3.5.4.1"
                    />, <xref xrefstyle="short" linkend="section-8.1.5.4"/>)</phrase></para>
        </section>
        <!--              -->
        <section xml:id="section-11.4.4" label="11.4.4"><title>Dealing with Conflicting Requirements</title>
            <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.4.4">
                    <primary>requirements</primary>
                    <secondary>conflicting</secondary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
            
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-adx_54r_lr"><phrase role="statement">Any individual,
                    group, or enterprise can create an organizing system that meets their specific
                    requirements, but once this organizing system involves two or more parties with
                    different requirements, there is a potential for conflict.</phrase> Roommates or
                spouses sometimes argue about how to organize items in the kitchen, in the
                refrigerator, or in some other shared space. To a person who arranges spices
                alphabetically and condiment jars by size, arranging them according to cuisine or
                frequency of use makes no sense. Similarly, if you are the sole user of a Dropbox or
                other cloud storage account, you can organize it any way you want. You can use any
                number of folders that need only make sense to you, or you can leave everything
                unorganized in a single folder. However, if you share the Dropbox account with
                another person, they are likely to have different organizational needs or
                preferences. Perhaps you tend to organize resources by file type, while they prefer
                to organize resources by topic or project.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" role="principle" xml:id="para-lhx_54r_lr"><phrase role="statement"
                    >A small number of people can often agree on an organizing system that meets the
                    needs of each participant through informal negotiations.</phrase> The potential
                for conflict increases when more people are involved, and <quote>bottom-up</quote>
                <foreignphrase>ad hoc</foreignphrase> negotiations to resolve every disagreement
                between every pair of participants just are not feasible. In many domains conflicts
                are avoided or suppressed because the parties have developed or agreed to conform to
                    standards<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref xrefstyle="short"
                        linkend="section-8.1.5"/>).</phrase> Nevertheless, conflicts in organizing
                principles for large-scale organizing systems are often resolved by parties with the
                legal authority or economic power to impose a solution on all the participants in a
                    <quote>top-down</quote> manner.<footnote xml:id="endnote-558" label="638"
                    audience="Business">
                    <para audience="Business" xml:id="para-zlx_54r_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-558">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Business</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-558">
                                    <primary>market power</primary>
                                    <secondary>imposed standards</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-558">
                                    <primary>business</primary>
                                    <secondary>imposed standards</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>Some people call this the <quote>Wal-Mart approach</quote> to
                        standardization. A firm with dominant market power does not need to
                        negotiate standards because it can impose whatever standards it chooses on
                        its partners as a condition of doing business with them. When there are
                        conflicting requirements, different relationships within the set of
                        participants trying to reach agreement, and different extents to which they
                        are subject to the authority behind the desired agreement, it is not
                        surprising that approaches <quote>that require perfect coordination and
                            altruism are of no practical interest</quote> <citation
                            xml:id="cite_Rosenthal2004-10.1" linkend="Rosenthal2004">(Rosenthal et
                            al. 2004, p 47)</citation>.</para>
                </footnote></para>
        </section>
        
        <!-- ###################### SECTION ########################################### -->
    </section>
    <!--              -->
    <?dbfo clear ?>
    <?need 7.5cm ?>
    
    <section xml:id="section-11.5" label="11.5"><title>Designing and Implementing an Organizing System</title>
        <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.5">
                <primary>organizing system</primary>
                <secondary>designing and implementing</secondary>
            </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
        <para audience="CORE" role="principle" xml:id="para-umy_54r_lr"><phrase role="statement"
                >Requirements define what must be done but NOT how to do it; that’s the role of the
                design and implementation phases.</phrase> Being explicit about requirements and the
            intended scope and scale of an organizing system before moving onto these phases in an
            organizing system’s lifecycle avoids two problems. The first is taking a narrow and
            short-term focus on the initial resources in a collection, which might not be
            representative of the collection when it reaches its planned scope and scale. This can
            result in overly customized and inflexible resource descriptions or arrangements that
            cannot easily accommodate the future growth of the collection. <phrase
                role="statement principle">A second problem, often a corollary of the first, is not
                separating design principles from their implementation in some specific environment
                or technology.</phrase></para>
        <!--              -->
        <section xml:id="section-11.5.1" label="11.5.1"><title>Choosing Scope- and Scale-Appropriate Technology</title>
            <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.5.1">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>choosing technology</secondary>
                    <tertiary>scope- and scale-appropriate</tertiary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
            
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-hry_54r_lr"><info><itermset>
                <indexterm zone="para-hry_54r_lr">
                    <primary>costs</primary>
                    <secondary>implementation tradeoffs</secondary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info><phrase role="statement">A simple organizing system to satisfy personal
                    record keeping or some short-lived information management requirements can be
                    implemented using folders and files on a personal computer or by using
                        <quote>off the shelf</quote> generic software such as web forms,
                    spreadsheets, databases, and wikis.</phrase> Other simple organizing systems run
                as applications on smart phones. Some small amount of configuration, scripting,
                structuring or programming might be involved, but in many cases this work can be
                done in an <foreignphrase>ad hoc</foreignphrase> manner. The low initial cost to get
                started with these kinds of applications must be weighed against the possible cost
                of having to redo a lot of the work later because the resources and the resource
                descriptions might not be easily exported to new ones.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-svy_54r_lr">More capable organizing
                systems that enable the persistent storage and efficient retrieval of large amounts
                of structured information resources generally require additional design and
                implementation efforts. Flat word processing files and spreadsheets are not
                adequate. Instead, <abbrev>XML</abbrev> document models and database schemas often
                must be developed to ensure more control of and validation of the information
                content and its descriptions. Software for version and configuration management,
                security and access control, query and transformation, and for other functions and
                services must also be developed to implement the organizing system.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" role="principle" xml:id="para-c1z_54r_lr"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-c1z_54r_lr">
                            <primary>constraints</primary>
                            <secondary>business rules</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="para-c1z_54r_lr">
                            <primary>requirements</primary>
                            <secondary>traceability</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info><phrase role="principle statement">Technology for organizing systems will
                    always evolve to enable new capabilities.</phrase> For example, cloud computing
                and storage are radically changing the scale of organizing systems and the
                accessibility of the information they contain. It might be possible to implement
                these capabilities and services to an organizing system in an incremental fashion
                with informal design and implementation methods. If information models, processing
                logic, business rules and other constraints are encoded in the software without
                explicit traceability to requirements and design decisions the organizing system
                will be difficult to maintain if the context, scope or requirements change. This is
                why we have repeatedly emphasized the importance of architectural thinking about
                organizing systems, beginning in <xref linkend="section-1.6" xrefstyle="short"/>
                where we proposed that organizing principles should ideally be expressed in a way
                that did not assume how they would be implemented.<phrase role="parenthetical"> (See
                    also <xref linkend="section-3.3.3.2" xrefstyle="short"/>, <xref
                        linkend="section-8.1.3" xrefstyle="short"/>, and <xref linkend="section-9.1"
                        xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase></para>
        </section>
        <!--              -->
        <section xml:id="section-11.5.2" label="11.5.2"><title>Architectural Thinking</title>
            <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.5.2">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>architectural thinking</secondary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="section-11.5.2">
                    <primary>architectural thinking</primary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
            
           
            
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-r2z_54r_lr"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-r2z_54r_lr">
                            <primary>abstraction</primary>
                            <secondary>in design</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info><phrase role="statement">Much of the advice about designing and implementing
                    an organizing system can be summarized as <quote>architectural thinking,</quote>
                    introduced in <xref linkend="section-1.6" xrefstyle="short"/>. The overall
                    purpose of architectural thinking is to separate design issues from
                    implementation ones to make a system more robust and flexible. Architectural
                    thinking leads to more modularity and abstraction in design, making it easier to
                    change an implementation to satisfy new requirements or to take advantage of new
                    technologies or procedures.</phrase> It is also important to think
                architecturally about the design of the vocabularies and schemas for resource
                description and of classification systems to leave room for expansion to accommodate
                new resource types<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref xrefstyle="short"
                        linkend="section-7.5"/> and <xref xrefstyle="short"
                        linkend="section-8.2.2.3"/>)</phrase>. Doing so is easier if the
                descriptions are logically and physically distinct from the resources they describe.
                A checklist the brings together useful principles and processes for architectural
                thinking from all parts of this book is in the nearby sidebar.</para>
            <sidebar revision="4.0" revisionflag="added">
                <?dbhtml sidebar-width="50%"?>
                <?dbhtml float-type="right"?>
                <?dbfo sidebar-width="50%" ?>
                <?dbfo float-type="outside" ?>
                <title>Principles and Processes for Architectural Thinking</title>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para xml:id="para-j5y_xny_pw">Explicitly define the purposes and users of
                            the organizing system, recognizing that users might not agree on
                            purposes or their priorities <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref
                                    linkend="section-2n.3" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para xml:id="para-t14_zny_pw">Select resources
                            <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref linkend="section-3.2.1" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase> and design interactions
                            <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref linkend="section-3.4.2" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase> to support the primary or highest
                            priority users.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para xml:id="para-tnd_14y_pw">Specify information and interaction
                            requirements in a conceptual and technology-neutral way
                            <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref linkend="section-1.6" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase> that conforms as much as possible to
                            domain standards, schemas, or vocabularies
                            <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref linkend="section-8.1.5" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para xml:id="para-lds_14y_pw"> Implement user interactions with design
                            patterns to make them more discoverable, usable, and effective
                            <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref linkend="section-3.3.3.2" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para xml:id="para-l2k_b4y_pw">Follow principles for good names <phrase
                                role="parenthetical">(<xref linkend="section-4.4.3"
                                    xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase> and good resource descriptions
                                <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref linkend="section-5.3.4.1"
                                    xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para xml:id="para-b3x_b4y_pw">Make an informed decision about the tradeoff
                            between flexibility and complexity; a simpler system might be easier to
                            adapt <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref linkend="section-8.2.2.3" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para xml:id="para-txj_c4y_pw">Make design and technology decisions
                            consistent with the expected life of the organizing system
                            <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref linkend="section-11.6" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </sidebar>
            
                
            <sidebar xml:id="StopAndThink-11.5.2-WhatIsALibrary">
                <?dbhtml sidebar-width="50%"?>
                <?dbhtml float-type="left"?>
                <?dbfo sidebar-width="50%" ?>
                <?dbfo float-type="inside" ?>
                <title>Stop and Think: What is a Library?</title>
                <info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="StopAndThink-11.5.2-WhatIsALibrary" condition="print">
                            <primary>Stop and Think</primary>
                            <secondary>What is a Library?</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="StopAndThink-11.5.2-WhatIsALibrary" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                            <primary>What is a Library?</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="StopAndThink-11.5.2-WhatIsALibrary">
                            <primary>library</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info>
                <para xml:id="para-ejz_54r_lr">The word <quote>library</quote> has several meanings
                    that differ in how much architectural thinking they embody. When you tell
                    someone you will meet them at the library for a cup of coffee and a study
                    session it is a specific physical place. At other times you might use a more
                    abstract notion of a library as an organizing system with a predictable type of
                    collection, resource arrangement, and supported interactions. Both meanings are
                    important for a city creating a new library. How would you ensure that both are
                    considered in an effective way? </para>
            </sidebar>
                
            <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-qnz_54r_lr">Nevertheless,
                architectural thinking requires more careful analysis of resources and
                implementation alternatives, and most people do not think this way, especially for
                personal and informal organizing systems. You can imagine that someone might arrange
                a collection of paperback books in a small bookcase whose shelf height and width
                were perfectly suited for the paperbacks they currently own. However, this
                organizing system would not work at all for large format books, and a paperback
                could not be added to the collection unless one was purged from the collection. It
                would be more sensible to start with a bigger bookcase with adjustable shelves so
                that the organizing system would have a longer lifetime.</para>
            <note userlevel="Editor">
                <title>Editors' Note</title>
                <para xml:id="para-o5p_rvg_hv">Section should be revisited in the light of "need to
                    be ready to learn"</para>
            </note>

            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-isz_54r_lr">You might think that large institutional
                organizing systems would avoid these problems caused by tying a collection too
                tightly to the physical environment in which it is initially organized, but
                sometimes they do not. A famous example involves the art collection of the Barnes
                Foundation, which had to keep its paintings in the exact same crowded arrangements
                when the museum made a controversial move from a small building to a larger one
                because the donor had mandated that the paintings never be moved from their original
                settings. (See the sidebar, <xref linkend="sidebar_Barnes_Collection"/>).</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-vwz_54r_lr"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-vwz_54r_lr">
                            <primary>big data</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="para-vwz_54r_lr">
                            <primary>constraints</primary>
                            <secondary>physical</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info><phrase role="definition" xml:id="def_big_data">For digital resources,
                    inexpensive storage and high bandwidth have largely eliminated capacity as a
                    constraint for organizing systems, with an exception for <glossterm
                        xml:id="term_big_data">big data</glossterm>, which is defined as a
                    collection of data that is too big to be managed by typical database software
                    and hardware architectures.</phrase><footnote xml:id="endnote-559" label="639"
                    audience="Computing">
                    <para audience="Computing" xml:id="para-fb1_v4r_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-559">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Computing</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-559">
                                    <primary>big data</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-559">
                                    <primary>computing</primary>
                                    <secondary>big data</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>Note that this definition does not include any specific size
                        threshold, such as some number of terabytes (thousands of gigabytes). This
                        allows the threshold size that makes a collection a big data one to increase
                        as storage technology advances. It also recognizes that different industries
                        or domains have different thresholds <citation
                            xml:id="cite_Manyika2011_11.2" linkend="Manyika2011">(Manyika et al
                            2011)</citation>.</para>
                </footnote> Even so, big data collections are often large but homogeneous, so their
                scale is not their most important challenge from an organizing system
                    perspective<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref xrefstyle="short"
                        linkend="section-11.3.1"/>)</phrase>.</para>

            <sidebar xml:id="sidebar_Barnes_Collection"><title>The Barnes Collection</title>
                <info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar_Barnes_Collection" condition="print"
                            userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                            <primary>sidebar</primary>
                            <secondary>Barnes Collection</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar_Barnes_Collection" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                            <primary>Barnes Collection</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar_Barnes_Collection">
                            <primary>museums</primary>
                            <secondary>Barnes Collection</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info>
                
                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-pf1_v4r_lr"
                            ><personname><firstname>Albert</firstname>
                        <surname>Barnes</surname></personname> was a chemist who made a fortune
                    inventing a preventive treatment for gonorrhea and who then amassed perhaps the
                    greatest private art collection ever, one that contained over 800 paintings by
                    artists like <personname><surname>Picasso</surname></personname>,
                            <personname><surname>Renoir</surname></personname>,
                            <personname><surname>Matisse</surname></personname>,
                            <personname><surname>van Gogh</surname></personname>, and
                            <personname><surname>Cezanne</surname></personname>. In
                        <date>1922</date> Barnes built a museum for his collection in his
                    residential neighborhood in Merion, PA, a suburb of Philadelphia. Barnes did not
                    open his collection to the public and in his will mandated that the collection
                    never be moved, loaned, or sold.</para>
                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ek1_v4r_lr"><info><itermset><indexterm zone="para-ek1_v4r_lr">
                        <primary>location</primary>
                        <secondary>constraint</secondary>
                    </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>In the decades after Barnes died in <date>1951</date> the Merion
                    museum needed extensive repairs and security upgrades, and some people suggested
                    that its remote location and access restrictions jeopardized its financial
                    viability. However, a proposal to relocate the collection to Philadelphia
                    seemingly violated the terms of the Barnes will.</para>
                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-q41_v4r_lr">A legal fight dragged on for decades.
                    Finally in <date>2004</date> a judge ruled that the collection could be moved to
                    Philadelphia, but only if the new museum contained exact copies of the gallery
                    rooms of the original museum and arranged the paintings exactly as they were in
                    Merion. The new museum building, opened in <date>2012</date>, is ten times
                    larger than the old one, but the collection takes up the same space as it did in
                    Merion. The other 90% of the building is occupied by an auditorium, offices,
                    classrooms, a gift shop, and other space that contains none of the
                        collection.<footnote xml:id="endnote-560" label="640" audience="Museums">
                        <para audience="Museums" xml:id="para-ss1_v4r_lr"><info>
                                <itermset>
                                    <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-560">
                                        <primary>endnote</primary>
                                        <secondary>Museums</secondary>
                                    </indexterm>
                                    <indexterm zone="endnote-560">
                                        <primary>museums</primary>
                                        <secondary>Barnes collection</secondary>
                                    </indexterm>
                                </itermset>
                            </info>The history of the collection and the legal battle are described
                            in <citation xml:id="cite_Anderson2003" linkend="Anderson2003">(Anderson
                                2003)</citation>. A documentary film with a conspiracy perspective
                            is <citation xml:id="cite_Argott2009" linkend="Argott2009">(Argott
                                2009)</citation>. See also BarnesFoundation.org.</para>
                    </footnote></para>
            </sidebar>

        </section>
        <!--              -->
        <section xml:id="section-11.5.3" label="11.5.3"><title>Distinguishing Access from Control</title>
            <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.5.3">
                    <primary>resource</primary>
                    <secondary>access vs control</secondary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
            
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ex1_v4r_lr"><info><itermset>
                <indexterm zone="para-ex1_v4r_lr">
                    <primary>location</primary>
                    <secondary>hidden</secondary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="para-ex1_v4r_lr">
                    <primary>abstraction</primary>
                    <secondary>layer</secondary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="para-ex1_v4r_lr">
                    <primary>identity</primary>
                    <secondary>obfuscated by services</secondary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>Because large resource collections are often used for multiple purposes
                by many different people or projects, they illustrate another important
                architectural issue for collections of digital resources. <phrase role="statement">A
                    requirement for access to resources does not imply a need to directly own or
                    control them, and information-intensive and web-based businesses have
                    increasingly adopted organizing system designs that involve storage of digital
                    resources in the cloud, licensing of globally distributed resources, and
                    outsourcing of information services.</phrase> Designs that use these
                architectural concepts can realize functional and quality improvements because the
                location and identity of the service provider is hidden by an abstraction
                    layer<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref xrefstyle="short"
                        linkend="section-3.4.2.1"/>, <xref xrefstyle="short"
                        linkend="section-4.4.3.5"/>)</phrase>. However, separating access from
                ownership has been a cultural challenge for some libraries and museums whose
                institutional identities emphasize the resources they directly control and the
                physical buildings in which they control them.<footnote xml:id="endnote-561"
                    label="641" audience="LIS">
                    <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-gcb_v4r_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-561">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>LIS</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-561" userlevel="Professional">
                                    <primary>library science</primary>
                                    <secondary>citations</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>See <citation xml:id="cite_Sandler2006-11.1" linkend="Sandler2006"
                            >(Sandler 2006)</citation>, <citation xml:id="cite_Freeman2005"
                            linkend="Freeman2005">(Freeman et al. 2005)</citation>.</para>
                </footnote></para>
        </section>
        <!--              -->
        <section xml:id="section-11.5.4" label="11.5.4"><title>Standardization and Legacy Considerations</title>
            <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.5.4">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>standardization and legacy</secondary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
            
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-sgb_v4r_lr">As we noted with the Barnes Collection, a
                building becomes old and outdated over time. <phrase role="statement">The technology
                    used in digital organizing systems becomes obsolete faster than physical
                    buildings do.</phrase> The best way to slow the inevitable transformation of
                today’s cutting edge technology to tomorrow’s legacy technology is to design with
                standard data formats, description vocabularies and schemas, and classification
                systems unless you have specific requirements that preclude these choices.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-alb_v4r_lr"><info><itermset>
                <indexterm zone="para-alb_v4r_lr">
                    <primary>API</primary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info><phrase role="statement">Even a requirement to interoperate with an
                    organizing system that uses proprietary or non-standard specifications can
                    usually be satisfied by transforming from a standard format<phrase
                        role="parenthetical"> (<xref xrefstyle="short" linkend="section-8.1.5.2"/>,
                            <xref xrefstyle="short" linkend="section-10.4"/>).</phrase></phrase>
                <phrase role="statement principle">Similarly, it is better to design the
                        <abbrev>API</abbrev>s and data feeds of an organizing system in a generic or
                    standard way that abstracts from their hidden implementation. This design
                    principle makes it easier for external users to understand the supported
                    interactions, and also prevents disclosure of any aspects of resource
                    description or organization that provide competitive advantage.</phrase> For
                example, the way in which a business classifies products, suppliers, customers, or
                employees can be competitively important.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-opb_v4r_lr"><info><itermset>
                <indexterm zone="para-opb_v4r_lr">
                    <primary>costs</primary>
                    <secondary>data conversion</secondary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info><phrase role="interrogative">Two important design questions that arise
                    with data transformation or conversion, whether it is required by a technology
                    upgrade or an interoperability requirement, are when to do it and where to do
                    it.</phrase> The job of converting all the resources in a collection can
                typically be outsourced to a firm that specializes in format conversion or resource
                description, and a batch or pre-emptive conversion of an entire collection enables
                an upgraded or new organizing system to operate more efficiently when it is not
                distracted by ongoing conversion activity. On the other hand, if resources vary
                greatly in their frequency of use, a <quote>do-it-yourself on-demand</quote> method
                is probably more cost effective as long as the conversion does not impact the
                interactions that need to be supported.</para>
        </section>
        
        <!-- ###################### SECTION ########################################### -->
    </section>
    <!--              -->
    <section xml:id="section-11.6" label="11.6"><title>Operating and Maintaining an Organizing System</title>
        <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.6">
                <primary>organizing system</primary>
                <secondary>operating and maintaining</secondary>
            </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
        
        
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-sqc_v4r_lr"><phrase role="statement">After the organizing
                system has been designed and implemented it can be put into its operation and
                maintenance phases.</phrase> We will look at these from two perspectives, first from
            the point of view of individual resources, and then from the point of view of the
            organizing system’s design and implementation. These two perspectives are not always
            clearly distinguished. Curation, for example, is often used to describe actions taken to
            maintain individual resources as well as those that result in new arrangements of
            them.</para>
        
        <!--              -->
        <section xml:id="section-11.6.1" label="11.6.1"><title>Resource Perspective</title>
            <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.6.1">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>maintaining</secondary>
                    <tertiary>resource perspective</tertiary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
            
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ivc_v4r_lr"><phrase role="statement">Sometimes an
                    organizing system is implemented with its organizing structures and
                    relationships waiting to be populated by resources as they are acquired and
                    described.</phrase> The scope and scale of the organizing system shapes how the
                descriptions are created and how the descriptions are then used to assign resources
                to the logical or physical containers of the organizing system. The most important
                decisions to be made at this point involve determining an appropriate mix of methods
                for creating the resource descriptions, because their cost, quality, consistency,
                completeness, and semantic richness depends on which human or computational agents
                do the work<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref xrefstyle="short"
                        linkend="section-5.3.6"/>)</phrase>.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-xzc_v4r_lr">For web-based and consumer-focused
                organizing systems, it is tempting to rely on users to assign descriptions, tags, or
                ratings to resources<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref linkend="section-5.2.2.3"
                        xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>. Some of these systems attempt to improve the
                quality and precision of these descriptions by providing forms, controlled
                vocabularies, or suggestions. Finding a balance is tricky; too much direction and
                control is demotivating to uncompensated volunteer describers, and too little of it
                results in the proverbial <quote>tag soup.</quote></para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-i2d_v4r_lr">An essential operational and maintenance
                activity is evaluation of resource descriptions, first with respect to the time and
                process by which they are created, and second with respect to how and when they
                support the designed interactions<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref
                        linkend="section-5.3.7" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-fjd_v4r_lr"><phrase role="statement">Some organizing
                    systems are initiated with a fixed set of resources that will not change in any
                    way.</phrase> For example, in an archive as most narrowly defined, neither the
                individual resources nor the organization of the collection as a whole will change.
                If an archive of Abraham Lincoln letters is established, we know that Lincoln will
                never revise any letters or write any new ones, and any new classifications or
                descriptions devised by people studying the archive will not be used to rearrange
                the letters.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-wnd_v4r_lr">Most organizing systems, however, need to
                support ongoing interactions with a collection that changes over time as new
                resources enter the collection and old ones leave. These selection and collection
                management processes are explicit in libraries, museums and similar institutions
                that maintain collections to satisfy the changing needs and preferences of their
                user communities<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref linkend="section-3.2.2"
                        xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>.</para>
        </section>
        <!--              -->
        <section xml:id="section-11.6.2" label="11.6.2"><title>Properties, Principles and Technology Perspective</title>
            <info><itermset><indexterm zone="section-11.6.2">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>maintaining</secondary>
                    <tertiary>technology perspective</tertiary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="section-11.6.2">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    <secondary>maintaining</secondary>
                    <tertiary>properties and principles</tertiary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
            
            <para audience="CORE" role="principle" xml:id="para-lsd_v4r_lr"><phrase role="statement"
                    >It is useful to consider how an organizing system as a whole is operated and
                    maintained over time.</phrase> We can analyze how the system’s organizing
                properties, principles and technology might change, and we can roughly order
                different types of change according to their overall impact.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" role="principle" xml:id="para-zwd_v4r_lr"><phrase role="statement"
                    >The most predictable maintenance activities for an organizing system with an
                    expected long lifetime <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref xrefstyle="short"
                            linkend="section-11.3.3"/>)</phrase> are incremental changes in
                    description vocabularies and classification schemes<phrase role="parenthetical">
                            (<xref linkend="section-8.2.2.3" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>.</phrase>
                These need to evolve when new instances or contexts require additional properties to
                maintain the distinctions between types of resources, but the basic principles
                embodied in the organizing systems are not affected.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-vb2_v4r_lr"><phrase role="statement">Incremental
                    category maintenance takes place even in personal organizing systems where the
                    categories are not always explicit.</phrase> The collection of clothes in a
                college student’s closet and the categories and properties for arranging them will
                change somewhat when he graduates and takes a job in a downtown office building
                where he needs to dress more formally than he did as a student. He will learn that
                despite the common term in the category name, <quote>student casual</quote> and
                    <quote>business casual</quote> do not contain the same sets of resources.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-lg2_v4r_lr"><phrase role="statement">Category
                    maintenance is an ongoing activity in institutional organizing systems.
                </phrase>The most commonly used bibliographic classification systems all have
                numbering and naming schemes that allow for subdivision and extension to create new
                subcategories to accommodate resources about new fields of knowledge and
                technology.</para>
            <para audience="Computing" xml:id="para-bl2_v4r_lr"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-bl2_v4r_lr">
                            <primary>ACM</primary>
                            <secondary>keyword classification</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="para-bl2_v4r_lr">
                            <primary>Moore’s Law</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info>As another example, the <firstterm xml:id="first_ACM"><citerefentry
                        xml:id="ref_ACM"><refentrytitle><orgname>Association for Computing
                                Machinery</orgname></refentrytitle><manvolnum>ACM</manvolnum></citerefentry></firstterm>
                professional society created a keyword classification in <date>1964</date> to
                organize articles in its many publications, but relentless change in the computing
                field driven by Moore’s Law has required the <abbrev>ACM</abbrev> to significantly
                revise the system almost every decade.<footnote xml:id="endnote-562" label="642"
                    audience="Computing">
                    <para audience="Computing" xml:id="para-wp2_v4r_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-562">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Computing</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-562">
                                    <primary>computing</primary>
                                    <secondary>ACM</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>No classification scheme ever devised is as unstable as the
                            <abbrev>ACM</abbrev>’s because new computing concepts, technologies, and
                        application areas are constantly emerging. Even the society’s name seems
                        outdated.</para>
                </footnote></para>
            <para audience="CORE Business" role="contrast principle" xml:id="para-n52_v4r_lr">In
                contrast, changes in business organizing systems are more likely to be driven by
                economic factors. Resource properties for managing collections of resource and the
                information that describes them often change over time as a result of new products
                and services, mergers and acquisitions, or refined customer segmentation. More
                substantial changes in business organizing systems reflect the need to comply with
                laws and regulations that impose new requirements for tracing money flows or
                transactions. These mandated classifications and processes might require new
                organizing principles, not just incremental properties<phrase role="parenthetical">
                        (<xref linkend="section-8.1.5.4" xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>.</para>
            <para audience="Computing" xml:id="para-fz2_v4r_lr"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-fz2_v4r_lr">
                            <primary>BPEL</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info>The choice of implementation technology influences how easy it is to handle
                these types of changes in organizing systems. In databases this problem is known as
                    <quote>schema migration.</quote> With XML implementations, schemas can be
                designed with <quote>extension</quote> or <quote>codelist</quote> elements to enable
                changes that will not invalidate existing information. Business processes that are
                driven by <quote>executable specifications</quote> like the <firstterm
                    xml:id="first_BPEL"><citerefentry xml:id="ref_BPEL"><refentrytitle>Business
                            Process Execution
                        Language</refentrytitle><manvolnum>BPEL</manvolnum></citerefentry></firstterm>
                can be easily modified because the <abbrev>BPEL</abbrev>
                <abbrev>XML</abbrev> instance is used to configure the software that carries out the
                process it describes.<footnote xml:id="endnote-563" label="643" audience="Computing">
                    <para audience="Computing" xml:id="para-udf_v4r_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-563">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Computing</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-563">
                                    <primary>BPEL</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-563">
                                    <primary>computing</primary>
                                    <secondary>BPEL</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>For a formal computer science treatment of BPEL see <citation
                            xml:id="cite_Fu2004" linkend="Fu2004">(Fu, Bultan, and Su
                            2004)</citation>; for a commercial perspective see <link
                            xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/middleware/bpel/overview/index.html"
                                ><uri>http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/middleware/bpel/overview/index.html</uri></link>.</para>
                </footnote></para>
            <para audience="CORE" role="principle" xml:id="para-c3f_v4r_lr">Another very predictable
                type of activity over time with organizing systems is a technology upgrade that
                improves its quality or capabilities without affecting the organizing principles. A
                student might replace his handwritten lecture notes with typed notes on a laptop or
                tablet computer but not significantly change the way the notes are organized.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-umf_v4r_lr"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-umf_v4r_lr">
                            <primary>costs</primary>
                            <secondary>storage</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info><phrase role="statement">Institutional organizing systems are adopting tiered
                    storage systems that automatically move resources between different types of
                    storage media to meet performance, availability and recovery
                    requirements.</phrase> For example, firms with high financial impact of downtime
                like banks run critical organizing systems with copies in <quote>failsafe</quote> or
                    <quote>hot</quote> modes that are synchronized with the production environments
                to prevent any interruptions in information access if the latter are disrupted. On
                the other hand, resources needed for regulatory compliance can be kept on lower cost
                disk storage.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-nrf_v4r_lr"><phrase role="principle statement">The
                    most challenging kinds of maintenance activities for organizing systems involve
                    changes to the principles for arranging resources along with changes in the
                    implementing technology.</phrase> An example is the ambitious effort to
                introduce semantic web and linked data concepts in bibliographic organizing
                    systems<phrase role="parenthetical"> (<xref xrefstyle="short"
                        linkend="section-6.8.2"/>, <xref xrefstyle="short" linkend="section-9.4.3"
                    />)</phrase>. And change comes faster to businesses than to libraries and
                museums. <phrase role="statement">New technologies can have a disruptive impact on
                    business organizing system, forcing major changes to enable strategy changes
                    that involve faster finding, retrieval, or delivery of informational or physical
                    goods.</phrase><footnote xml:id="endnote-564" label="644" audience="Computing">
                    <para audience="Computing" xml:id="para-fwf_v4r_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-564">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Computing</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-564" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                                    <primary>business applications</primary>
                                    <secondary>managing qualitative change</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-564">
                                    <primary>computing</primary>
                                    <secondary>managing qualitative change</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>This means that the organizing systems used by business applications
                        more often employ configuration management, version control, model-based
                        code generation, and other computing techniques that robustly support the
                        need for qualitative changes in the organizing systems.</para>
                </footnote></para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-x1g_v4r_lr"><phrase role="statement principle"
                    >Sometimes major changes to organizing principles and technologies can be
                    introduced incrementally, with changes <quote>rolled out</quote> to different
                    sets of resources or user groups during a transition period. However, sometimes
                    the changes are inherently ”all or none” because it is impossible to have two
                    conflicting organizing systems operating in the same context.</phrase> An easy
                to understand example of an organizing system that changed radically is the system
                governing which side of the road you drive on, which was changed in Samoa in
                    <date>2009</date>.<phrase role="parenthetical"> (See the sidebar, <xref
                        linkend="sidebar_Driving_Samoa"/>)</phrase>.</para>
            
            
            <sidebar xml:id="sidebar_Driving_Samoa"><title>Driving in Samoa</title>
                <info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar_Driving_Samoa" condition="print"
                            userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                            <primary>sidebar</primary>
                            <secondary>Driving in Samoa</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar_Driving_Samoa" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                            <primary>Driving in Samoa</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info>
                
                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-yjg_v4r_lr">Whether you travel by bus, car, or
                    bicycle, you always keep to one side of the road. The convention of driving on
                    either the right side or the left side is a legal standard that everyone takes
                    for granted. However, you must follow it to ensure safe driving and avoid
                    collisions and crashes.</para>
                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-j4g_v4r_lr">This standard of which side of the
                    road you drive on was not decided arbitrarily, but rather, it was adopted as a
                    result of history, convention, and the need for organization. If you were the
                    only person to use the road, you could choose to travel on any side you wanted,
                    even travel right down the middle. As soon as more than one person needs to use
                    the same road, the risk of collisions compels the creation of a coordinating
                    standard.</para>
                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-atg_v4r_lr">In <date>2009</date>, the government
                    of Samoa took the rare step of changing the side of the road standard from
                    driving on the right to driving on the left. The original standard reflected the
                    influence of German colonization in the early <date>1900s</date>. However, Samoa
                    is both geographically close to and economically intertwined with Australia and
                    New Zealand, former British colonies that follow the British convention of
                    driving on the left side. This proximity gives Samoa access to a nearby source
                    of used cars that would be attractive to Samoa’s relatively poor population. So,
                    the Samoan government decided to use its authority to change the driving
                    standard so that more of its people could afford to buy cars.</para>
                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-kzg_v4r_lr">As one could imagine, this decision
                    was not implemented without controversy and opposition. While the decision
                    benefited people currently without cars, it negatively affected those who
                    already owned them. After a switch like this, what happens to the current market
                    value of the thousands of cars designed to drive on the right? Opponents also
                    claimed that the switch would cause unprecedented safety hazards. If even a
                    small fraction of drivers were not able to immediately get the hang of driving
                    on the other side, the accident rate could increase tremendously. Imagine the
                    current pool of buses designed with doors that open on the right hand
                        side<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>would they now let passengers out in the middle
                    of the street? Who would pay to have the buses modified to put doors on the left
                    hand side?<footnote xml:id="endnote-565" label="645" audience="Business">
                        <para audience="Business" xml:id="para-q2h_v4r_lr"><info>
                                <itermset>
                                    <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-565">
                                        <primary>endnote</primary>
                                        <secondary>Business</secondary>
                                    </indexterm>
                                    <indexterm zone="endnote-565">
                                        <primary>business</primary>
                                        <secondary>Barta</secondary>
                                    </indexterm>
                                </itermset>
                            </info><citation xml:id="cite_Barta2009" linkend="Barta2009">(Barta
                                2009)</citation>.</para>
                    </footnote></para>
            </sidebar>
        </section>
        
        <!-- ###################### SECTION ########################################### -->
    </section>




    <!--              -->
    <?dbfo clear ?>
    <section xml:id="section-11.7" label="11.7"><title>Key Points in Chapter Eleven</title>
        
        <qandaset role="quiz">
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative">What three initial
                        characteristics of an organizing system influence most of the decisions
                        about that organizing system?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para audience="CORE">Most of the specific decisions that must be made for an
                        organizing system are shaped by the initial decisions about its domain,
                        scope, and scale.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-11.2"/>)</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative">What is the
                        effect of broad scope in an organizing system?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para audience="CORE">The impact of broad scope arises
                        more from the heterogeneity of the resources and users in a collection
                        rather than from their absolute number.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-11.3.1"/>)</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative">What is a
                        practical effect of increasing collection size?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para audience="CORE">Larger collections need more
                        people to organize and maintain them, creating communication and
                        coordination problems that grow much faster than the collection.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-11.3.1"/>)</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative">How do you
                        avoid problems of scope and scale?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para audience="CORE">Standardization is the best way to prevent problems of
                        scope and scale.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-11.3.1"/>)</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative">What is an
                        effect of a heterogeneous user community?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para audience="CORE">Organizing systems in the same
                        domain and with nominally the same scope can differ substantially in the
                        resources they contain and the interactions they support if they have
                        different categories of users.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-11.3.2"/>)</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            
            <!-- NEW KEY POINT -->
            <qandaentry audience="CORE" revision="3.0" revisionflag="added">
                <question>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative">How can designers mitigate possible negative consequences of the system and technology they design?
                    </para>
                </question>
                <answer><para>Designers who recognize that their systems have real consequences for people should commit to measures of transparency and an ongoing process of negotiation that enables those affected to voice concerns related to any detrimental effects the technology might have on them and their communities. 
                </para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref linkend="section-11.3.2"
                        />)</para></answer>
            </qandaentry>
            
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative">What is the
                        single biggest factor affecting the implementation of interactions?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para audience="CORE">For most organizing systems other
                        than personal ones, the set of interactions that are implemented in an
                        organizing system is strongly determined by economic factors.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-11.4.1"/>)</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative">What is the
                        most essential requirement of interactions?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para audience="CORE">An essential requirement in every
                        organizing system is ensuring that the supported interactions can be
                        discovered and invoked by their intended users.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-11.4.1"/>)</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative">What is the
                        role of computational agents in the creation and consumption of resource
                        descriptions?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para audience="CORE">Automated and computerized
                        processes can create the resource descriptions in an organizing system and
                        their use is primarily driven by scale.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-11.4.2"/>)</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative">What is the
                        relationship between organizing principles and resource descriptions?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="principle">Organizing
                        principles depend on resource descriptions, so requirements for the former
                        are always intertwined with those for the latter.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-11.4.3"/>)</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>

            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative">What
                        characteristics of resource descriptions impede growth?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para audience="CORE">Overly customized and inflexible
                        resource descriptions or arrangements cannot easily accommodate the future
                        growth of the collection.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-11.5"/>)</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative">What are the
                        advantages of architectural thinking?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para audience="CORE">Architectural thinking leads to
                        more modularity and abstraction in design, making it easier to change an
                        implementation to satisfy new requirements or to take advantage of new
                        technologies or procedures.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-11.5.2"/>)</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative">What is big
                        data?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para audience="CORE"><xref linkend="def_big_data"
                            role="transclusion" endterm="def_big_data"/></para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-11.5.2"/>)</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>

            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative">What are the
                        most predictable maintenance activities?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para audience="CORE">The most predictable maintenance
                        activities for an organizing system with an expected long lifetime are
                        incremental changes in description vocabularies and classification
                        schemes.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="principle">Another very
                        predictable type of activity over time with organizing systems is a
                        technology upgrade that improves its quality or capabilities without
                        affecting the organizing principles.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-11.6.2"/>)</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative">What changes
                        in organizing systems make maintenance especially difficult?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="principle">The most
                        challenging kinds of maintenance activities for organizing systems involve
                        changes to the principles for arranging resources along with changes in the
                        implementing technology.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See <xref
                            linkend="section-11.6.2"/>)</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative">What six
                        questions should be asked when approaching any organizing system?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para audience="CORE">What resources are being
                        organized? Why are the resources being organized? Who does the organizing?
                        When are the resources organized? Where are the resources organized? How
                        much are the resources organized? </para>
                    <para audience="CORE" role="parenthetical">(See the
                        case studies presented in <xref linkend="chapter-12"/>)</para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
        </qandaset>
        
        <!-- ###################### CHAPTER ########################################### -->
    </section>
</chapter>
