<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.0 -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="chapter-1" label="1"
    audience="CORE">
    <title>Foundations for Organizing Systems</title>
    <info>
        <author>
            <personname><firstname>Robert</firstname><othername>J.</othername><surname>Glushko</surname></personname>
        </author>
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>organize</keyword>
            <keyword>organizing system</keyword>
            <keyword>discipline</keyword>
            <keyword>framework</keyword>
            <keyword>resource</keyword>
            <keyword>collection</keyword>
            <keyword>intentional arrangement</keyword>
            <keyword>agent</keyword>
            <keyword>description resource</keyword>
            <keyword>primary resource</keyword>
            <keyword>surrogate resource</keyword>
            <keyword>metadata</keyword>
        </keywordset>
        
        
    </info>

    <!--              -->
    <section xml:id="section-1.1" label="1.1">
        <title>The Discipline of Organizing</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-1.1">
                    <primary>Organizing Systems</primary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm zone="section-1.1">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm zone="section-1.1">
                    <primary>collection</primary>
                    <secondary>resources</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm zone="section-1.1">
                    <primary>intentional arrangement</primary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm zone="section-1.1">
                    <primary>interactions</primary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm zone="section-1.1">
                    <primary>resource</primary>
                    <secondary>physical</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm zone="section-1.1">
                    <primary>resource</primary>
                    <secondary>digital</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm zone="section-1.1">
                    <primary>physical things</primary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm zone="section-1.1">
                    <primary>digital things</primary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>

        
        
        <sidebar xml:id="ch01-stats" condition="epub3 print" role="statistics" userlevel="Editor">
            <?dbhtml sidebar-width="60%"?>
            <?dbhtml float-type="right"?>
            <?dbfo sidebar-width="60%"?>
            <?dbfo float-type="inside"?>
            <informalfigure xml:id="inf-fig-ch01-stats">
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="Visualisations/ch01-stats.png" format="JPG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                        <phrase role="ALT descriptive">This graphic describes the content breakdown
                            of the chapter. A wheel with colored segments depicts core content
                            versus disciplinary content in this chapter, and a bar chart illustrates
                            the disciplinary content distribution. In this chapter, Web and LIS
                            predominate, followed by Law, then Computing, Business, CogSci,
                            Archives, IA, and Philosophy. There are no Linguistics or Museums notes
                            in this chapter.</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>The discipline of organizing emerges at the intersection of existing
                            disciplines. We distinguish discipline-specific content and illustrate
                            the disciplinary mix of endnotes in each chapter. <phrase
                                role="parenthetical">(See <xref linkend="sidebar-endnote-types"
                                />.)</phrase></para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure>
        </sidebar>
        
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-a4l_snr_lr"><info><itermset>
            <indexterm significance="preferred"
                zone="def_organize">
                <primary>organize</primary>
            </indexterm><indexterm zone="def_organize">
                <primary>activities</primary>
                <secondary>organizing</secondary>
            </indexterm></itermset>
        </info><phrase role="definition" xml:id="def_organize">To <glossterm
            xml:id="term_organize">organize</glossterm> is to create capabilities by
            intentionally imposing order and structure.</phrase>
        </para>
        
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ktl_snr_lr"><phrase role="statement">Organizing is such a
                common <glossterm linkend="gloss_activities">activity</glossterm> that we often do
                it without thinking much about it.</phrase> 

We organize shoes in our closet, 
            books on our book shelves, spices in our kitchen, receipts and records in tax preparation folders, and people on business projects and sports teams. Quite a few of us have jobs that involve
            specific types of organizing tasks. We might even have been explicitly trained to
            perform them by following specialized disciplinary practices. We might learn to do these
            tasks very well, but even then we often do not reflect on the similarity of the
            organizing tasks we do and those done by others, or on the similarity of those we do at
            work and those we do at home. We take for granted and as givens the concepts and methods
            used in the Organizing System we work with most often.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-azl_snr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm significance="preferred" zone="def_organizing_system">
                        <primary>organizing system</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>The goal of this book is to help readers become more self-conscious about what it
            means to organize resources of any type and about the principles by which the resources
            are organized. In particular, this book introduces the concept of an <phrase
                role="definition" xml:id="def_organizing_system"><glossterm
                    xml:id="term_organizing_system">Organizing System</glossterm>: an intentionally
                arranged collection of resources and the interactions they support.</phrase> The
            book analyzes the design decisions that go into any systematic organization of resources
            and the design patterns for the interactions that make use of the resources, as
            follows:</para>
        <formalpara audience="CORE"><title>We organize physical things.</title>
          <para xml:id="para-qwx_pzv_ps">Each of us organizes many kinds of
                    <hardware>things</hardware> in our lives<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>our books on
                bookshelves; printed financial records in folders and filing cabinets; clothes in
                dressers and closets; cooking and eating utensils in kitchen drawers and cabinets.
                Public libraries organize printed books, periodicals, maps, CDs, DVDs, and maybe
                some old record albums. Research libraries also organize rare manuscripts,
                pamphlets, musical scores, and many other kinds of printed information. Museums
                organize paintings, sculptures, and other artifacts of cultural, historical, or
                scientific value. Stores and suppliers organize their goods for sale to consumers
                and to each other. Sports leagues organize players into teams, and the teams
                organize players by position or role.</para></formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE"><title>We organize information about physical
                things.</title>
          <para xml:id="para-fvm_vzv_ps">Each of us organizes information about things: when we
                inventory the <hardware>contents of our house</hardware> for insurance purposes,
                when we sell our <hardware>unwanted stuff</hardware> on
                    <application>eBay</application>, or when we rate a restaurant on
                    <application>Yelp</application>. Library card catalogs, and their online
                replacements, tell us what books a library’s collection contains and where to find
                them. <hardware>Sensors</hardware> and <hardware>RFID tags</hardware> track the
                movement of goods<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>even library
                books<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>through supply chains, and the movement (or lack of
                movement) of <hardware>cars</hardware> on highways.</para></formalpara>
        <formalpara audience="CORE"><title>We organize digital things.</title>
          <para xml:id="para-qlr_21w_ps">Each of us organizes personal digital
                    information<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>email, documents, ebooks, MP3 and video
                files, appointments, contacts<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>on our computers, smartphone,
                ebook readers, or in <quote>the cloud,</quote>
                <symbol>&#8212;</symbol>through information services that use Internet protocols.
                Large research libraries organize digital journals and books, computer programs,
                government and scientific datasets, databases, and many other kinds of digital
                information. Companies organize their digital business records and customer
                information in enterprise applications, content repositories, and databases.
                Hospitals and medical clinics maintain and exchange electronic health records and
                digital X-rays and scans.</para></formalpara>
        <formalpara xml:id="para-mvm_snr_lr"><title>We organize information about digital things.</title>
            <para><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-mvm_snr_lr">
                            <primary>digital library</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info>Digital library catalogs, web portals, and aggregation websites organize
                links to other digital resources. Web search engines use content and link analysis
                along with relevance ratings, to organize the billions of web pages competing for
                our attention. Web-based services, data feeds and other information resources can be
                    <phrase revision="4.0" revisionflag="changed" audience="CORE DS">interconnected
                    and choreographed to carry out information-intensive business processes, or
                    aggregated and analyzed to enable prediction and personalization of information
                    services.</phrase></para></formalpara>
        <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-ccn_snr_lr">Let us take a closer look at
            these four different types or contexts of organizing. We contrasted <quote><phrase
                    remap="action">organizing things</phrase></quote> with <quote><phrase
                    remap="action">organizing information</phrase>.</quote> At first glance it might
            seem that organizing physical things like books, compact discs, machine parts, or
            cooking utensils has an entirely different character than organizing intangible digital
            things. We often arrange physical things according to their shapes, sizes, material of
            manufacture, or other intrinsic and visible properties: for example, we might arrange
            our shirts in the clothes closet by style and color, and we might organize our music
            collection by separating the old vinyl albums from the CDs. We might arrange books on
            bookshelves by their sizes, putting all the big, heavy picture books on the bottom
            shelf. Organization for clothes and information artifacts in tangible formats that is
            based on visible properties does not seem much like how you store and organize digital
            books on your Kindle or arrange digital music on your music player. Arranging, storing,
            and accessing X-rays printed on film might appear to have little in common with these
            activities when the X-rays are in digital form.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-zhn_snr_lr">It is hardly surprising that
            organizing things and organizing information sometimes do not differ much when
            information is represented in a tangible way. The era of ubiquitous digital information
            of the last decade or two is just a blip in time compared with the more than ten
            thousand years of human experience with information carved in stone, etched in clay, or
            printed with ink on papyrus, parchment, or paper. These tangible information artifacts
            have deeply embedded the notion of information as a physical thing in culture, language,
            and methods of information design and organization. This perspective toward tangible
            information artifacts is especially prominent in rare book collections where books are
            revered as physical objects with a focus on their distinctive binding, calligraphy, and
            typesetting.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-onn_snr_lr">Nevertheless, at other times
            there are substantial differences in how we organize things and how we organize
            information, even when the latter is in physical form. We more often organize our
                    <quote><hardware>information things</hardware></quote> according to what they
            are about rather than on the basis of their visible properties. At home we sort our CDs
            by artist or genre; we keep cookbooks separate from travel books, and fiction books
            apart from reference books. Libraries employ subject-based classification schemes that
            have a few hundred thousand distinct categories.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-p5n_snr_lr">Likewise, there are times
            when we pay little attention to the visible properties of tangible things when we
            organize them and instead arrange them according to functional or task properties. We
            keep screwdrivers, pliers, a hammer, a saw, a drill, and a level in a toolbox or
            together on a workbench, even though they have few visual properties in common. We are
            not organizing them because of what we see about them, but because of what we know about
            to use them. The task-based organization of the tools has some similarity to the
            subject-based organization of the library.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-tyn_snr_lr">We also contrasted
                    <quote><phrase remap="action">organizing things</phrase></quote> with
                <quote>organizing information about things.</quote> This difference seems clear if
            we consider the traditional library card catalog, whose printed cards describe the books
            on library shelves. When the things and the information about them are both in physical
            format, it is easy to see that the former is a primary resource and the latter a
            surrogate or associated resource that describes or relates to it.</para>
        <sidebar xml:id="chapter-1-sidebar-1">
            <title>What Is Information?</title>
            <info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-1" condition="print" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>sidebar</primary>
                        <secondary>What Is Information?</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-1" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>What Is Information?</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-1">
                        <primary>information</primary>
                        <secondary>as thing</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm audience="LIS" zone="chapter-1-sidebar-1">
                        <primary>Buckland, Michael</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm audience="LIS" zone="chapter-1-sidebar-1">
                        <primary>Nunberg, Geoff</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-1">
                        <primary>concept</primary>
                        <secondary>information</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>

            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-wd4_snr_lr" revision="4.0" revisionflag="changed"
                >Most of the hundreds of definitions of information treat it as an idea that swirls
                around equally hard-to-define terms like <quote>data,</quote>
                <quote>knowledge,</quote> and <quote>communication.</quote> Moreover, these
                intellectual and ideological perspectives on information coexist with more mundane
                uses of the term, as when we ask a station agent: <quote role="interrogative">Can
                    you give me some information about the train schedule?</quote></para>
            
            <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-dk4_snr_lr"
                >An abstract view of information as an intangible thing is the intellectual
                foundation for both modern information science and the information economy and
                society. Nevertheless, the abstract view of information often conflicts with the
                much older idea that information is a tangible thing that naturally arose when
                information was inextricably encoded in material formats. We often blur the sense of
                    <quote>information as content</quote> with the sense of <quote>information as
                    container,</quote> and we too easily treat the number of stored bits on a
                computer or in <quote>the cloud</quote> as a measure of information content or
                value.</para>
            
            <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-xn4_snr_lr" revision="4.0" revisionflag="changed"
                >Geoff Nunberg has eloquently explained in <citetitle linkend="Nunberg1996"
                    pubwork="book">Farewell to the Information Age</citetitle> that information is
                    <quote>a collection of notions, rather than a single coherent concept.</quote>
                <personname><firstname>Michael</firstname>
                    <surname>Buckland</surname></personname>’s oft-cited essay <citetitle
                    linkend="Buckland1991" pubwork="journal">Information as Thing</citetitle> argues
                against the notion that information is inherently intangible and instead defines it
                more broadly and provocatively based on function. A resource that can be learned
                from or serve as evidence is <quote>information-as-thing,</quote> a definition that
                treats the tangible objects in museum or personal collections as
                    information.<footnote xml:id="endnote-001" label="1" audience="LIS">
                    <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-ev4_snr_lv"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-001">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>LIS</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-001" userlevel="Professional">
                                    <primary>library science</primary>
                                    <secondary>citations</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info><citation xml:id="cite_Nunberg1996" linkend="Nunberg1996">(Nunberg
                            1996</citation>, <citation xml:id="cite_Nunberg2011"
                            linkend="Nunberg2011">2011)</citation>. <citation
                            xml:id="cite_Buckland1991" linkend="Buckland1991">(Buckland
                            1991)</citation>. See also <citation xml:id="cite_Bates2005"
                            linkend="Bates2005">(Bates 2005)</citation>.</para>
                </footnote></para>
        </sidebar>
        <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-lkp_snr_lr">When it comes to
                    <quote><phrase remap="action">organizing information about digital
                    things</phrase></quote> the contrast is much less clear. When you search for a
            book using a search engine, first you get the catalog description of the book, and often
            the book itself is just a click away. When the things and the information about them are
            both digital, the contrast we posed is not as sharp as when one or both of them is in a
            physical format. And while we used X-rays<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>on film or in digital
                format<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>as examples of things we might organize, when a
            physician studies an X-ray, is it not being used as information about the subject of the
            X-ray, namely, the patient? And when businesspeople make marketing and pricing decisions
            by analyzing digital information about what and when people buy, we can think of this as
            organizing customers into categories, or as organizing customer information.</para>
        <para audience="CORE CogSci Linguistics Philosophy" role="contrast" xml:id="para-ynp_snr_lr"
            >These differences and relationships between <quote>physical things</quote> and
                <quote>digital things</quote> have long been discussed and debated by philosophers,
            linguists, psychologists, and others. <phrase role="parenthetical">(See the sidebars,
                    <xref linkend="chapter-1-sidebar-1"/><phrase revision="4.0" revisionflag="added"
                    > and <xref linkend="chapter-1-sidebar-data-information"
            />.</phrase>)</phrase></para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-wqp_snr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-wqp_snr_lr">
                        <primary>zoo</primary>
                        <secondary>antelope as document</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>The distinctions among organizing physical things, organizing digital things, or
            organizing information about physical or digital things are challenging to describe
            because many of the words we might use are as overloaded with multiple meanings as
                <quote>information</quote> itself. For example, the library science perspective
            often uses presentation or implementation properties in definitions of
                <quote>document,</quote> using the term to refer only to traditional physical forms.
            In contrast, the informatics or computer science perspective takes an abstract view of
                <quote>document</quote> to refer to any self-contained unit of information,
            separating a document's content from its presentation or container.<footnote label="2"
                audience="Computing" xml:id="endnote-001a">
                <para audience="Computing" xml:id="para-ev4_snr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-001a">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Computing</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-001a" userlevel="Professional">
                                <primary>computing</primary>
                                <secondary>citations</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><citation xml:id="cite_Glushko2005" linkend="Glushko2005">(Glushko and
                        McGrath 2005)</citation>. </para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para audience="LIS" role="contrast" xml:id="para-jg2_xsd_xs" revision="4.0"
            revisionflag="changed"><phrase role="definition">The most abstract definition of
                    <quote>document,</quote> presented in <citetitle linkend="Buckland1997"
                    pubwork="journal">What is a Document?</citetitle> follows from Buckland's
                    <quote>information as thing</quote> idea. Because it can be studied to provide
                evidence, an antelope is both <quote>information as thing</quote> and also a
                    <quote>document</quote> when it is in a zoo, even though it is just an animal
                when it is running wild on the plains of Africa.</phrase> However, in 2015 the
            United States Supreme Court rejected this expansive definition in a case that hinged on
            whether a fish could be viewed as a document.<footnote xml:id="endnote-002" label="3"
                audience="Law">
                <para xml:id="para-avp_snr_lp" revision="3.0" revisionflag="changed" audience="LIS"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-002">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>LIS</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-002">
                                <primary>library science</primary>
                                <secondary>antelope</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><citation xml:id="cite_Buckland1997" linkend="Buckland1997">(Buckland
                        1997)</citation>. <phrase revision="3.0" revisionflag="added">The idea that
                        an antelope could be a document was first proposed in <citation
                            xml:id="cite_Briet1951" linkend="Briet1951">(Briet 1951)</citation>.
                    </phrase></para>
                <para xml:id="para-hr4_snr_la" audience="Law"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="para-hr4_snr_la" condition="print"
                                userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                                <primary>sidebar</primary>
                                <secondary>Can a Fish be a Document?</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="para-hr4_snr_la" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                                <primary>Can a Fish be a Document?</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="para-hr4_snr_la">
                                <primary>information</primary>
                                <secondary>as thing</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="para-hr4_snr_la">
                                <primary>Buckland, Michael</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="para-hr4_snr_la">
                                <primary>concept</primary>
                                <secondary>document</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>A commercial fisherman in Florida was found with fish in his catch below
                    the legal size limit. An inspector ordered him to return to port and hand the
                    fish over to the authorities; when he dumped them overboard instead, he was
                    charged with violating the Sarbanes-Oxley Act, a law drafted in response to
                    high-profile white-collar crimes such as the Enron scandal. The law imposes
                    harsh penalties for destroying <quote>any record, document, or tangible
                        object</quote> to impede a federal investigation. The fisherman argued that
                    the law should only apply to written documents, but the United States government
                    contended that because the fish were <quote>tangible objects</quote> whose
                    presence on the boat served as the only documentation of the allegedly illegal
                    fishing, there was no practical difference between a fish and a document in this
                    case. The Supreme Court ruled in favor of the fisherman, finding that
                        <quote>tangible object</quote> must be interpreted in the context of
                        <quote>record</quote> and <quote>document</quote> and, as such, only applies
                    to an object <quote>used to record or preserve information.</quote> The fact
                    that a fish is tangible evidence in this case does not make it a
                    document.</para>
                <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-ev4_snr_lz"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="para-ev4_snr_lz">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>LIS</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="para-ev4_snr_lz">
                                <primary>library science</primary>
                                <secondary>document</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><citation xml:id="cite_Buckland1991-1a" linkend="Buckland1991">(Buckland
                        1991)</citation>.</para>
                <para audience="Law" xml:id="para-dz4_snr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="para-dz4_snr_lr">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Law</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="para-dz4_snr_lr">
                                <primary>law</primary>
                                <secondary>SCOTUS</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><citation xml:id="cite_Liptak2014" linkend="Liptak2014">(Liptak
                        2014)</citation>. Brief for the United States in Opposition, Yates v. United
                    States. SCOTUSblog, <date>March 14, 2014</date>. <link
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.scotusblog.com/case-files/cases/yates-v-united-states/"
                            ><uri>http://www.scotusblog.com/case-files/cases/yates-v-united-states/</uri></link></para>
                <para audience="Law" xml:id="para-bcp_snr_lr">For the complete history of the case,
                    see: <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.scotusblog.com/case-files/cases/yates-v-united-states/"
                            ><uri>http://www.scotusblog.com/case-files/cases/yates-v-united-states/</uri></link>.</para>
                <para audience="Law" xml:id="para-mfp_snr_lr">See also the related
                        <citetitle>Sarbanes-Oxley Act</citetitle> endnote.<footnoteref
                        audience="Law" linkend="endnote-086"/></para>
            </footnote></para>
        <sidebar audience="CORE DS" xml:id="chapter-1-sidebar-data-information" revision="4.0"
            revisionflag="added">
            <title>The Distinction between Data and Information</title>
            <info userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-data-information">
                        <primary>sidebar</primary>
                        <secondary>Distinction between Data and Information</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-data-information">
                        <primary>Distinction between Data and Information</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-data-information">
                        <primary>DIKW hierarchy</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-data-information">
                        <primary>knowledge pyramid</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>
            <para xml:id="para-wnx_xd5_4v" audience="CORE DS">Astute readers might have noticed that
                we included sensor data as <quote>information about physical things</quote> and data
                feeds as <quote>information about digital things.</quote> Many textbooks in the
                information science and knowledge management fields distinguish data and information
                in a more precise way. To them, data sits at the bottom of an Information Hierarchy,
                Knowledge Pyramid, or DIKW Hierarchy in which Data is transformed into Information,
                which is transformed into Knowledge, which is then transformed into Wisdom.</para>
            <para xml:id="para-kvf_125_4v" audience="CORE DS">In this framework, data are raw or
                elementary observations about properties of objects, events, and their environment.
                Data becomes information when it is aggregated, processed, analyzed, formatted, and
                organized to add meaning and context so it can be used to answer questions. This
                processing can include calculation, inference, or refinement operations on the data.
                For example, measurements of temperature, precipitation, and wind speed are data.
                When combined and summarized, a set of data becomes statistical information about
                the weather on a particular day. When collected over a period of months or years,
                these datasets become information about the climate of the location where they were
                collected.</para>
            <para xml:id="para-yxw_125_4v" audience="CORE DS">The Discipline of Organizing does not
                make this sharp contrast between data and information in the Hierarchy/Pyramid.
                People who read this book are likely to be aspiring or practicing professionals in
                information-intensive industries where information and data are often treated as
                synonyms to mean the content of a database or data-managing application. A
                distinction between data and information might be useful in theory, but not in these
                applied settings. </para>
            <para xml:id="para-etp_b25_4v" audience="CORE DS">The distinction between data and
                information is also being blurred by the expansion in the scope of the definition of
                data in the emerging career field of <firstterm linkend="gloss_data-science">data
                    science</firstterm>. Indeed, a popular introductory text eliminates information
                entirely from the Hierarchy/Pyramid with its title, <citetitle audience="CORE DS"
                    linkend="Larose2014" xml:id="cite_Larose2014">Discovering knowledge in data: an
                    introduction to data mining.</citetitle><footnote audience="DS" label="4"
                    xml:id="endnote-002a" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added">
                        <para xml:id="para-sss_2ts_sv"  audience="DS">The DIKW hierarchy seems to have been inspired by
                            <citetitle linkend="Eliot1934">The Rock, A Pageant Play</citetitle>
                        <citation xml:id="cite_Eliot1934" linkend="Eliot1934">(Eliot
                            1934)</citation> by the poet T S Eliot, whose opening chorus contains
                        these lines: </para>
                        <para xml:id="para-okz_fts_sv">
                        <literallayout>Where is the wisdom we have lost in knowledge? 
Where is the knowledge we have lost in information? </literallayout>
                    </para>
                        <para xml:id="para-dhf_gts_sv" audience="DS">Most people credit Ackoff’s <citetitle
                            linkend="Ackoff1989">From Data to Wisdom</citetitle>
                        <citation xml:id="cite_Ackoff1989" linkend="Ackoff1989">(Ackoff
                            1989)</citation> as the first articulation of the hierarchy in an
                        information science and systems context. The hierarchy is mentioned in
                        nearly twenty textbooks, but their close analysis by <citation
                            xml:id="cite_Rowley2007" linkend="Rowley2007">(Rowley 2007)</citation>
                        reveals only partial agreement on the definitions and relationships among
                        the four key concepts. The hierarchy has been criticized as lacking in
                        philosophical rigor <citation xml:id="cite_Fricke2009" linkend="Fricke2009"
                            >(Fricke 2009)</citation> and for ignoring the context-specificity of
                        how knowledge is learned and applied <citation xml:id="cite_Jennex2009"
                            linkend="Jennex2009">(Jennex 2009)</citation>.<citation
                            linkend="Larose2014" xml:id="cite2_Larose2014">  (Larose
                            2014)</citation></para>
                </footnote></para>
        </sidebar>
                    
                        
                       
            
               <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-wqp_snr_lz" revisionflag="added"
            revision="3.0"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-wqp_snr_lz">
                        <primary>library science</primary>
                        <secondary>document</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-wqp_snr_lz">
                        <primary>library science</primary>
                        <secondary>authorship</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-wqp_snr_lz" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>Melville, Herman</primary>
                        <secondary>is the author of</secondary>
                        <tertiary>Moby Dick</tertiary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-wqp_snr_lz" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>Moby Dick</primary>
                        <secondary>has author</secondary>
                        <tertiary>Melville, Herman</tertiary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>Similar definitional variation occurs with <quote>author</quote> or
                <quote>creator.</quote> When we say that
                        <quote><personname><firstname>Herman</firstname><surname>Melville</surname></personname>
                is the author of <citetitle linkend="Melville1851" pubwork="book">Moby
                    Dick</citetitle></quote>
            <citation xml:id="cite_Melville1851" linkend="Melville1851">(Melville 1851)</citation>
            the meaning of <quote>author</quote> does not depend on whether we have a printed copy
            or an ebook in mind, but what counts as authorship varies a great deal across academic
            disciplines. Furthermore, different standards for describing resources disagree in the
            precision with which they identify the person(s) or organization(s) primarily
            responsible for creating the intellectual content of the resource, People who are
            serious about music description rightly criticize streaming services and online stores
            that have only a single <quote>artist</quote> field because this fails to distinguish
            the composer, conductor, orchestra, and other people with distinct roles in creating the
            music. </para>
            
           
            
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ezp_snr_lr">If we allow the concept of information to be
            anything we can study<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>to be <quote>anything that
                informs</quote><symbol>&#8212;</symbol>the concept becomes unbounded. Our goal in
            this book is to bridge the intellectual gulf that separates the many disciplines that
            share the goal of organizing but differ in what they organize. This requires us to focus
            on situations where information exists because of intentional acts to create or
            organize. <phrase role="parenthetical">(See the sidebar, <xref
                    linkend="chapter-1-sidebar-2"/>)</phrase></para>
        <sidebar xml:id="chapter-1-sidebar-2" audience="CORE" role="contrast">
            <title>The Discipline of Organizing</title>
            <info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-2" condition="print" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>sidebar</primary>
                        <secondary>The Discipline of Organizing</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-2">
                        <primary>The Discipline of Organizing</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-2">
                        <primary>discipline</primary>
                        <secondary>of organizing</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-dnq_snr_lr" revision="4.0" revisionflag="changed"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm significance="preferred" zone="def_discipline">
                            <primary>discipline</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info><phrase role="definition" xml:id="def_discipline">A <glossterm
                        xml:id="term_discipline">discipline</glossterm> is an integrated field of
                    study in which there is some level of agreement about the issues and problems
                    that deserve study, how they are interrelated, how they should be studied, and
                    how findings or theories about the issues and problems should be
                    evaluated.</phrase>
                <phrase role="definition" xml:id="def_framework">A <glossterm
                        xml:id="term_framework" xreflabel="framework">framework</glossterm> is a set
                    of concepts that provide the basic structure for understanding a domain,
                    enabling a common vocabulary for different explanatory theories.</phrase>
            </para>
            <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-jsq_snr_lr"><firstterm
                    xml:id="first_organizing" linkend="gloss_organizing" xreflabel="Organizing"
                    >Organizing</firstterm> is a fundamental issue in many disciplines, most notably
                library and information science, computer science, systems analysis, informatics,
                law, economics, and business. However, these disciplines have only limited agreement
                in how they approach problems of organizing and what they seek as their solutions.
                For example, library and information science has traditionally studied organizing
                from a public sector bibliographic perspective, paying careful attention to user
                requirements for access and preservation, and offering prescriptive methods and
                    solutions.<footnote xml:id="endnote-003" label="5" audience="LIS">
                    <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-uxq_snr_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-003">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>LIS</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-003">
                                    <primary>library science</primary>
                                    <secondary>bibliographic universe</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-003" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                                    <primary>Wilson, Patrick</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-003">
                                    <primary>bibliographic</primary>
                                    <secondary>universe</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>We can continue the debate in the previous paragraphs and the
                        sidebar, <xref linkend="chapter-1-sidebar-1"/> by pointing out that in both
                        common and professional usage, <quote>bibliographic</quote> activities
                        involve describing and organizing information resources of the kinds that
                        might be found in a library. But noted information scientist
                                <personname><firstname>Patrick</firstname>
                            <surname>Wilson</surname></personname> argued for a much broader expanse
                        of the bibliographic universe, suggesting that <quote>it includes
                            manuscripts as well as printed books, bills of lading and street signs
                            as well as personal letters, inscriptions on stone as well as phonograph
                            recordings of speeches, and most notably, memorized texts in human heads
                            and texts stored up in the <emphasis>memories</emphasis> of
                            machines</quote>
                        <citation xml:id="cite_Wilson1968" linkend="Wilson1968">(Wilson 1968, p.
                            12)</citation>.</para>
                </footnote> In contrast, computer science and informatics tend to study organizing
                in the context of information-intensive business applications with a focus on
                process efficiency, system architecture, and implementation. The disciplines of
                management and industrial organization deal with the organization of human,
                material, and information resources in contexts shaped by commercial, competitive,
                and regulatory forces. </para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ucr_snr_lr" revision="4.0" revisionflag="changed"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm significance="preferred" zone="def_framework">
                            <primary>framework</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info>This book presents a more abstract framework for issues and problems of
                organizing that emphasizes the common concepts and goals of the disciplines that
                study them. <phrase role="principle statement">Our framework proposes that every
                    system of organization involves a collection of resources, and we can treat
                    physical things, digital things, and information about such things as resources. </phrase>
                <phrase role="statement principle">Every system of organization involves a choice of
                    properties or principles used to describe and arrange the resources, and ways of
                    supporting interactions with the resources. </phrase>By comparing and
                contrasting how these activities take place in different contexts and domains, we
                can identify patterns of organizing and see that Organizing Systems often follow a
                common life cycle. We can create a discipline of organizing in a disciplined
                way.</para>
        </sidebar>
        <para audience="CORE Computing LIS Web" xml:id="para-wdq_snr_lr" revision="4.0"
            revisionflag="changed">Many of the foundational topics for a discipline of organizing
            have traditionally been presented from the perspective of the library sector and taught
            as <quote>library and information science.</quote> These include bibliographic
            description, classification, naming, authority control, curation, and information
            standards. In recent decades these foundations have been built on and extended by
            computer science, cognitive science, informatics, and other new fields to include more
            private sector and non-bibliographic contexts, multimedia and social media, and new
            information-intensive applications and service systems enabled by mobile, pervasive, and
            scientific computing. The latest additions to the discipline of organizing are coming
            from <glossterm linkend="gloss_data-science">data science</glossterm> and <glossterm
                linkend="gloss_machine_learning">machine learning</glossterm>, introducing
            considerations of speed and scale that arise when massive computational power and new
            statistical techniques are harnessed to organize and act on information.</para>
        <para xml:id="para-s1m_m4v_rv" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added" audience="CORE DS">The
            new methods and tools of <glossterm linkend="gloss_data-science">data
                science</glossterm> and <glossterm linkend="gloss_machine_learning">machine
                learning</glossterm> let us organize more information, to do it faster, and to make
            predictions based on what people have clicked on, bought, or said. But this is not the
            first time that new ideas and technologies have challenged how people organized and
            interacted with resources. Fifty years ago, searchable online catalogs radically changed
            how people used libraries. The web, invented less than thirty years ago so that
            scientists could share technical reports, is now an essential part of many human
            activities. It is important not to view the latest new thing as changing everything,
            because new things will continue to come, and these technology breakthroughs still
            depend on and complement the organizing work done by people. Data science will not
            replace human organizers, any more than any other science has replaced humans. (See
            sidebar, <xref linkend="sidebar-DataScience"/>).</para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="comparative" xml:id="para-d3q_snr_lr">This is why we need to
            take a transdisciplinary view that lets us emphasize what the different disciplines have
            in common and how they fit together rather than what distinguishes them. Resource
            selection, organizing, interaction design, and maintenance are taught in every
            discipline, but these concepts go by different names. A vocabulary for discussing common
            organizing challenges and issues that might be otherwise obscured by narrow disciplinary
            perspectives helps us understand existing systems of organizing better while also
            suggesting how to invent new ones by making different design choices.</para>
        <sidebar xml:id="sidebar-DataScience" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added" audience="CORE DS">
            <title>Data Science and the Discipline of Organizing</title>
            <info userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-DataScience">
                        <primary>sidebar</primary>
                        <secondary>Data Science and the Discipline of Organizing</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-DataScience">
                        <primary>Data Science and the Discipline of Organizing</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-DataScience">
                        <primary>data science</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-DataScience">
                        <primary>tall data</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-DataScience">
                        <primary>wide data</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-DataScience">
                        <primary>data</primary>
                        <secondary>wide</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-DataScience">
                        <primary>data</primary>
                        <secondary>tall</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>
            <para xml:id="para-fgg_tnv_rv" audience="CORE DS">Advances in computing power and
                statistical techniques are making it possible to identify patterns in data and
                extract meaningful information at a scale never before possible. Many books and
                articles about <glossterm linkend="gloss_data-science">data science</glossterm>,
                machine learning, and predictive analytics make bold predictions that these emerging
                fields will radically change the world. These claims are both provocative and
                promising, but at its core, data science is about how resources are selected,
                described, and organized; concepts with a long tradition in information and library
                science. Instead of organizing and describing the books in a library or the products
                in a warehouse, a data scientist might organize information about books or products
                into massive data tables, treating each resource as a row and its descriptive
                properties as the columns. After people might have organized books or products into
                categories, machine learning techniques might classify new books or products using
                those categories, or perhaps discover new categories based on access or purchasing
                behaviors. So while the techniques of data science are new, many of the challenges
                are not; data scientists need to select resources wisely and decide how best to
                describe them; they need to understand that resource description and categorization
                can be biased; they need to understand the tradeoffs and complements between people
                and computers; and, they need to test the discoveries that algorithms make with
                controlled experiments.</para>
            <para xml:id="para-yrr_tnv_rv" audience="CORE DS">To make sense of the discussions
                around data science, one must understand the difference between kind and degree. A
                hundred years ago, a car’s highway travel speed was about forty miles an hour.
                Today’s cars travel twice as fast, but this is just a change in degree. However, an
                increase in speed to about 17,500 miles an hour achieves an <quote>orbital
                    velocity</quote> that allows us to go into Earth orbit in space, travel that is
                different in kind.</para>
            <para xml:id="para-ift_5nv_rv" audience="CORE DS">What about data science? Some data
                science involves collections of data that are <quote>tall,</quote> containing many
                millions or even billions of records that each have a relatively small number of
                variables. Being able to analyze <quote>tall</quote> data more rapidly than ever
                before is primarily a change in degree compared with traditional database
                techniques. Nevertheless, for collections of data that are <quote>wide,</quote>
                where each record might contain hundreds or thousands of variables, data science
                techniques might allow us to see patterns that could not be seen at all, or could
                not be seen affordably and in quantity. Here, data science might be yielding changes
                in kind.<footnote audience="DS" label="6" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added"
                    xml:id="endnote-002b">
                    <para xml:id="para-thp_sts_sv" audience="DS">Siegel’s <citetitle
                            linkend="Siegel2013">Predictive Analytics: The Power to Predict who will
                            Click, Buy, Lie or Die</citetitle>” <citation linkend="Siegel2013"
                            xml:id="cite_Siegel2013">(Siegel 2013)</citation> is written for a
                        non-technical audience and enthusiastically describes over 100 applications.
                            <citetitle linkend="Domingos2015">The Master Algorithm</citetitle>
                        <citation xml:id="cite_Domingos2015" linkend="Domingos2015">(Domingos
                            2015)</citation> shares Siegel’s enthusiasm but is far more technical;
                        the book attempts to explain and compare the five <quote>tribes</quote> of
                        machine learning: the symbolists, connectionists, evolutionaries, Bayesians,
                        and analogizers. The title of Chris Anderson’s provocative article in Wired
                        Magazine <citation xml:id="cite_Anderson2008" linkend="Anderson2008"
                            >(Anderson, 2008)</citation> is self-explanatory: <quote>The end of
                            theory: The data deluge makes the scientific method obsolete.</quote>
                    </para>
                    <para xml:id="para-b2h_wts_sv" audience="DS"><quote>Difference in kind or
                            difference in degree</quote> is an important issue in legal contexts and
                        more generally arises whenever there is a disagreement about whether some
                        difference or change is strict and categorical or whether it is incremental.
                        We introduce it here so that readers can think critically about the
                        socio-business-technical changes that might come about as a result of new
                        methods and technologies for organizing and analyzing data. We believe that
                        data science is on its way to becoming an important part of the organizing
                        tool box. But everyone needs to remember that humans own the tool box, and
                        that they design and build the tools..</para>
                </footnote></para>
        </sidebar>
    </section>
    <!--              -->
    <?dbfo clear ?>
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <?need 10cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-1.2" label="1.2">
        <title>The <quote>Organizing System</quote> Concept</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-1.2">
                    <primary>organizing system</primary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm zone="section-1.2">
                    <primary>concept</primary>
                    <secondary>organizing system</secondary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>

        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-q3r_snr_lr"><info><itermset>
            <indexterm zone="para-q3r_snr_lr">
                <primary>computational</primary>
                <secondary>agents</secondary>
            </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>We propose to unify many perspectives about organizing and information with
            the concept of an <glossterm linkend="gloss_organizing_system">Organizing
                System</glossterm>, <emphasis>an intentionally arranged collection of resources and
                the interactions they support.</emphasis> This definition brings together several
            essential ideas that we will briefly introduce in this chapter and then develop in
            detail in subsequent chapters.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="descriptive" xml:id="para-hnr_snr_lr"><xref
                linkend="chapter-1-figure-1.1" xrefstyle="select: label"/> depicts a conceptual
            model of an Organizing System that shows intentionally arranged resources, interactions
            (distinguished by different types of arrows), and the human and computational agents
            interacting with the resources in different contexts.</para>
        
        <figure xml:id="chapter-1-figure-1.1" floatstyle="true" label="1.1">
            <title>An Organizing System.</title>
            <mediaobject xml:id="chapter-1-figure-1.1a">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="figs/Figure-1.1.jpg" format="JPG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase role="ALT descriptive">A conceptual representation of an Organizing
                        System. The left side, labeled <quote>Arranged Collection of
                            Resources,</quote> presents organized groups of round, square and
                        circular shapes within a circle. The right side, labeled <quote>Supported
                            Interactions,</quote> presents a group of icons representing, for
                        example, a computer terminal, a human agent, a mobile phone, and so on.
                        There is a grouping of four arrows between the two sides; two pointed left
                        and two pointed right.</phrase>
                </textobject>
                <caption>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-qsr_snr_lr"><phrase role="caption">An
                            Organizing System is a collection of resources arranged in ways that
                            enable people or computational agents to interact with them.</phrase>
                    </para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        
        
        <para audience="CORE Computing Linguistics LIS" role="contrast principle"
            xml:id="para-fyr_snr_lr">An Organizing System is an abstract characterization of how
            some collection of resources is described and arranged to enable human or computational
            agents to interact with the resources. The Organizing System is an architectural and
            conceptual view that is distinct from the physical arrangement of resources that might
            embody it, and also distinct from the person, enterprise, or institution that implements
            and operates it. These distinctions are sometimes hard to maintain in ordinary language;
            for example, we might describe some set of resource descriptions, organizing principles,
            and supported interactions as a <quote>library</quote> Organizing System. However, we
            also need at times to refer to a <quote>library</quote> as the institution in which this
            Organizing System operates, and of course the idea of a <quote>library</quote> as a
            physical facility is deeply engrained in language and culture.</para>
        
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-hds_snr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-hds_snr_lr">
                        <primary>cataloging</primary>
                        <secondary>bibliographic domain</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-hds_snr_lr">
                        <primary>Svenonius, Elaine</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-hds_snr_lr">
                        <primary>tradeoffs</primary>
                        <secondary>principle</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-hds_snr_lr">
                        <primary>principle</primary>
                        <secondary>tradeoffs</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info><phrase role="statement" xml:id="TIFIO">Our concept of the Organizing System was
                in part inspired by the concepts proposed in <date>2000</date> for bibliographic
                domains by <personname><firstname>Elaine</firstname>
                    <surname>Svenonius,</surname></personname> in <citetitle linkend="Svenonius2000"
                    pubwork="book">The Intellectual Foundation of Information
                    Organization.</citetitle> She recognized that the traditional <firstterm
                    linkend="gloss_information_organization" xml:id="first_information_organization"
                    >information organization</firstterm> activities of bibliographic description
                and cataloging were complemented, and partly compensated for, by automated text
                processing and indexing that were usually treated as part of a separate discipline
                of <firstterm linkend="gloss_information_retrieval"
                    xml:id="first_information_retrieval">information retrieval</firstterm>.</phrase>
            <phrase role="statement principle"><personname>
                    <surname>Svenonius</surname></personname> proposed that decisions about
                organizing information and decisions about retrieving information were inherently
                linked by a tradeoff principle and thus needed to be viewed as an interconnected
                system: <emphasis><quote>The effectiveness of a system for accessing information is
                        a direct function of the intelligence put into organizing it</quote>
                    (p.ix)</emphasis>.</phrase> We celebrate and build upon her insights by
            beginning each of the sub-parts of <xref linkend="chapter-2n" xrefstyle="short"/> with a
            quote from her book.<footnote xml:id="endnote-004" label="7" audience="LIS">
                <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-jgs_snr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-004">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>LIS</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-004" userlevel="Professional">
                                <primary>library science</primary>
                                <secondary>citations</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><citation xml:id="cite_Svenonius2000" linkend="Svenonius2000">(Svenonius
                        2000)</citation>.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        <para audience="CORE Computing" role="contrast" xml:id="para-njs_snr_lr"
            revisionflag="added" revision="3.0"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-njs_snr_lr">
                        <primary>tradeoffs</primary>
                        <secondary>inherent</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>A systems view of information organization and information retrieval captures and
            provides structure for the inherent tradeoffs obscured by the silos of traditional
            disciplinary and category perspectives: the more effort put into organizing information
                <quote>on the way in</quote> when it is created or added to a collection, the more
            effectively it can be retrieved, and the more effort put into retrieving information
                <quote>on the way out,</quote> the less it needs to be organized first. <phrase
                revision="4.0" revisionflag="added">Sometimes a collection of resources is highly
                organized, but because it was organized by someone else for different purposes that
                have in mind, we need to reorganize it “on the way in.” This is especially common
                with digital text or datasets, where previously organized resources or their
                descriptions might be sorted, translated in format or language, combined,
                summarized, or otherwise transformed to fit into a new Organizing System. For
                example, to understand seasonal buying patterns, a retailer might combine shopping
                data with weather data and calendar data about commonly-watched sporting events
                (because bad weather and broadcast sports cause people to stay home), and all three
                datasets would need to describe <quote>time</quote> and <quote>location</quote> in
                the same way.</phrase>
        </para>
        <para audience="CORE Computing" role="contrast" revisionflag="added" revision="3.0"
            xml:id="para-wwr_qg5_4v">A systems view no longer contrasts information organization as
            a human activity and information retrieval as a machine activity, or information
            organization as a topic for library and information science and information retrieval as
            one for computer science. Instead, we readily see that computers now assist people in
            organizing and that people contribute much of the information used  <phrase
                revision="4.0" revisionflag="added">when computers analyze and organize
                resources.</phrase>
            <phrase audience="CORE DS" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added">For example, many
                algorithms for computational classification use <glossterm
                    linkend="gloss_supervised_learning">supervised learning</glossterm> approaches
                that start with items classified by people</phrase>. </para>
            
             <para audience="CORE" revisionflag="added" revision="3.0">Finally, a systems view can
            be applied to Organizing Systems with any kind of resource, enabling more nuanced
            discussion of how economic, social, and cognitive costs and benefits of organizing are
            allocated among different stakeholders. <phrase revision="4.0" revisionflag="added"
                >Every Organizing System is biased by the perspectives and experiences of the people
                who create it. Some of these biases are inescapable, a kind of automatic organizing,
                because they reflect innate human perceptual and cognitive capabilities. Our minds
                impose structure and find patterns, even when there aren’t any, and we are not
                capable of acting perfectly rationally, so we simplify without realizing it. People
                are also not very good at thinking about future possibilities and revising their
                expectations given new evidence, and this mental inertia makes us preserve resources
                and interactions in Organizing Systems that are no longer needed. Other biases in
                Organizing Systems reflect more intentional choices that</phrase> implicitly or
            explicitly create winners or losers, treat some interactions as preferred while
            deprecating others, or otherwise impose or overlay a set of values on the stakeholders
            of the system. For example, many Organizing Systems arrange people in groups or queues
            to make interactions more efficient, but when an airline gives boarding priority to
            customers who paid more for their tickets it might not seem fair to you if are in the
            last boarding group. </para>
    </section> 
             
        <!--              -->
        <?dbfo clear ?>
        <?need 10cm ?>
        
        <section xml:id="section-1.3" label="1.3">
            <title>The Concept of <quote>Resource</quote></title>
            <info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="section-1.3">
                        <primary>resource</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="section-1.3">
                        <primary>concept</primary>
                        <secondary>resource</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="section-1.3">
                        <primary>HTTP</primary>
                        <secondary>resource</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="section-1.3">
                        <primary>URI</primary>
                        <secondary>resource</secondary>
                    </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>

            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-kms_snr_lr"><phrase role="definition"
                    xml:id="def_resource_ordinary"><glossterm xml:id="term_resource_ordinary"
                        xreflabel="resource">Resource</glossterm> has an ordinary sense of anything
                    of value that can support goal-oriented activity. This definition means that a
                    resource can be a <hardware>physical thing</hardware>, a non-physical thing,
                    information about physical things, information about non-physical things, or
                    anything you want to organize. Other words that aim for this broad scope are
                        <firstterm xml:id="first_entity" linkend="gloss_entity">entity</firstterm>,
                        <firstterm linkend="gloss_object">object</firstterm>, <firstterm
                        linkend="gloss_item">item</firstterm>, and <firstterm
                        linkend="gloss_instance">instance</firstterm>. <firstterm
                        linkend="gloss_document">Document</firstterm> is often used for an
                    information resource in either digital or physical format; <firstterm
                        linkend="gloss_artifact">artifact</firstterm> refers to resources created by
                    people, and <firstterm linkend="gloss_asset">asset</firstterm> for resources
                    with economic value.</phrase>
            </para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ups_snr_lr"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-ups_snr_lr">
                            <primary>URI</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="para-ups_snr_lr">
                            <primary>HTTP</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info><phrase role="definition" xml:id="def_resource_internet"><glossterm
                        linkend="gloss_resource" xml:id="term_resource">Resource</glossterm> has
                    specialized meaning in Internet architecture. It is conventional to describe web
                    pages, images, videos, and so on as <glossterm linkend="gloss_resource"
                        >resources</glossterm>, and the protocol for accessing them, <firstterm
                        xml:id="first_HTTP"><citerefentry
                            xreflabel="Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP)"><refentrytitle>Hypertext
                                Transfer
                            Protocol</refentrytitle><manvolnum>HTTP</manvolnum></citerefentry></firstterm>,
                    uses the <firstterm xml:id="first_URI"><citerefentry><refentrytitle>Uniform
                                Resource
                            Identifier</refentrytitle><manvolnum>URI</manvolnum></citerefentry></firstterm>.</phrase><footnote 
                    xml:id="endnote-005" label="8" audience="Web">
                    <para audience="Web" xml:id="para-sss_snr_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-005">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Web</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-005">
                                    <primary>URI</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-005">
                                    <primary>HTTP</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-005">
                                    <primary>Web</primary>
                                    <secondary>content negotiation</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-005">
                                    <primary>business applications</primary>
                                    <secondary>content negotiation</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>The <abbrev>URI</abbrev> identifies a resource as an abstract entity
                        that can have <quote>multiple representations,</quote> which are the
                            <quote>things</quote> that are actually exposed through applications or
                        user interfaces. The <abbrev>HTTP</abbrev> protocol can transfer the
                        representation that best satisfies the content properties specified by a web
                        client, most often a browser. This means that interactions with web
                        resources are always with their representations rather than directly with
                        the resource <foreignphrase xml:lang="Latn">per se</foreignphrase>. The
                        representation of the resource might seem to be implied by the
                            <abbrev>URI</abbrev> (as when it ends in <filename>.htm</filename> or
                            <filename>.html</filename> to suggest text in <firstterm
                            xml:id="first_HTML"><citerefentry xml:id="ref_HTML"
                                    ><refentrytitle>Hypertext Markup
                                    Language</refentrytitle><manvolnum>HTML</manvolnum></citerefentry></firstterm>
                        format), but the <abbrev>URI</abbrev> is not required to indicate anything
                        about the <quote>representation.</quote> A web resource can be a static web
                        page, but it can also be dynamic content generated at the time of access by
                        a program or service associated with the <abbrev>URI</abbrev>. Some
                        resources like geolocations have <quote>no representations at all;</quote>
                        the resource is simply some point or space and the interaction is
                            <quote>show me how to get there.</quote> The browser and web server can
                        engage in <quote>content negotiation</quote> to determine which
                            <quote>representation</quote> to retrieve, and this is particularly
                        important when that format further requires an <application>external
                            application</application> or
                            <quote><application>plug-in</application></quote> in order for it to be
                        rendered properly, as it does when the server returns a Power Point file or
                        an other file format that is not built into the browser.</para>
                    <para audience="Web" xml:id="para-hvs_snr_lr">Internet architecture’s definition
                        of <glossterm linkend="gloss_resource">resource</glossterm> as a conceptual
                        entity that is never directly interacted with is difficult for most people
                        to apply when those resources are <hardware>physical or tangible
                            objects</hardware>, because then it surely seems like we are interacting
                        with something real. So we will most often talk about interactions with
                        resources, and will mention <quote>resource representations</quote> only
                        when it is necessary to align precisely with the narrower Internet
                        architecture sense.</para>
                </footnote></para>
            
            
            <sidebar xml:id="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets">
                <?dbhtml sidebar-width="40%"?>
                <?dbhtml float-type="left"?>
                <?dbfo sidebar-width="58%"?>
                <?dbfo float-type="left"?>
                <title>Concert Tickets</title>
                <info userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets">
                            <primary>Concert Tickets</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" condition="print"  audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>sidebar</primary>
                            <secondary>Concert Tickets</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>The Beatles</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>Elton John</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>The Grateful Dead</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>Emerson, Lake and Palmer</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>Rod Stewart and the Faces</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>Maria Muldaur</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>The Who</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>U2</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>CSN&amp;Y</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>YES</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>Wings</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>The Rolling Stones</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>Neil Young</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>Ten Years After</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>Pink Floyd</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>Doobie Brothers</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>Bob Marley and the Wailers</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>Jethro Tull</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>Simon &amp; Garfunkel</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>Santana</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>Weather Report</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>The Bee Gees</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>Deep Purple</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>Arlington Theater</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>UCSB Campus Stadium</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>Santa Barbara County Bowl</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>Maple Leaf Gardens</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1b-Concert-Tickets" audience="LIS Computing CogSci">
                            <primary>Colisee de Quebec</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info>
                <informalfigure xml:id="inf-fig-Ch1-Tickets">
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="Pictures/1.2.1-Tickets.JPG" format="JPG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <textobject>
                            <phrase role="ALT descriptive">A collage of concert tickets. The face
                                value of the ticket and various terms and conditions are included on
                                some tickets. Featured performers listed include: the Beatles; the
                                Rolling Stones; the Grateful Dead;  Neil Young; CSN&amp;Y; Simon
                                &amp; Garfunkel; Bob Marley &amp; the Wailers; the Who; YES; U2; Ten
                                Years After; Pink Floyd; Deep Purple; the Doobie Brothers; Elton
                                John; Rod Stewart and the Faces; Emerson, Lake and Palmer; Jethro
                                Tull; Frank Zappa;  Weather Report; Maria Muldaur; Wings; and, the
                                Bee Gees. Event dates range between 1964 and 2006. Venues include
                                University of Toronto's Varsity Stadium, Maple Leaf Gardens,
                                Skydome, Colisee de Quebec, Montreal's Bell Centre, Santa Barbara
                                County Bowl, Arlington Theater, and UCSB Campus Stadium.</phrase>
                        </textobject>
                        <caption>
                            <para xml:id="para-r3t_snr_lr">Tickets are physical artifacts that
                                convey event-related <glossterm linkend="gloss_metadata"
                                    >metadata</glossterm>: including time, place, and seat number;
                                price and terms of admission; and featured performers. <phrase>For
                                    concert goers, tickets offer the promise of all that, and a
                                    memory of the ineffable quality of more.</phrase></para>
                            <para xml:id="para-fmt_snr_lr"><phrase role="credit">(Photo by
                                            <personname><firstname>Murray</firstname>
                                        <surname>Maloney</surname></personname>.)</phrase></para>
                        </caption>
                    </mediaobject>
                </informalfigure>
            </sidebar>
            <sidebar xml:id="sidebar-1.2.1-Concert-Tickets">
                <?dbhtml sidebar-width="60%"?>
                <?dbhtml float-type="right"?>
                <?dbfo sidebar-width="38%"?>
                <?dbfo float-type="right"?>
                <title>Concert Ticket</title>
                <info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1-Concert-Tickets" condition="print" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                            <primary>sidebar</primary>
                            <secondary>Concert Tickets</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1-Concert-Tickets">
                            <primary>Concert Tickets</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1-Concert-Tickets">
                            <primary>resource</primary>
                            <secondary>primary</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-1.2.1-Concert-Tickets">
                            <primary>resource</primary>
                            <secondary>description</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info>
                
                <para xml:id="para-lpt_snr_lr">A concert ticket is a vehicle for conveying a package
                    of assertions about an event, so it is a <glossterm
                        linkend="gloss_description_resource">description resource</glossterm>, like
                    a card in a library card catalog. A concert ticket is also a <glossterm
                        linkend="gloss_resource">resource</glossterm> in its own right, with
                    intrinsic value; it can be bought and sold, sometimes for a greater price than
                    its <glossterm linkend="gloss_resource_description">resource
                        description</glossterm> specifies. A ticket is a license to use a seat in a
                    venue for a specified purpose at a specified time; after the event, the ticket
                    loses its intrinsic value, but might acquire extrinsic value as an artifact in a
                    collection like this one. </para>
            </sidebar>
            
            <para audience="CORE Computing Web" xml:id="para-dys_snr_lr"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm significance="preferred" zone="def_primary_resource">
                            <primary>primary resource</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="def_primary_resource">
                            <primary>resource</primary>
                            <secondary>primary</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="def_primary_resource">
                            <primary>RFID</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="def_primary_resource">
                            <primary>computational</primary>
                            <secondary>agents</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info><phrase role="definition" xml:id="def_primary_resource">Treating as a
                        <glossterm xml:id="term_primary_resource">primary resource</glossterm>
                    anything that can be identified is an important generalization of the concept
                    because it enables web-based services, data feeds, objects with <hardware>RFID
                        tags</hardware>, <hardware>sensors</hardware> or other <glossterm
                        linkend="gloss_smart_things">smart devices,</glossterm> or
                        <hardware>computational agents</hardware> to be part of Organizing
                    Systems.</phrase></para>
            <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-ubt_snr_lr">Instead of emphasizing
                the differences between tangible and intangible resources, we consider it essential
                to determine whether the tangible resource has information
                    content<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>whether it needs to be treated as being
                    <quote>about</quote> or representing some other resource rather than being
                treated as a thing in itself. Whether a book is printed or digital, we focus on its
                information content, what it is about; its tangible properties become secondary. In
                contrast, the hangars in our closet and the measuring cups in our kitchen are not
                about anything more than their obvious utilitarian features, which makes their
                tangible properties most important. (Of course, there is no sharp boundary here; you
                can buy <quote>fashion hangers</quote> that make a style statement, and the old
                measuring cup could be a family memento because it belonged to Grandma).</para>
            <para audience="CORE" role="comparative" xml:id="para-rft_snr_lr"><phrase
                    role="definition" xml:id="def_description_resources">Many of the resources in
                    Organizing Systems are <glossterm xml:id="term_description_resources"
                        >description resources</glossterm> or <firstterm
                        linkend="gloss_surrogate_resource">surrogate resources</firstterm> that
                    describe the <glossterm linkend="gloss_primary_resource" xreflabel="primary"
                        >primary resources</glossterm>; library catalog entries or the list of
                    results in web search engines are familiar examples.</phrase> In museums,
                information about the production, discovery, or history of ownership of a resource
                can be more important than the resource; a few shards of pottery are of little value
                without these associated information resources. Similarly, business or scientific
                data often cannot be understood or analyzed without additional information about the
                manner in which they were collected. <phrase audience="CORE DS" revisionflag="added"
                    revision="4.0">Most web-based businesses exploit data about how users interact
                    with resources, such as the log files that record every web search you make,
                    every link you click, and every web page you visit. </phrase></para>
            <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-hst_snr_lr"><phrase role="statement"
                    >Resources that describe, or are associated with other resources are sometimes
                    called <firstterm linkend="gloss_metadata">metadata</firstterm>.</phrase>
                However, when we look more broadly at Organizing Systems, it is often difficult to
                distinguish between the resource being described and any description of it or
                associated with it. One challenge is that when descriptions are embedded in
                resources, as metadata often is<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>in the title page of a book,
                the masthead of a newspaper, or the source of web
                pages<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>deciding which resources are primary is often
                arbitrary. </para>
            <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-evj_f2c_55">A second challenge is
                that what serves as metadata for one person or process can function as a primary
                resource or data for another one. Rather than being an inherent distinction, the
                difference between primary and associated resources is often just a decision about
                which resource we are focusing on in some situation. An animal specimen in a natural
                history museum might be a <glossterm linkend="gloss_primary_resource">primary
                    resource</glossterm> for museum visitors and scientists interested in anatomy,
                but information about where the specimen was collected is the <glossterm
                    linkend="gloss_primary_resource">primary resource</glossterm> for scientists
                interested in ecology or migration.</para>
            
            

            
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-uvt_snr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-uvt_snr_lr">
                        <primary>resources</primary>
                        <secondary>human resources</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-uvt_snr_lr">
                        <primary>human resources</primary>
                        <secondary>intentional arrangement</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-uvt_snr_lr">
                        <primary>intentional communities</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info><phrase role="statement">Organizing Systems can refer to people as resources, and
                we often use that term to avoid specifying the gender or specific role of an
                employee or worker, as in the management concept of the <quote>human
                    resources</quote> department in a workplace.</phrase>
            <phrase revision="3.0" revisionflag="added">A business is defined by its intentional
                arrangement of human resources, and there is both variety and regularity in these
                arrangements (see the sidebar, <xref linkend="sidebar-BizStructures"/> in <xref
                    linkend="section-6.5" xrefstyle="short"/>). </phrase><footnote label="9"
                revision="3.0" revisionflag="added" xml:id="endnote-005a" audience="Philosophy">
                <para xml:id="para-i13_y1w_ps" audience="Philosophy" revision="3.0"
                    revisionflag="added"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-005a">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Philosophy</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-005a">
                                <primary>philosophy</primary>
                                <secondary>intentional communities</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-005a">
                                <primary>intentional communities</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><phrase revision="3.0" revisionflag="added">In addition, groups of people
                        have come together to form <quote>intentional communities</quote> for
                        thousands of years in monasteries, communes, artist colonies, cooperative
                        houses, and religious or ethnic enclaves so they can live with people who
                        share their values and beliefs.</phrase> A directory of intentional
                    communities organized by type and location is managed by the <link
                        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://www.ic.org/directory/">Fellowship of Intentional
                        Communities</link>.</para>
            </footnote></para>
            <para>Human resources in Organizing Systems can be understood much the same way as
            inanimate physical or digital resources: they are selected, organized, and managed, and
            can create value individually or through their interactions with others inside and
            outside of the system.<footnote xml:id="endnote-006" label="10" audience="Business">
                <para audience="Business" xml:id="para-gzt_snr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-006">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Business</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-006">
                                <primary>business</primary>
                                <secondary>intellectual capital</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>The shift from a manufacturing to an information and services economy in
                    the last few decades has resulted in greater emphasis on intellectual resources
                    represented in skills and knowledge rather than on the natural resources of
                    production materials and physical goods.</para>
                <para audience="Business" xml:id="para-fbb_4qj_wv">The intellectual resources of a
                    firm are embodied in a firm’s people, systems, management techniques, history of
                    strategy and design decisions, customer relationships, and intellectual property
                    like patents, copyrights, trademarks, and brands. Some of this knowledge is
                    explicit, tangible, and traceable in the form of documents, databases,
                    organization charts, and policy and procedure manuals. But much of it is tacit:
                    informal and not systematized in tangible form because it is held in the minds
                    and experiences of people; a synonym is <quote>know-how.</quote> A more modern
                    term is <citetitle linkend="Stewart1997" pubwork="book">Intellectual
                        Capital,</citetitle> a concept originated in a <date>1997</date> book with
                    that title <citation xml:id="cite_Stewart1997" linkend="Stewart1997">(Stewart
                        1997)</citation>.</para>
            </footnote> However, human beings are uniquely complicated resources, and any Organizing
            System that uses them must take into account their rights, motivations, and
            relationships. <phrase role="parenthetical">(See the sidebar, <xref
                    linkend="sidebar-PeopleAsResources"/>.)</phrase></para>
            
        </section>
    <!--              -->
    <?dbfo clear ?>
    <?need 1.5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-1.4" label="1.4">
            <title>The Concept of <quote>Collection</quote></title>
            <info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="section-1.4">
                        <primary>collection</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="section-1.4">
                        <primary>concept</primary>
                        <secondary>collection</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="section-1.4">
                        <primary>concept</primary>
                        <secondary>index</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="section-1.4">
                        <primary>resource description</primary>
                        <secondary>index</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm significance="preferred" zone="def_collection">
                        <primary>collection</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="def_collection">
                        <primary>resource</primary>
                        <secondary>collection</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="def_collection">
                        <primary>set</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="def_collection">
                        <primary>aggregation</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="def_collection">
                        <primary>dataset</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="def_collection">
                        <primary>corpus</primary>
                    </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ed5_snr_lr"><phrase role="definition"
                    xml:id="def_collection">A <glossterm xml:id="term_collection"
                        >collection</glossterm> is a group of resources that have been selected for
                    some purpose.</phrase> Similar terms are <emphasis role="italic">set</emphasis>
                (mathematics), <emphasis role="italic">aggregation</emphasis> (data modeling),
                    <emphasis role="italic">dataset</emphasis> (science and business), and <emphasis
                    role="italic">corpus</emphasis> (linguistics and literary analysis).</para>
            
            
            
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-yg5_snr_lr">We prefer <firstterm
                linkend="gloss_collection">collection</firstterm> because it has fewer specialized
            meanings. <emphasis>Collection</emphasis> is typically used to describe personal sets of
            physical resources (my stamp or record album collection) as well as digital ones (my
            collection of digital music). We distinguish law libraries from software libraries,
            knowledge management systems from data warehouses, and personal <hardware>stamp
                collections</hardware> from <hardware>coin collections</hardware> primarily because
            they contain different kinds of resources. Similarly, we distinguish <hardware>document
                collections</hardware> by resource type, contrasting narrative document types like
            novels and biographies with transactional ones like catalogs and invoices, with hybrid
            forms like textbooks and encyclopedias in between.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ksn_twy_rv">A collection can contain identifiers for
            resources along with or instead of the resources themselves, which enables a resource to
            be part of more than one collection, like songs in playlists.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-cm5_snr_lr"><info><itermset>
                <indexterm
                    significance="preferred" zone="def_index">
                    <primary>index</primary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="def_index">
                    <primary>resource</primary>
                    <secondary>description</secondary>
                    <tertiary>index</tertiary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="def_index">
                    <primary>library science</primary>
                    <secondary>index</secondary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="def_index">
                    <primary>language</primary>
                    <secondary>index</secondary>
                </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>A <firstterm xml:id="first_collection"
                    linkend="gloss_collection">collection</firstterm> itself is also a <glossterm
                    linkend="gloss_resource">resource</glossterm>. Like other resources, a
                collection can have description resources associated with it. 
                <phrase role="definition" xml:id="def_index">An <glossterm
                        xreflabel="index" xml:id="term_index">index</glossterm> is a <glossterm
                        linkend="gloss_description_resource">description resource</glossterm> that
                    contains information about the locations and frequencies of terms in a document
                        <glossterm linkend="gloss_collection">collection</glossterm> to enable it to
                    be searched efficiently.</phrase></para>
            <para audience="CORE" role="principle" xml:id="para-xq5_snr_lr">Because <glossterm
                linkend="gloss_collection">collections</glossterm> are an important and frequently
            used kind of <glossterm linkend="gloss_resource">resource</glossterm>, it is important
            to distinguish them as a separate concept. In particular, the concept of <glossterm
                linkend="gloss_collection">collection</glossterm> has deep roots in
                <hardware>libraries, museums and other institutions</hardware> that <phrase
                remap="action">select, assemble, arrange, and maintain resources</phrase>.
            Organizing Systems in these domains can often be described as collections of collections
            that are variously organized according to resource type, author, creator, or collector
            of the resources in the collection, or any number of other principles or properties.
                <phrase revision="3.0" revisionflag="added">In business contexts, the use of
                    <quote>collection</quote> to describe a set of resources is much less common,
                but businesses organize many types of resources, including their employees,
                suppliers, customers, products, and the tangible and intangible assets used to
                create the products and run the business. Indeed, a business itself can sometimes be
                abstractly described as a collection of resources, especially when the resources are
                software components or services.<phrase role="parenthetical" audience="Computing">
                    (See endnote<footnoteref linkend="endnote-040" audience="Computing"
                /></phrase>.)</phrase>
        </para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-btf_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-btf_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>zoo</primary>
                        <secondary>as organizing system</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>A type of resource and its conventional Organizing System are often the focal
            point of a discipline. Category labels such as library, museum, zoo, and data repository
            have core meanings and many associated experiences and practices. Specialized concepts
            and vocabularies often evolve to describe these. The richness that follows from this
            complex social and cultural construction makes it difficult to define category
            boundaries precisely. </para>
        <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-ajq_3kc_55" revision="4.0" revisionflag="changed"
            >Libraries can be defined as institutions that <quote>select, collect, organize,
                conserve, preserve, and provide access to information on behalf of a community of
                users.</quote> Many Organizing Systems are described as libraries, although they
            differ from traditional libraries in important respects. <phrase role="parenthetical"
                >(See the sidebar, <xref linkend="sidebar-WhatIsLibrary" xrefstyle="short"
                />)</phrase></para>
        <sidebar xml:id="sidebar-WhatIsLibrary">
            <title>What Is a Library?</title>
            <info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-WhatIsLibrary" condition="print" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>sidebar</primary>
                        <secondary>What Is a Library?</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-WhatIsLibrary" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>What Is a Library?</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-WhatIsLibrary">
                        <primary>library science</primary>
                        <secondary>what is</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="sidebar-WhatIsLibrary">
                        <primary>interactions</primary>
                        <secondary>circulation</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-lxf_tnr_lr">Most birds fly, but not all of them do.
                What characteristics are most important to us when we classify something as a bird?
                What characteristics are most important when we think of something as a
                library?</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-fbg_tnr_lr"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm significance="preferred" zone="def_circulation">
                            <primary>circulation</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="def_circulation">
                            <primary>interactions</primary>
                            <secondary>circulation</secondary>
                            <tertiary>defines a library</tertiary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info><phrase role="definition" xml:id="def_circulation">We might treat <glossterm
                        xml:id="term_circulation">circulation</glossterm>, borrowing and returning
                    the same item, as one of the interactions with resources that defines a
                    library.</phrase> In that case, an institution that lends items in its
                collection with the hope that the borrowers return something else that is better
                hardly seems like a library. But if the resources are the seeds of heirloom plants
                and the borrowers are expected to return seeds from the plants they grew from the
                borrowed seeds, perhaps <quote>seed library</quote> is an apt name for this novel
                Organizing System. Similarly, even though the resources in its collection are
                encyclopedia articles rather than living species, the Wikipedia open-source
                encyclopedia resembles the Seed Library by encouraging its users to
                    <quote>return</quote> articles that are improvements of the current ones.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-dfg_tnr_lr">The photo-sharing website
                    <orgname>Flickr</orgname> functions for most of its users as a personal photo
                archiving site. Flickr’s billions of user-uploaded photos and the choice of many
                users to share them publicly transform it into a searchable shared collection, and
                many people also think of Flickr as a photo library. But Flickr lacks the
                authoritative description and standard classification that typify a library.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-cjg_tnr_lr"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="para-cjg_tnr_lr" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                            <primary>Brin, Sergei</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="para-cjg_tnr_lr" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                            <primary>business applications</primary>
                            <secondary>digitization</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="para-cjg_tnr_lr">
                            <primary>categorization</primary>
                            <secondary>challenge</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info>A similar categorization challenge arises with the <application>Google
                    Books</application> digitization project. <footnote xml:id="endnote-016"
                    label="11" audience="Law">
                    <para audience="Law" xml:id="para-bng_tnr_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-016">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Law</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-016">
                                    <primary>law</primary>
                                    <secondary>orphan works</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-016">
                                    <primary>orphan works</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-016">
                                    <primary>Google</primary>
                                    <secondary>book digitization project</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-016">
                                    <primary>Samuelson, Pamela</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-016">
                                    <primary>costs</primary>
                                    <secondary>legal</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-016">
                                    <primary>copyright</primary>
                                    <secondary>orphan works</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-016">
                                    <primary>digital library</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-016" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                                    <primary>Hathi Trust</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info>In <date>2004</date>, <orgname>Google</orgname> began digitizing
                        millions of books from several major research libraries with the goal of
                        making them available through its search engine <citation
                            xml:id="cite_Brin2009" linkend="Brin2009">(Brin 2009)</citation>. But
                        many millions of these books are still in copyright, and in
                            <date>2005</date> Google was sued for copyright infringement by several
                        publishers and an author’s organization. In <date>2011</date> a <orgname>US
                            District Court</orgname> judge rejected the proposed settlement the
                        parties had negotiated in <date>2008</date> because many others objected to
                        it, including the <orgname>US Justice Department</orgname>, several foreign
                        governments, and numerous individuals <citation xml:id="cite_Samuelson2011"
                            linkend="Samuelson2011">(Samuelson 2011)</citation>.</para>
                    <para audience="Law" xml:id="para-yqg_tnr_lr">The major reason for the rejection
                        was that the settlement was a <quote>bridge too far</quote> that went beyond
                        the claims made against Google to address issues that were not in
                        litigation. In particular, the judge objected to the treatment of the
                        so-called <quote>orphan works</quote> that were still under copyright but
                        out of print because money they generated went to the parties in the
                        settlement and not to the rights holders who could not be located (why the
                        books are <quote>orphans</quote>) or to defray the costs of subscriptions to
                        the digital book collection. The judge also was concerned that the
                        settlement did not adequately address the concerns of academic
                            authors<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>who wrote most of the books scanned from
                        research libraries<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>who might prefer to make their
                        books freely available rather than seek to maximize profits from them. Other
                        concerns were that the settlement would have entrenched Google’s monopoly in
                        the search market and that there were inadequate controls for protecting the
                        privacy of readers.</para>
                    <para audience="Law" xml:id="para-avg_tnr_lr">Google’s plan would have
                        dramatically increased access to out of print books, and the rejection of
                        the proposed settlement has heightened calls for an open public digital
                        library <citation xml:id="cite_Darnton2011" linkend="Darnton2011">(Darnton
                            2011)</citation>. A good start toward such a library was the digital
                        copies that the research libraries received in return for giving Google
                        books to scan, which were collected and organized by the Hathi Trust <phrase
                            audience="LIS" revision="4.0" revisionflag="changed">(See the sidebar,
                                <xref linkend="sidebar-HathiTrust"/>).</phrase> In
                        <date>2010</date>, the <orgname>Alfred P. Sloan Foundation</orgname>
                        provided funding to launch the <firstterm xml:id="first_DPLA"><citerefentry
                                xml:id="ref_DPLA"><refentrytitle><orgname>Digital Public Library of
                                        America</orgname></refentrytitle><manvolnum>DPLA</manvolnum></citerefentry></firstterm>:
                            <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="http://dp.la/"><uri>http://dp.la/</uri></link>. This
                        non-proprietary goal might induce the <orgname>US Congress</orgname> and
                        other governments to pass legislation that fixes the copyright problems for
                        orphan works.</para>
                </footnote></para>
        </sidebar>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-czg_tnr_lr">We can always create new categories by
            stretching the conventional definitions of <quote>library</quote> or other familiar
            Organizing Systems and adding modifiers, as when <application>Flickr</application> is
            described as a web-based photo-sharing library. But whenever we define an Organizing
            System with respect to a familiar category, the typical or mainstream instances and
            characteristics of that category that are deeply embedded in language and culture are
            reinforced, and those that are atypical are marginalized. In the
                <application>Flickr</application> case, this means we suggest features that are not
            there (like authoritative classification) or omit the features that are distinctive
            (like tagging by users).</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-cdh_tnr_lr">More generally, a categorical view of
            Organizing Systems makes it matter greatly which category is used to anchor definitions
            or comparisons. The <application>Google Books</application> project makes out-of-print
            and scholarly works vastly more accessible, but <phrase revision="4.0"
                revisionflag="added">when Google co-founder Sergei Brin described it as <quote>a
                    library to last forever</quote> it upset</phrase> many people with a more
            traditional sense of what the library category implies. We can readily identify design
            choices in <application>Google Books</application> that are more characteristic of the
            Organizing Systems in business domains, and the project might have been perceived more
            favorably had it been described as an online bookstore that offered many beneficial
            services for free.</para>
        </section>
    <!--              -->
    <?dbfo clear ?>
    <?need 6cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-1.5" label="1.5">
            <title>The Concept of <quote>Intentional Arrangement</quote></title>
            <info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="section-1.7">
                        <primary>intentional arrangement</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="section-1.7">
                        <primary>concept</primary>
                        <secondary>intentional arrangement</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="section-1.7">
                        <primary>self-organizing systems</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="section-1.7" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>Smith, Adam</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="section-1.7" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>Darwin, Charles</primary>
                    </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-nv5_snr_lr"><info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm significance="preferred" zone="def_intentional_arrangement">
                            <primary>intentional arrangement</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="para-nv5_snr_lr">
                            <primary>computational</primary>
                            <secondary>agents</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info><phrase role="definition" xml:id="def_intentional_arrangement"><glossterm
                        xml:id="term_intentional_arrangement">Intentional arrangement</glossterm>
                    emphasizes explicit or implicit acts of organization by people, or by
                    computational processes acting as proxies for, or as implementations of, human
                    intentionality. </phrase> Intentional arrangement is easiest to see in
                Organizing Systems created by individual people who can make all the necessary
                decisions about organizing their own resources. It is also easy to see in Organizing
                Systems created by institutions like libraries, museums, businesses, and governments
                where the responsibility and authority to organize is centralized and explicit in
                policies, laws, or regulations. </para>
                    
                      <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-nv5_snr_jj" revisionflag="added"
                revision="3.0">However, top-down intentionality is not always necessary to create an
                Organizing system. Organization can emerge over time via collective behavior in
                situations without central control when decisions made by individuals, each acting
                intentionally,  <phrase audience="CORE DS" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added"
                    >create traces, records, or other information that accumulates over
                    time</phrase>. Organizing systems that use bottom-up rather than top-down
                mechanisms are sometimes called self-organizing, because they emerge from the
                aggregated interactions of actors with resources or with each other. <indexterm
                    significance="preferred" zone="def_self-organizing_systems">
                    <primary>self-organizing systems</primary>
                </indexterm><indexterm zone="def_self-organizing_systems">
                    <primary>data structures</primary>
                    <secondary>self-organizing system</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <phrase role="definition" xml:id="def_self-organizing_systems"><glossterm
                        xml:id="term_self-organizing_systems">Self-organizing systems</glossterm>
                    can change their internal structure or their function in response to feedback or
                    changed circumstances.</phrase></para>
                    
                    
                       <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-nv5_snr_lb" revisionflag="added"
            revision="3.0">This definition is broad enough to include business and biological
            ecosystems, traffic patterns, and open-source software projects. Another good example of
            emergent organization involves path systems, where people (as well as ants and other
            animals) <phrase audience="CORE DS" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added">can
                follow</phrase> and thereby reinforce the paths taken by their predecessors. When
            highly orderly and optimal arrangements emerge from local interactions among ants, bees,
            birds, fish, and other animal species, it is often called <quote>swarm
                intelligence.</quote> When this happens with human ratings for news stories, YouTube
            videos, restaurants, and other types of digital and physical resources we call it
                <quote>crowdsourcing.</quote> What the animal and human situations have in common is
            that information is being communicated between individuals. Sometimes this communication
            is direct, as when Amazon shows you the average rating for a book or what books have
            been bought by people like you. At other times the communication is indirect, achieved
            when the agents modify their environment (as they do when they create paths) and others
            can respond to these modifications. Adam Smith's <quote>invisible hand</quote> is
            another example where individuals collectively generate an outcome they did not directly
            intend but that arose from their separate self-interested actions <phrase
                audience="CORE DS" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added">as they respond to price
                signals</phrase> in the marketplace. <phrase revision="3.0" revisionflag="added"
                >Likewise, even though there is no top-down organization, the web as a whole, with
                its more than a trillion unique pages, is a self-organizing system that at its core
                follows clear organizing principles.</phrase><footnote label="12"
                xml:id="endnote-006a" audience="Computing" revision="3.0" revisionflag="added">
                <para audience="Computing" role="contrast" xml:id="para-kmv_snr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-006a">
                                <primary>natural selection</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>Self-organizing is also used to describe phenomena like climate, neural
                    networks, and phase transitions and equilibrium states in physics and chemistry.
                    But when systems involve collections of <emphasis role="italic"
                        >inanimate</emphasis> resources that are very large and open, with complex
                    interactions among the resources, it seems less sensible to attribute
                    intentional arrangement to the outcomes. The resource arrangements that emerge
                    cannot always be interpreted as the result of intentional or deterministic
                    principles and instead are more often described in probabilistic or statistical
                    terms. And even though it involves animate resources,
                            <personname><firstname>Charles</firstname>
                        <surname>Darwin</surname></personname>’s <quote>natural selection</quote> in
                    evolutionary biology is a self-organizing mechanism where intentionality is hard
                    to pinpoint or absent entirely.</para>
                <para audience="Computing" xml:id="para-y1z_z1w_ps" revision="3.0"
                    revisionflag="added"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-006a">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Computing</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-006a">
                                <primary>computing</primary>
                                <secondary>complex modelling</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>The rules governing these local interactions can be simple and yet
                    produce highly complex structures. For example, in flocks of birds or schools of
                    fish the rules are: (1) follow things like you, (2) do not bump into each other,
                    but stay close, and (3) move in the same direction as the rest of the group.
                    With just these three rules computer models can create complex three-dimensional
                    arrangements that can make abrupt changes in shape and density while moving
                    rapidly, just as live things do. <citation xml:id="cite_Friederici2009"
                        linkend="Friederici2009">(Friederici 2009)</citation></para>
                    <para xml:id="para-bcd_krj_wv" audience="Computing"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-006a">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Web</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-006a">
                                <primary>Web</primary>
                                <secondary>folksonomy</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-006a">
                                <primary>business applications</primary>
                                <secondary>social bookmarking</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-006a">
                                <primary>folksonomy</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>The term <quote>Crowdsourcing</quote> was invented by
                            <personname><firstname>Jeff</firstname>
                        <surname>Howe</surname></personname> in a <date>June 2006</date> article in
                    Wired magazine, and the concept was developed further in a book published two
                    years later <citation linkend="Howe2006" xml:id="cite_Howe2006">(Howe
                        2006</citation>, <citation linkend="Howe2008" xml:id="cite_Howe2008"
                        >2008)</citation>. <quote>Folksonomy</quote> was coined by
                            <personname><firstname>Thomas</firstname>
                        <surname>Van der Wal</surname></personname> at about the same time in
                        <date>2004</date>; see <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="http://vanderwal.net/folksonomy.html"
                            ><uri>http://vanderwal.net/folksonomy.html</uri></link> and <citation
                        linkend="Trant2009" xml:id="cite_Trant2009">(Trant 2009)</citation>.</para>
                
            
                    <para xml:id="para-qkn_fbw_ps" revision="3.0" revisionflag="added" audience="Computing"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-006a">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>CogSci</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-006a">
                                <primary>cognitive science</primary>
                                <secondary>collective behavior</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><citation xml:id="cite_Goldstone2009" linkend="Goldstone2009">(Goldstone
                        and Gureckis 2009)</citation> present a cognitive science perspective on
                    collective behavior, analyze important themes and controversies, and suggest
                    areas for future research. <citation xml:id="cite_Moussaid2009"
                        linkend="Moussaid2009">(Moussaid et al. 2009)</citation> analyze
                    self-organizing phenomena in animal swarms and human crowds in terms of
                    information exchange among individuals.</para>
            
                    <para audience="Computing" revision="3.0" revisionflag="added"
                    xml:id="para-knj_xqj_wv"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-006a">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Computing</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-006a">
                                <primary>computing</primary>
                                <secondary>non-deterministic algorithms</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>Self-organizing behaviors in ants, bees, bats, cuckoos, fireflies and
                    other animals have been analyzed to identify heuristics that can be applied to
                    difficult optimization problems in network design, cryptography, and other
                    domains where deterministic algorithms are infeasible. <citation
                        xml:id="cite_Yang2010" linkend="Yang2010">(Yang 2010)</citation></para>
            
              <para  audience="Computing" revision="3.0" revisionflag="added"
                    xml:id="para-rxw_qyx_ps"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-006a">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Business</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-006a">
                                <primary>business</primary>
                                <secondary>Smith</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><citation linkend="Smith1776" xml:id="cite_Smith1776">(Smith
                        1776)</citation></para>
            </footnote><footnote xml:id="endnote-007" label="13" audience="Web">
                <para audience="Web" xml:id="para-mrv_snr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-007">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Web</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-007">
                                <primary>Web</primary>
                                <secondary>Banzhaf</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><citation xml:id="cite_Banzhaf2009" linkend="Banzhaf2009">(Banzhaf
                        2009)</citation>.</para>
            </footnote><footnote label="14" audience="IA" xml:id="endnote-007a">
                <para audience="IA" xml:id="para-nvv_snr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-007a">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>IA</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-007a">
                                <primary>information architecture</primary>
                                <secondary>web pages</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>The concept of a web page is imprecise because many web pages, especially
                    home pages designed as navigation gateways to an organized collection of pages,
                    are constructed from heterogeneous blocks of content that could have been
                    organized as separate pages.</para>
            </footnote></para>
            <sidebar xml:id="chapter-1-sidebar-3" audience="CORE Web">
                <title>The Web as an Organizing System</title>
                <info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-3" condition="print" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                            <primary>sidebar</primary>
                            <secondary>Web as an Organizing System</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-3" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                            <primary>Web as an Organizing System</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-3">
                            <primary>CERN</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-3">
                            <primary>Berners-Lee, Tim</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
                </info>
                <para xml:id="para-qzv_snr_lr"><phrase role="statement principle">Today’s web barely
                        resembles the system for distributing scientific and technical reports it
                        was designed to be when physicist and computer scientist
                                <personname><firstname>Tim</firstname>
                            <surname>Berners-Lee</surname></personname> devised it in
                            <date>1990</date> at the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>European
                                Organization for Nuclear
                                Research</refentrytitle><manvolnum>CERN</manvolnum></citerefentry>
                        lab near Geneva. However, as an <glossterm linkend="gloss_organizing_system"
                            >Organizing System</glossterm> the web still follows the principles that
                        Berners-Lee defined at its creation. These include standard data formats and
                        interaction protocols; no need for centralized control of page creation or
                        linking; remote access over the network from anywhere; and the ability to
                        run on a large variety of computers and operating systems. This architecture
                        makes the web open and extensible, but gives it no built-in mechanisms for
                        authority or trust.</phrase><footnote xml:id="endnote-008" label="15"
                        audience="Web">
                        <para audience="Web" xml:id="para-xdw_snr_lr"><info>
                                <itermset>
                                    <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-008">
                                        <primary>endnote</primary>
                                        <secondary>Web</secondary>
                                    </indexterm>
                                    <indexterm zone="endnote-008">
                                        <primary>business applications</primary>
                                        <secondary>walled gardens</secondary>
                                    </indexterm>
                                    <indexterm zone="endnote-008">
                                        <primary>W3C</primary>
                                    </indexterm>
                                    <indexterm zone="endnote-008">
                                        <primary>Web</primary>
                                        <secondary>plain web</secondary>
                                    </indexterm>
                                </itermset>
                            </info>The <quote>plain web</quote>
                            <citation xml:id="cite_Wilde2008a" linkend="Wilde2008a">(Wilde
                                2008a)</citation>, whose evolution is managed by the <firstterm
                                xml:id="first_W3C"><citerefentry><refentrytitle><orgname>World Wide
                                            Web
                                        Consortium</orgname></refentrytitle><manvolnum>W3C</manvolnum></citerefentry></firstterm>,
                            is rigorously standardized, but unfortunately the larger ecosystem of
                            technologies and formats in which the web exists is becoming less so.
                            Web-based Organizing Systems often contain proprietary media formats and
                            players (like <application>Flash</application>) or are implemented as
                            closed environments that are intentionally isolated from the rest of the
                            web (like <application>Facebook</application> or
                                <orgname>Apple</orgname>’s <application>iTunes</application> and
                            other smart phone <quote>app stores</quote>).</para>
                    </footnote></para>
                <para audience="CORE" role="principle" xml:id="para-akw_snr_lr"><phrase
                        role="statement principle">Because the web works without any central
                        authority or authorship control, any person or organization can add to it.
                        As a result, even though the web as a whole does not exhibit the centralized
                        intentional arrangement of resources that characterizes many Organizing
                        Systems, we can view it as consisting of millions of Organizing Systems that
                        each embody a separate intentional arrangement of web pages. In addition, we
                        most often interact with the web indirectly by using a search engine, which
                        meets the definition of <glossterm linkend="gloss_organizing_system"
                            >Organizing System</glossterm> because its indexing and retrieval
                        algorithms are principled.</phrase></para>
                
                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-a4w_snr_lr">A great many Organizing Systems are
                    implemented as collections of web pages. Some of these collections are created
                    on the web as new pages, some are created by transforming existing collections
                    of resources, and some combine new and existing resources.</para>
            </sidebar>
        <para xml:id="para-kd3_vqz_rv">The requirement for intentional arrangement excludes
            naturally occurring patterns <phrase revision="3.0" revisionflag="changed">created by
                physical or geological processes</phrase> from being thought of as Organizing
            Systems. <phrase role="principle statement">There is information in the piles of debris
                left after a tornado or tsunami and the strata of the Grand Canyon. But they are not
                Organizing Systems because the patterns of arrangement were created by deterministic
                natural forces rather than by agents following one or more organizing
                principles.</phrase>
            <phrase audience="CORE DS" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added">On the other hand,
                collections of geological data like the measurements of chemical composition from
                different strata and locations in the Grand Canyon <emphasis role="bold"
                    >are</emphasis> Organizing Systems. Decisions about what to measure, how to
                combine and analyze the measurements, and any theories that are tested or created,
                reflect intentional arrangement of the data by the geologist.</phrase></para>
        <para audience="CORE" role="comparative" revisionflag="added" xml:id="para-vz5_snr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-vz5_snr_lr">
                        <primary>location</primary>
                        <secondary>astronomical constellations</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>Other patterns of resource arrangements are illusions or perceptions that require
            a particular vantage point. The best examples are patterns of stars as they appear to an
            observer on Earth. The three precisely aligned stars, often described as <quote>Orion’s
                belt,</quote> are hundreds of light years from Earth, and also from each other. The
            perceived arrangement of the stars is undeniable, but the stars are not aligned in the
            universe. Astronomical constellations like Orion are <glossterm
                linkend="gloss_intentional_arrangement">intentional arrangements</glossterm> imposed
            on our perceived locations of the stars, and these perceived arrangements and the
            explanations for them that constellations provide, form an Organizing System that is
            deeply embedded in human culture and in the practice of celestial navigation over the
            seas.</para>
            
            <sidebar xml:id="sidebar-SelfOrganizing">
                <title>Not an Intentional Arrangement</title>
                <info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-SelfOrganizing" condition="print" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                            <primary>sidebar</primary>
                            <secondary>Not an Intentional Arrangement</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-SelfOrganizing" condition="print" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                            <primary>Not an Intentional Arrangement</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                        <indexterm zone="sidebar-SelfOrganizing">
                            <primary>intentional arrangement</primary>
                        </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
                
                <informalfigure xml:id="PICTURE-S1.2.3-SelfOrganizing" xreflabel="Self Organizing">
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="Pictures/1.2.3SelfOrganizing-CC.jpg" format="JPG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <textobject>
                            <phrase role="ALT descriptive">An image of the Grand Canyon. The
                                formations of rock reveal colored patterns at different
                                layers.</phrase>
                        </textobject>
                        <caption>
                            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-b2v_snr_lr">The composition and
                                arrangement of the rock layers (<quote>strata</quote>) in the Grand
                                Canyon in the Southwest United States have been studied extensively
                                by geologists. The composition of rock suggests the environment in
                                which it was formed, and the absolute and relative arrangement of
                                the rock layers reveals the timing of important geological
                                events.</para>
                            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-e3v_snr_lr"><phrase role="credit"
                                        >(<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                        xlink:href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/rosengrant/2966470172/"
                                        >Photo by B. Rosen.</link> Creative Commons CC BY-ND 2.0
                                    license.)</phrase></para>
                        </caption>
                    </mediaobject>
                </informalfigure>
            </sidebar>
            
            
            <para audience="CORE" role="interrogative" xml:id="para-gsw_snr_lr">Taken together, the
            intentional arrangements of resources in an Organizing System are the result of
            decisions about what is organized, why it is organized, how much it is organized, when
            it is organized, and how or by whom it is organized<phrase role="parenthetical"> (each
                of these will be discussed in greater detail in <xref linkend="chapter-2n"
                    xrefstyle="short"/>)</phrase>. An Organizing System is defined by the composite
            impact of the choices made on these design dimensions. Because these questions are
            interrelated their answers come together in an integrated way to define an Organizing
            System.</para>
        </section>
    <!--              -->
    <?dbfo clear ?>
    <?need 6cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-1.6" label="1.6">
                <title>The Concept of <quote>Organizing Principle</quote></title>
                <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-1.6">
                    <primary>organizing</primary>
                    <secondary>principle</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm zone="section-1.6">
                    <primary>concept</primary>
                    <secondary>organizing principle</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm zone="section-1.6">
                    <primary>architectural thinking</primary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm zone="section-1.6">
                    <primary>sensemaking</primary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-aww_snr_lr"><phrase role="statement principle"
                >The arrangements of resources in an Organizing System follow or embody one or more
                organizing principles that enable the Organizing System to achieve its
                purposes.</phrase>
            <phrase role="definition" xml:id="def_organizing_principles"><glossterm
                    xml:id="term_organizing_principles">Organizing principles</glossterm> are
                directives for the design or arrangement of a <glossterm linkend="gloss_collection"
                    >collection</glossterm> of resources that are ideally expressed in a way that
                does not assume any particular implementation or realization.</phrase>
            <phrase revision="3.0" revisionflag="added">We call this design philosophy
                    <quote>Architectural Thinking</quote>
                <phrase role="parenthetical">(<xref linkend="section-11.5.2" xrefstyle="short"
                    />.)</phrase></phrase>
        </para>
                <sidebar xml:id="sidebar-OrganizingSpicesByCuisine">
                    <title>Organizing Spices By Cuisine</title>
                    <info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="sidebar-OrganizingSpicesByCuisine" condition="print" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                                <primary>sidebar</primary>
                                <secondary>Organizing Spices By Cuisine</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="sidebar-OrganizingSpicesByCuisine" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                                <primary>Organizing Spices By Cuisine</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="sidebar-OrganizingSpicesByCuisine">
                                <primary>organizing</primary>
                                <secondary>spices</secondary>
                            </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
                    
                    <informalfigure xml:id="PICTURE-S1.2.3.1-OrganizingSpicesByCuisine"
                        xreflabel="Organizing Spices By Cuisine">
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="Pictures/1.2.3.1-OrganizingSpicesByCuisine-OK.JPG"
                                    format="JPG"/>
                            </imageobject>
                            <textobject>
                                <phrase role="ALT descriptive">A picture of three round containers, each
                                    of which contains seven round containers filled with
                                    spices.</phrase>
                            </textobject>
                            <caption>
                                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-dzw_snr_lr">An alternative to
                                    organizing spices alphabetically is to organize them according
                                    to cuisines or flavor profiles, which can be defined in terms of
                                    ingredients and spices that tend to be used together. Patricia
                                    Glushko organizes her spices into three groups: Indian (includes
                                    cayenne pepper, coriander, cumin, turmeric), Mediterranean /
                                    Middle Eastern (includes basil, dill, oregano, paprika, thyme),
                                    and seeds. Each group of spices is in a separate large
                                    container, which makes it convenient when cooking.</para>
                                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-fcx_snr_lr"><phrase role="credit"
                                        >(Photo by R. Glushko.)</phrase></para>
                            </caption>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </informalfigure>
                </sidebar>
                <para audience="CORE" role="principle" xml:id="para-gfx_snr_lr"><phrase
                role="statement principle">When we organize a <hardware>bookshelf</hardware>,
                    <hardware>home office</hardware>, <hardware>kitchen</hardware>, or the MP3 files
                on our <hardware>music player</hardware>, the resources themselves might be new and
                modern but many of the principles that govern their organization are those that have
                influenced the design of Organizing Systems for thousands of years.</phrase> For
            example, we organize many collections of resources using the properties that are easiest
            to perceive, or whose values vary the most among the items in the collection, because
            these principles make it easy to locate a particular resource. We also group together
            resources that we often use together, we make resources that we use often more
            accessible than those we use infrequently, and we put rare or unique resources where we
            can protect them. <phrase role="statement principle">Very general and abstract
                organizing principles are sometimes called design heuristics (e.g., <quote>make
                    things easier to find</quote>).</phrase>
            <phrase role="statement principle">More specific and commonly used organizing principles
                include <indexterm zone="def_alphabetical" significance="preferred">
                    <primary>alphabetical ordering</primary>
                </indexterm><glossterm xml:id="term_alphabetical">alphabetical ordering</glossterm>
                    (<phrase role="definition" xml:id="def_alphabetical">arranging resources
                    according to their names</phrase>) and <indexterm zone="def_chronological"
                    significance="preferred">
                    <primary>chronological ordering</primary>
                </indexterm><glossterm xml:id="term_chronological">chronological
                    ordering</glossterm> (<phrase role="definition" xml:id="def_chronological"
                    >arranging resources according to the date of their creation or other important
                    event in the lifetime of the resource</phrase>).</phrase>
            <phrase role="statement principle">Some organizing principles sort resources into
                pre-defined categories and other organizing principles rely on novel combinations of
                resource properties to create new categories.</phrase></para>
                <para xml:id="para-rw1_tgv_gv" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added"
            audience="CORE DS"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-rw1_tgv_gv">
                        <primary>sensemaking</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>Because this book was motivated by the goal of broadening the study of
            information organization beyond its roots in library and information science, it
            emphasizes organizing principles with a specific functional purpose like identifying,
            selecting, retrieving, or preserving resources. However, for thousands of years people
            have systematically collected things, information about those things, and observations
            of all kinds, organizing them in an effort to understand how their world works; the
            Babylonians created inventories and star charts; ancient Egyptians tracked the annual
            Nile floods; and, Mesoamericans created astronomical calendars. The term <glossterm
                linkend="gloss_sensemaking">sensemaking</glossterm> is often used to describe this
            generic and less specific purpose of organizing to derive meaning from experience by
            fitting new events or observations into what they already know.<footnote
                audience="CogSci" xml:id="endnote-008a" label="16" revision="4.0"
                revisionflag="added">
                <para audience="CogSci" xml:id="para-sfj_jrs_sv" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added"><citation
                        linkend="Weick2005">(Weick et al , 2005 p. 410).</citation></para>
            </footnote></para>
                <para audience="CORE" role="comparative principle" xml:id="para-ejx_snr_lr"><phrase
                        role="statement principle">Expressing organizing principles in a way that
                        separates design and implementation aligns well with the three-tier
                        architecture familiar to software architects and designers: user interface
                        (implementation of interactions), business logic (intentional arrangement),
                        and data (resources).</phrase>
                    <phrase role="parenthetical">(See the sidebar, <xref
                            linkend="chapter-1-sidebar-4"/>.)</phrase></para>
                <para audience="CORE" role="contrast principle" xml:id="para-ymx_snr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-ymx_snr_lr">
                        <primary>digital library</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info><phrase role="statement principle">The logical separation between organizing
                principles and their implementation is easy to see with digital resources.</phrase>
            In a digital library it does not matter to a user if the resources are stored locally or
            retrieved over a network. The essence of a library Organizing System emerges from the
            resources that it organizes and the interactions with the resources that it enables.
            Users typically care a lot about the interactions they can perform, like the kinds of
            searching and sorting allowed by the online library catalog. How the resources and
            interactions are implemented are typically of little concern.</para>
                <para audience="CORE" role="comparative principle" xml:id="para-yqx_snr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="para-yqx_snr_lr">
                                <primary>location</primary>
                                <secondary>kitchen</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="para-yqx_snr_lr">
                                <primary>location</primary>
                                <secondary>storage tier</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><phrase role="statement principle">The separation of organizing
                        principles and their implementation is harder to recognize in an Organizing
                        System that only contains <hardware>physical resources</hardware>, such as
                        your <hardware>kitchen</hardware> or <hardware>clothes closet</hardware>,
                        where you appear to have unmediated interactions with resources rather than
                        accessing them through some kind of user interface or <quote>presentation
                            tier</quote> that supports the principles specified in the <quote>middle
                            tier</quote> and realized in the <quote>storage tier.</quote></phrase>
                    As a result, people can easily get distracted by presentation-tier concerns. Too
                    often we waste time color-coding file folders and putting labels on storage
                    containers, when it would have better to think more carefully about the logical
                    organization of the folder and container contents. It does not help to use
                    colors and labels to make the logical organization more salient if that is not
                    well designed first. </para>
                            
                            
                            
                     <para audience="CORE" revisionflag="added" revision="3.0">        
                   One place where you can easily appreciate these different tiers for physical resources is in the organization of
                        <hardware>spices in a kitchen</hardware>. Different kitchens might all
                    embody an <glossterm linkend="gloss_alphabetical">alphabetic order</glossterm>
                    organizing principle for arranging a collection of spices, but the exact
                    locations and arrangement of the spices in any particular kitchen depends on the
                    configuration of shelves and drawers, whether a spice rack or rotating tray is
                    used, and other storage-tier considerations. Similarly, spices could be
                    logically organized by cuisine, with Indian spices separated from Mexican
                    spices, but this organizing principle does not imply anything about where they
                    can be found in the kitchen.</para>
                <sidebar xml:id="chapter-1-sidebar-4" audience="CORE Computing IA LIS"
                    role="principle">
                    <title>The Three Tiers of Organizing Systems</title>
                    <info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-4" condition="print" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                                <primary>sidebar</primary>
                                <secondary>Three Tiers of Organizing Systems</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-4" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                                <primary>Three Tiers of Organizing Systems</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-4">
                                <primary>organizing system</primary>
                                <secondary>three tiered</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-4">
                                <primary>data storage</primary>
                                <secondary>architectural tier</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-4">
                                <primary>business logic</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-4">
                                <primary>presentation</primary>
                                <secondary>architectural tier</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-4">
                                <primary>architectural perspective</primary>
                                <secondary>three tier model</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="chapter-1-sidebar-4">
                                <primary>architectural thinking</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-x5x_snr_lr"><phrase
                            role="statement principle">Software architects and designers agree that
                            it is desirable to build applications that separate the storage of data,
                            the business logic or functions that use the data, and the user
                            interface or presentation components through which users or other
                            applications interact with the data.</phrase> This modular architecture
                        allows each of the three tiers to be upgraded or reimplemented independently
                        to satisfy changed requirements or to take advantage of new technologies. An
                        analogous distinction is that between an algorithm as a logical description
                        of a method for solving a computational problem and its implementation in a
                        particular programming language like
                                <citerefentry><refentrytitle>Java</refentrytitle></citerefentry> or
                                <citerefentry><refentrytitle>Python</refentrytitle></citerefentry>.</para>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-uyx_snr_lr">These architectural distinctions
                        are equally important to librarians and information scientists. <phrase
                            role="statement principle">Our new way of looking at Organizing Systems
                            emphasizes the importance of identifying the desired interactions with
                            resources, determining which organizing principles can enable the
                            interactions, and then deciding how to store and manage the resources
                            according to those principles.</phrase> Applying architectural thinking
                        to Organizing Systems makes it easier to compare and contrast existing ones
                        and design new ones. Separating the organizing principles in the
                            <quote>middle tier</quote> from their implications in the
                            <quote>data</quote> and <quote>presentation</quote> tiers often makes it
                        possible to implement the same logical Organizing System in different
                        environments that support the same or equivalent interactions with the
                        resources. For example, a new requirement to support searching through a
                        library catalog on a smart phone would only affect the presentation
                        tier.</para>
                </sidebar>
                <para audience="CORE" role="descriptive" xml:id="para-qcy_snr_lr"><xref
                        linkend="chapter-1-figure-1.3.2"/> illustrates the separation of the
                    presentation, logic, and storage tiers for four different types of library
                    Organizing Systems and for Google Books. No two of them are the same in every
                    tier. Note how a library that uses inventory robots to manage the storage of
                    books does not reveal this in its higher tiers. <phrase role="parenthetical"
                        revision="3.0" revisionflag="added">(See the sidebar, <xref
                            linkend="sidebar-LibraryRobot"/>.) </phrase></para>
                <figure xml:id="chapter-1-figure-1.3.2" floatstyle="normal" label="1.2">
                    <title>Presentation, Logic and Storage Tiers.</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="figs/Figure-1.2.jpg"
                                format="JPG" scalefit="1"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <textobject>
                            <phrase role="ALT descriptive">A conceptual depiction of an Organizing
                                System as three layers. The top layer is the Presentation layer;
                                icons represent card catalogs, online catalogs and search
                                interfaces. The middle row is the Logic layer; icons represent
                                library classifications and search engines. The lowest layer depicts
                                a Storage layer; icons represent books on shelves, digital books and
                                physical retrieval systems. </phrase>
                        </textobject>
                        <caption>
                            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-pgy_snr_lr"><phrase role="caption">It
                                    is highly desirable when the design and implementation of an
                                    Organizing System separates the storage of the resources from
                                    the logic of their arrangement and the methods for interacting
                                    with them. This three-tier architect is familiar to designers of
                                    computerized Organizing Systems but it is also useful to think
                                    about Organizing Systems in this way even when it involves
                                    physical resources.</phrase></para>
                        </caption>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
                
                
                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-mky_snr_lr">Because tangible things can only be
                    in one place at a time, many Organizing Systems, like those in the modern
                    library with online catalogs and physical collections, resolve this constraint
                    by creating digital proxies or surrogates to organize their tangible resources,
                    or create parallel digital resources (e.g., digitized books).<footnote 
                        xml:id="endnote-009" label="17" audience="Web">
                        <para audience="Web" xml:id="para-i4y_snr_lr"><info>
                                <itermset>
                                    <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-009">
                                        <primary>endnote</primary>
                                        <secondary>Web</secondary>
                                    </indexterm>
                                    <indexterm zone="endnote-009">
                                        <primary>Web</primary>
                                        <secondary>alternative resources</secondary>
                                    </indexterm>
                                </itermset>
                            </info>Instead of thinking of a digital book as a <quote>parallel
                                resource</quote> to a printed book, we could consider both of them
                            as alternate representations of the same abstract resource that are
                            linked together by an <quote>alternative</quote> relationship, just as
                            we can use the <abbrev>HTML</abbrev>
                            <literal>ALT</literal> tag to associate text with an image so its
                            content and function can be understood by text-only readers.</para>
                    </footnote> The implications for arranging, finding, using and reusing resources
                    in any Organizing System directly reflect the mix of these two embodiments of
                    information; in this way we can think of the modern library as a digital
                    Organizing System that primarily relies on digital resources to organize a
                    mixture of physical and digital ones.</para>
                
                
                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-esy_snr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-esy_snr_lr">
                        <primary>location</primary>
                        <secondary>collocation principle</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="def_collocation" significance="preferred">
                        <primary>collocation</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="def_collocation">
                        <primary>principle</primary>
                        <secondary>collocation</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info><phrase role="definition" xml:id="def_collocation">The Organizing System for a
                small collection can sometimes use only the minimal or default organizing principle
                of <glossterm xml:id="term_collocation"
                    >colocation</glossterm><symbol>&#8212;</symbol>putting all the resources in the
                same location: in the same container, <hardware>on the same shelf</hardware>, or in
                the same email in-box.</phrase> If you do not cook much and have only a small number
            of spices in your kitchen, you do not need to alphabetize them because it is easy to
            find the one you want.<footnote xml:id="endnote-010" label="18" audience="Computing">
                <para audience="Computing" xml:id="para-bwy_snr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-010">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Computing</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-010">
                                <primary>computing</primary>
                                <secondary>algorithm analysis</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>For collections of non-trivial size the choice of searching or sorting
                    algorithm in computer programs is a critical design decision because they differ
                    greatly in the time they take to complete and the storage space they require.
                    For example, if the collection is arranged in an unorganized or random manner
                    (as a <quote>pile</quote>) and every resource must be examined, the time to find
                    a particular item increases linearly with the collection size. If the collection
                    is maintained in an ordered manner, a binary search algorithm can locate any
                    item in a time proportional to the logarithm of the number of items. Analysis of
                    algorithms is a fundamental topic in computer science; a popular textbook is
                        <citetitle pubwork="book" linkend="Cormen2009">Introduction to
                        Algorithms</citetitle> by <citation xml:id="cite_Cormen2009"
                        linkend="Cormen2009">(Cormen et al. 2009)</citation>.</para>
            </footnote></para>
                
                
                <sidebar xml:id="sidebar-SeparationOfPrincipleFromImplement">
                    <title>Separation Of Organizing Principle From Implementation</title>
                    <info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="sidebar-SeparationOfPrincipleFromImplement" condition="print" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                                <primary>sidebar</primary>
                                <secondary>Separation Of Organizing Principle From Implementation</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="sidebar-SeparationOfPrincipleFromImplement" condition="print" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                                <primary>Separation Of Organizing Principle From Implementation</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="sidebar-SeparationOfPrincipleFromImplement">
                                <primary>principle</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="sidebar-SeparationOfPrincipleFromImplement">
                                <primary>implementation</primary>
                            </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>
                    
                    <informalfigure xml:id="PICTURE-S1.2.3.1-SeparationOfPrincipleFromImplement"
                        xreflabel="Separation Of Principle From Implement">
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata
                                    fileref="Pictures/1.2.3.1-SeparationOfPrincipleFromImplement.gif"
                                    format="GIF"/>
                            </imageobject>
                            <textobject>
                                <phrase role="ALT descriptive">Five spice racks, each with a unique
                                    arrangement of containers.</phrase>
                            </textobject>
                            <caption>
                                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-e1z_snr_lr"><phrase
                                        role="caption">Whether spices are organized alphabetically
                                        by their names, by cuisines, by season, by frequency of use,
                                        or any other principle, this decision is logically distinct
                                        from the physical arrangement of the spices. There are many
                                        types of spice racks, shelves, circular <quote>lazy
                                            susans,</quote> and other devices designed for arranging
                                        spices.</phrase></para>
                                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-a2z_snr_lr"><phrase role="credit"
                                        >(Photo collage created by R. Glushko from various web
                                        catalogs.)</phrase></para>
                            </caption>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </informalfigure>
                </sidebar>
                
                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-e3z_snr_lr"><phrase role="definition"
                        xml:id="def_frequency_of_use">Some organization emerges implicitly through a
                            <glossterm xml:id="term_frequency_of_use">frequency of use</glossterm>
                        principle. In your kitchen or clothes closet, the resources you use most
                        often migrate to the front because that is the easiest place to return them
                        after using them.</phrase> But as a collection grows in size, the time to
                    arrange, locate, and retrieve a particular resource becomes more important. The
                    collection must be explicitly organized to make these interactions efficient,
                    and the organization must be preserved after the interaction takes place; i.e.,
                    resources are put back in the place they were found. <phrase
                        role="statement principle">As a result, most Organizing Systems employ
                        organizing principles that make use of properties of the resources being
                        organized (e.g., name, color, shape, date of creation, semantic or
                        biological category), and multiple properties are often used
                        simultaneously.</phrase> For example, in your kitchen you might arrange your
                        <hardware>cooking pots</hardware> and pans by <hardware>size and
                        shape</hardware> so you can nest them and store them compactly, but you
                    might also arrange things by cuisine or style and separate your grilling
                    equipment from the wok and other items you use for making Chinese food.</para>
                <para xml:id="para-jyv_x3v_gv" revision="4.0" revisionflag="changed">Unlike those
            for physical resources, the most useful organizing properties for information resources
            are those <phrase>that reflect</phrase> their content and meaning, and these are not
            directly apparent when you look at a book, document, or collection of data. Significant
            intellectual effort or statistical computation is necessary to reveal these properties
            when assigning subject terms, creating an index, or using them as input features for
            machine learning and data analysis programs.</para>
        <?need 2.5cm ?>
                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-vpz_snr_lr">The most effective Organizing Systems
            for information resources often are based on statistical properties that emerge from
            analyzing the collection as a whole. For example, the relevance of documents to a search
            query is higher when they contain a higher than average frequency of the query terms
            compared to other documents in the collection, or when they are linked to relevant
            documents. Likewise, algorithms for classifying email messages continuously recalculate
            the probability that words like <quote>beneficiary</quote> or <quote>Viagra</quote>
            indicate whether a message is <quote>spam</quote> or <quote>not spam</quote> in the
            collection of messages processed. </para>
                
                
                
            </section>
    <!--              -->
    <?dbfo clear ?>
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-1.7" label="1.7">
                <title>The Concept of <quote>Agent</quote></title>
                <info>
                    <itermset>
                        <indexterm zone="section-1.7">
                            <primary>concept</primary>
                            <secondary>agent</secondary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </itermset>
        </info>
                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-cvz_snr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm significance="preferred" zone="def_agent">
                                <primary>agent</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="def_agent">
                                <primary>interactions</primary>
                                <secondary>agent</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>Many disciplines have specialized job titles to distinguish among the
                        <jobtitle>people who organize resources</jobtitle> (for example:
                        <jobtitle>cataloger</jobtitle>, <jobtitle>archivist</jobtitle>,
                        <jobtitle>indexer</jobtitle>, <jobtitle>curator</jobtitle>,
                        <jobtitle>collections manager</jobtitle>...).<footnote xml:id="endnote-011"
                        label="19" audience="LIS">
                        <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-ozz_snr_lr"><info>
                                <itermset>
                                    <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-011">
                                        <primary>endnote</primary>
                                        <secondary>LIS</secondary>
                                    </indexterm>
                                    <indexterm zone="endnote-011">
                                        <primary>library science</primary>
                                        <secondary>job titles</secondary>
                                    </indexterm>
                                </itermset>
                            </info>For precise distinctions, see the <orgname>US Department of
                                Labor, Bureau of Labor Statistics</orgname> occupational outlook
                            handbooks at <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                xlink:href="http://www.bls.gov/oco/ocos065.htm"
                                    ><uri>http://www.bls.gov/oco/ocos065.htm</uri></link> and <link
                                xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                xlink:href="http://www.bls.gov/oco/ocos068.htm"
                                    ><uri>http://www.bls.gov/oco/ocos068.htm</uri></link> and <link
                                xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                xlink:href="http://www.michellemach.com/jobtitles/realjobs.html"
                                    ><uri>http://www.michellemach.com/jobtitles/realjobs.html</uri></link>.</para>
                    </footnote><phrase role="definition" xml:id="def_agent"> We use the more general
                        word, <glossterm xml:id="term_agent">agent</glossterm>, for any entity
                        capable of autonomous and intentional organizing effort, because it treats
                        organizing work done by people and organizing work done by computers as
                        having common goals, despite obvious differences in methods.</phrase></para>
                <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-kd1_tnr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="para-kd1_tnr_lr">
                                <primary>costs</primary>
                                <secondary>accounting</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>We can analyze agents in Organizing Systems to understand how human and
                    computational efforts to arrange resources complement and substitute for each
                    other. We can determine the economic, social, and technological contexts in
                    which each type of agent can best be employed. We can determine how the
                    Organizing System allocates effort and costs among its creators, users,
                    maintainers and other stakeholders.</para>
                <para audience="CORE" role="comparative" xml:id="para-oh1_tnr_lr"><info><itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-oh1_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>agency</primary>
                    </indexterm></itermset>
        </info><phrase
                        role="statement">A group of people can be an organizing <glossterm
                            linkend="gloss_agent">agent</glossterm>, as when a group of people come
                        together in a service club or standards body technical committee in which
                        the members of the group subordinate their own individual agency to achieve
                        a collective good.</phrase></para>
                <para audience="CORE" role="comparative" xml:id="para-ml1_tnr_lr"><info><itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-ml1_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>computational</primary>
                        <secondary>processes</secondary>
                    </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>We also use the term <glossterm linkend="gloss_agent"
                        >agent</glossterm> when we discuss <phrase remap="action">interactions with
                        Organizing Systems</phrase>. The entities that most typically access the
                    contents of libraries, museums, or other collections of physical resources are
                        <jobtitle>human agents</jobtitle><symbol>&#8212;</symbol>that is, people. In
                    other Organizing Systems, such as business information systems or data
                    repositories, interactions with resources are carried out by computational
                    processes, robotic devices, or other entities that act autonomously on behalf of
                    a person or group.</para>
                <para audience="CORE" role="comparative" xml:id="para-hq1_tnr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm zone="para-hq1_tnr_lr">
                                <primary>RFID</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="para-hq1_tnr_lr">
                                <primary>location</primary>
                                <secondary>RFID</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="para-hq1_tnr_lr">
                                <primary>computational</primary>
                                <secondary>agents</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info><phrase role="statement">In some Organizing Systems, the resources
                        themselves are capable of initiating interactions with other resources or
                        with external agents.</phrase> This is most obvious with <hardware>human or
                        other living resources</hardware>, where a critical part of the design of
                    any Organizing System with them is determining what kinds of interactions they
                    should be encouraged or allowed to initiate. We will return to this issue after
                    we discuss the design of interactions with ordinary resources that are passive,
                    the situation in most Organizing Systems that involve physical resources.</para>
                    
                    
                      <para audience="CORE" role="comparative" xml:id="para-hq1_tnr_rjg">
               Other resources that can initiate interactions are <hardware>resources augmented with sensory,
                        computational or communication capabilities</hardware> that enable them to
                    obtain information from their environment and then do something useful with it.
                    You are probably familiar with <phrase remap="action"><hardware>RFID
                            tags</hardware></phrase>, which enable the precise identification and
                    location of physical resources as they move through supply chains and stores,
                    and with <quote>smart</quote> devices like Nest thermostats that learn how to
                    program themselves.</para> 
                
                
                    
                
            </section>
    <!--              -->
    <?dbfo clear ?>
    <?need 5cm ?>
    <section xml:id="section-1.8" label="1.8">
            <title>The Concept of <quote>Interactions</quote></title>
            <info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="section-1.8">
                        <primary>interactions</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="section-1.8">
                        <primary>concept</primary>
                        <secondary>interactions</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="section-1.8">
                        <primary>finding</primary>
                        <secondary>interaction</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="section-1.8">
                        <primary>identifying</primary>
                        <secondary>interaction</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="section-1.8">
                        <primary>selecting</primary>
                        <secondary>interaction</secondary>
                    </indexterm></itermset>
        </info>

            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-e51_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm significance="preferred" zone="def_interaction">
                        <primary>interactions</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info><phrase role="definition" xml:id="def_interaction">An <glossterm
                    xreflabel="interaction" xml:id="term_interaction">interaction</glossterm> is an
                    <phrase remap="action">action</phrase>, <phrase remap="action"
                >function</phrase>, <phrase remap="action">service</phrase>, or <phrase
                    remap="action">capability</phrase> that makes use of the resources in a
                collection or the collection as a whole. The interaction of <emphasis><phrase
                        remap="action">access</phrase></emphasis> is fundamental in any collection
                of resources, but many Organizing Systems provide additional <phrase remap="action"
                    >functions</phrase> to make <phrase remap="action">access</phrase> more
                efficient and to support <phrase remap="action">additional interactions</phrase>
                with the accessed resources.</phrase> For example, libraries and similar Organizing
            Systems implement catalogs to enable interactions for <emphasis><phrase remap="action"
                    >finding</phrase></emphasis> a known resource, <emphasis><phrase remap="action"
                    >identifying</phrase></emphasis> any resource in the collection, and
            discriminating or <emphasis><phrase remap="action">selecting</phrase></emphasis> among
            similar resources.<footnote xml:id="endnote-012" label="20" audience="LIS">
                <para audience="LIS" xml:id="para-dy1_tnr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-012">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>LIS</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-012">
                                <primary>IFLA</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-012">
                                <primary>library science</primary>
                                <secondary>IFLA</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-012" audience="LIS">
                                <primary>Cutter, Charles</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>The four objectives listed in this paragraph as those proposed in
                        <date>1997</date> by the <firstterm xml:id="first_IFLA"
                                    ><citerefentry><refentrytitle><orgname xml:id="ref_IFLA"
                                    >International Federation of Library Associations and
                                    Institutions</orgname></refentrytitle><manvolnum>IFLA</manvolnum></citerefentry></firstterm>.
                    The first statement of the objectives for a bibliographic system was made by
                        <citation xml:id="cite_Cutter1876" linkend="Cutter1876">(Cutter
                        1876)</citation>, which <citation xml:id="cite_Svenonius2000-1.2"
                        linkend="Svenonius2000">(Svenonius 2000)</citation> says it is likely the
                    most cited text in the bibliographic literature. Cutter called his three
                    objectives <quote>finding,</quote>
                    <quote>co-locating,</quote> and <quote>choice.</quote></para>
            </footnote></para>
            
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-nnb_tnr_lr"><phrase role="statement">Some of the
                    interactions with resources in an Organizing System are inherently determined by
                    the characteristics of the resource.</phrase> Because many museum resources are
                unique or extremely valuable, visitors are allowed to <phrase remap="action"
                    >view</phrase> them but cannot <phrase remap="action">borrow</phrase> them, in
                contrast with most of the resources in libraries. A library might have multiple
                printed copies of <citetitle linkend="Melville1851" pubwork="book">Moby
                    Dick</citetitle> but can never lend more of them than it possesses. After a
                printed book is checked out from the library, there are many types of interactions
                that might take place<symbol>&#8212;</symbol><phrase remap="action"
                >reading</phrase>, <phrase remap="action">translating</phrase>, <phrase
                    remap="action">summarizing</phrase>, <phrase remap="action">annotating</phrase>,
                and so on<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>but these are not directly supported by the library
                Organizing System and are invisible to it. </para>
                <para xml:id="para-fair_use"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-fair_use">
                        <primary>law</primary>
                        <secondary>fair use doctrine</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-fair_use">
                        <primary>fair use doctrine</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-fair_use">
                        <primary>copyright</primary>
                        <secondary>fair use doctrine</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>For works not in the public domain, copyright law gives the copyright holder the
            right to <phrase remap="action">prevent some uses</phrase>, but at the same time
                <quote>fair use</quote> and similar copyright doctrines enable certain limited uses
            even for copyrighted works.<footnote xml:id="endnote-013" label="21" audience="Law">
                <para audience="Law" xml:id="para-srb_tnr_lr"><info>
                        <itermset>
                            <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-013">
                                <primary>endnote</primary>
                                <secondary>Law</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-013">
                                <primary>law</primary>
                                <secondary>DRM</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-013">
                                <primary>business applications</primary>
                                <secondary>DRM</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-013">
                                <primary>copyright</primary>
                                <secondary>DRM</secondary>
                            </indexterm>
                            <indexterm zone="endnote-013">
                                <primary>DRM</primary>
                            </indexterm>
                        </itermset>
                    </info>Copyright law, license or contract agreements, terms of use and so on
                    that shape interactions with resources are part of the Organizing System, but
                    compliance with them might not be directly implemented as part of the system.
                    With digital resources, <application>digital rights management (<phrase
                            remap="abbrev">DRM</phrase>)</application>, passwords, and other
                    security mechanisms can be built into the Organizing System to enforce
                    compliance.</para>
            </footnote></para>
            <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-pvb_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-pvb_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>API</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-pvb_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>costs</primary>
                        <secondary>accounting</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info><phrase role="statement">Digital resources enable a greater range of interactions
                than physical ones.</phrase> Any number of people or processes can request a weather
            forecast from a web-based weather service because the forecast is not used up by the
            request and the marginal cost of allowing another access is nearly zero. Furthermore,
            with digital resources many new kinds of interactions can be enabled through application
            software, web services, or <firstterm
                xreflabel="application programming interfaces (API)" xml:id="first_API">application
                program interfaces (<abbrev xreflabel="API">API</abbrev>s)</firstterm> in the
            Organizing System. In particular, translation, summarization, annotation, and keyword
            suggestion are highly useful services that are commonly supported by web search engines
            and other web applications. Similarly, an Organizing System with digital resources can
            implement a <quote>keep everything up to date</quote> interaction that automatically
            pushes current content to your browser.</para>
            <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-izb_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-izb_tnr_lr" userlevel="Professional Graduate">
                        <primary>business applications</primary>
                        <secondary>resource management</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-izb_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>fair use doctrine</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm zone="para-izb_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>copyright</primary>
                        <secondary>fair use doctrine</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>But just as technology can enable interactions, it can prevent or constrain them.
            If your collection of digital resources (ebooks or music, for example) is not stored on
            your own computer or device, a continuous Internet connection is a requirement for
            access. In addition, access control policies and <firstterm xml:id="first_DRM"
                    ><application>digital rights management (<phrase remap="abbrev"
                    >DRM</phrase>)</application></firstterm> technology can limit the devices that
            can access the collection and prevent copying, annotation and other actions that might
            otherwise be enabled by the fair use doctrine. </para>
                        
            <para audience="CORE" revisionflag="added" revision="3.0">Interaction design is
                especially crucial for managing resources that have the capability to initiate
                interactions with each other or with external agents. Consider the vast differences
                in how workers behave in businesses organized according to principles of scientific
                management and those that embody the Kaizen principles of continuous improvement. In
                the former, work is highly standardized and bureaucratic, giving workers little
                autonomy. In the latter, work is also standardized, but workers are motivated to
                analyze and improve work processes whenever possible, and they are given great
                discretion in how to do that.<footnote xml:id="endnote-013a" label="22"
                    audience="Business" revision="3.0" revisionflag="added">
                    <para xml:id="para-qmx_rxx_ps" revision="3.0" revisionflag="added"
                        audience="Business"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm audience="Markup" zone="endnote-013a">
                                    <primary>endnote</primary>
                                    <secondary>Business</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-013a">
                                    <primary>business</primary>
                                    <secondary>scientific management</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                                <indexterm zone="endnote-013a">
                                    <primary>Kaizen</primary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info><personname><firstname>Frederick</firstname>
                            <surname>Taylor</surname></personname> developed <quote>scientific
                            management</quote> to improve industrial efficiency and conducted
                        detailed time and motion studies to devise what he thought were optimal ways
                        to perform work tasks <citation linkend="Taylor1914"
                            xml:id="cite_Taylor1914">(Taylor 1914)</citation>. The Kaizen principles
                        of continuous improvement were introduced to Western audiences by
                                <personname><firstname>Imai</firstname>
                            <surname>Masaaki</surname></personname> and by numerous books about
                        their application in the <orgname>Toyota</orgname> production system
                            <citation linkend="Masaaki1986" xml:id="cite_Masaaki1986">(Masaaki
                            1986)</citation>.</para>
                    <para audience="Business">Scientific management views a business as a machine,
                        while Kaizen principles treat it as a brain that learns. These metaphors for
                        business organization are among those described by <citation
                            linkend="GMorgan1997" xml:id="cite_GMorgan1997">(Morgan 1997)</citation>
                        in a classic business textbook. Other metaphors discussed include organisms,
                        cultures, political systems, and psychic prisons.</para>
                </footnote></para>

            <para audience="CORE" role="contrast" xml:id="para-jdc_tnr_lr">Just as with organizing
            principles, it is useful to think of interactions in an abstract or logical way that
            does not assume an implementation because it can encourage innovative designs for
            Organizing Systems.</para>
            
            
                         
        </section>
    
    <!--              -->
    <?dbfo clear ?>
    <?need 5cm ?>
    
        <section xml:id="section-1.9" label="1.9"
            revision="4.0" revisionflag="added">
            <title>The Concept of <quote>Interaction Resource</quote></title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-1.9">
                    <primary>interaction resource</primary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
            <para xml:id="para-hb4_s12_55" audience="CORE DS" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added"
            >Interactions with physical resources sometimes leave traces or other evidence. Many of
            these traces are unintentional, like fingerprints, a coffee cup stain on a newspaper, or
            the erosion on a shortcut path across a lawn. Fans of <citetitle>Sherlock
                Holmes</citetitle> and  <citetitle>CSI</citetitle> know that clever forensic
            investigators can use these residues of interactions to identify or vindicate suspects.
            Other interaction traces are intentional, like a student's yellow highlighting or notes
            in a textbook or spray-painted graffiti on a building. But not every interaction leaves
            a trace, traces fade over time, and different traces associated with the same resource
            lack consistency. This means that most traces are not of much use. </para>
            <para xml:id="para-b4h_cb2_55" audience="CORE DS" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added"
            >However, when Organizing Systems contain digital resources, or physical resources that
            have sensing, recording, or communication capabilities, interaction traces can be made
            predictable, persistent, and consistent. Each record of a user choice in accessing,
            browsing, buying, highlighting, linking, and other interactions then becomes an
                <quote>interaction resource</quote>  that can be analyzed to reorganize the resource
            collection or otherwise influence subsequent interactions with the primary resources. </para>
            <para xml:id="para-ht5_cb2_55" audience="CORE DS" revision="4.0" revisionflag="added"
            >Interaction resources are often essential pieces of information that make Organizing
            Systems function. Most human toll-takers have been replaced by smart <quote>toll
                tags</quote> that broadcast their identity when the car they are in passes a radio
            receiver at a tolling location. Each interaction resource created identifies an account
            and credit card with which to pay the toll; taken together, the collection of these
            interaction resources can be used as the primary resources in other Organizing Systems
            that manage traffic congestion, or that support road design. Similarly, interaction
            resources created by search engines can be used to adjust the order of search hits,
            select ads, or personalize the content of web pages.</para>
        </section>
        
        <!-- ###################### SECTION ########################################### -->
    <!--              -->
    <?dbfo clear ?>
    <?need 7cm ?>
    
    <!--              -->
    <section xml:id="section-1.10" label="1.10">
        <title>Organizing This Book</title>
        <info>
            <itermset>
                <indexterm zone="section-1.4">
                    <primary>organizing</primary>
                    <secondary>this book</secondary>
                </indexterm>
            </itermset>
        </info>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-gzw_tnr_lr">Devising concepts, methods, and technologies
            for describing and organizing resources have been essential human activities for
            millennia, evolving both in response to human needs and to enable new ones. Organizing
            Systems enabled the development of civilization, from agriculture and commerce to
            government and warfare. Today Organizing Systems are embedded in every domain of
            purposeful activity, including research, education, law, medicine, business, science,
            institutional memory, sociocultural memory, governance, public accountability, as well
            as in the ordinary acts of daily living.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-xcx_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-xcx_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>location</primary>
                        <secondary>tailored content delivery</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>With the World Wide Web and ubiquitous digital information, along with
            effectively unlimited processing, storage and communication capability, millions of
            people create and browse websites, blog, tag, tweet, and upload and download content of
            all media types without thinking <quote>I am organizing now</quote> or <quote>I am
                retrieving now.</quote> Writing a book used to mean a long period of isolated work
            by an author followed by the publishing of a completed artifact, but today some books
            are continuously and iteratively written and published through the online interactions
            of authors and readers. When people use their <hardware>smart phones</hardware> to
            search the web or run applications, location information transmitted from their phone is
            used to filter and reorganize the information they retrieve. Arranging results to make
            them fit the user’s location is a kind of computational curation, but because it takes
            place quickly and automatically we hardly notice it.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-ogx_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-ogx_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>location</primary>
                        <secondary>tailored content delivery</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>Likewise, almost every application that once seemed predominantly about
            information retrieval is now increasingly combined with activities and functions that
            most would consider to be information organization. <orgname>Google</orgname>,
                <orgname>Microsoft</orgname>, and other search engine operators have deployed
            millions of computers to analyze billions of web pages and millions of books and
            documents to enable the almost instantaneous retrieval of published or archival
            information. However, these firms increasingly augment this retrieval capability with
            information services that organize information in close to real-time. Further, the
            selection and presentation of search results, advertisements, and other information can
            be tailored for the person searching for information using his implicit or explicit
            preferences, location, or other <firstterm xml:id="first_contextual_properties"
                linkend="gloss_contextual_properties">contextual information</firstterm>.</para>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-dkx_tnr_lr"><info>
                <itermset>
                    <indexterm zone="para-dkx_tnr_lr">
                        <primary>tradeoffs</primary>
                        <secondary>organization versus retrieval</secondary>
                    </indexterm>
                </itermset>
            </info>Taken together, these innovations in technology and its application mean that the
            distinction between <glossterm>information organization</glossterm> and
                <glossterm>information retrieval</glossterm> that is often manifested in academic
            disciplines and curricula is much less important than it once was. </para>
        <?need 5cm ?>
        <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-rly_2s3_vw">This book has few sharp divisions between
                <glossterm>information organization</glossterm> (<abbrev>IO</abbrev>) and
                <glossterm>information retrieval</glossterm> (<abbrev>IR</abbrev>) topics. Instead,
            it explains the key concepts and challenges in the design and deployment of Organizing
            Systems in a way that continuously emphasizes the relationships and tradeoffs between
                <abbrev>IO</abbrev> and <abbrev>IR</abbrev>. The concept of the Organizing System
            highlights the design dimensions and decisions that collectively determine the extent
            and nature of resource organization and the capabilities of the processes that compare,
            combine, transform and interact with the organized resources.</para>
        
        <?need 6cm ?>
        
        <variablelist xml:id="sidebar-nav-ch1" role="editorial">
            <title>Navigating <citetitle>The Discipline of Organizing</citetitle></title>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><xref linkend="chapter-2n"/></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-wgw_ldx_qv">This chapter introduces six broad
                        design questions or dimensions whose intertwined answers define an
                        Organizing System: What, why, how much, when, how, and where. This framework
                        for describing and comparing Organizing Systems overcomes the biases and
                        conservatism built into familiar categories like libraries and museums while
                        enabling us to describe them as design patterns. We can then use these
                        patterns to support inter-disciplinary work that cuts across categories and
                        applies knowledge about familiar domains to unfamiliar ones.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><xref linkend="chapter-3"/></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-m5w_ldx_qv">Developing a view that brings
                        together how we organize as individuals with how libraries, museums,
                        governments, research institutions, and businesses create Organizing Systems
                        requires that we generalize the organizing concepts and methods from these
                        different domains. <xref linkend="chapter-3" xrefstyle="short"/> surveys a
                        wide variety of Organizing Systems and describes four activities or
                        functions shared by all of them: selecting resources, organizing resources,
                        designing resource-based interactions and services, and maintaining
                        resources over time.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><xref linkend="chapter-4"/></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-nrx_tnr_lr">The design of an Organizing
                        System is strongly shaped by what is being organized, the first of the six
                        design decisions we introduced earlier in <xref linkend="section-2n.2"/>. To
                        enable a broad perspective on this fundamental issue we use <glossterm
                            linkend="gloss_resource">resource</glossterm> to refer to anything being
                        organized, an abstraction that we can apply to physical things, digital
                        things, information about either of them, or web-based services or objects.
                            <xref linkend="chapter-4" xrefstyle="short"/> discusses the challenges
                        and methods for identifying the resources in an Organizing System in great
                        detail and emphasizes how these decisions reflect the goals and interactions
                        that must be supported<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>the <quote>why</quote> design
                        decisions introduced in <xref linkend="section-2n.3"/>.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <?need 6cm ?>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><xref linkend="chapter-5"/></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-evx_tnr_lr"><phrase
                            role="statement principle">The principles by which resources are
                            organized and the kinds of services and interactions that can be
                            supported for them largely depend on the nature and explicitness of the
                            resource descriptions.</phrase> This <quote role="interrogative">how
                            much description</quote> design question was introduced in <xref
                            linkend="section-2n.4"/>; <xref linkend="chapter-5" xrefstyle="short"/>
                        presents a systematic process for creating effective descriptions and
                        analyzes how this general approach can be adapted for different types of
                        Organizing Systems.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><xref linkend="chapter-6"/></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-uyx_tnr_lr">An important aspect of organizing
                        a collection of resources is describing the relationships between them.
                            <xref linkend="chapter-6" xrefstyle="short"/> introduces the specialized
                        vocabulary used to describe semantic relationships between resources and
                        between the concepts and words used in resource descriptions. It also
                        discusses the structural relationships within multipart resources and
                        between resources, like those expressed as citations or hypertext
                        links.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><xref linkend="chapter-7"/></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-mcy_tnr_lr">Groups or sets of resources with
                        similar or identical descriptions can be treated as equivalent, making them
                        members of an <emphasis>equivalence class</emphasis> or
                            <emphasis>category</emphasis>. Identifying and using categories are
                        essential human activities that take place automatically for perceptual
                        categories like <quote>red things</quote> or <quote>round things.</quote>
                        Categorization is deeply ingrained in language and culture, and we use
                        linguistic and cultural categories without realizing it, but categorization
                        can also be a deeply analytic and cognitive process. <xref
                            linkend="chapter-7" xrefstyle="short"/> reviews theories of
                        categorization from the point of view of how categories are created and used
                        in Organizing Systems.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><xref linkend="chapter-8"/></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-agy_tnr_lr">The terms
                            <emphasis>categorization</emphasis> and
                            <emphasis>classification</emphasis> are often used interchangeably but
                        they are not the same. <phrase role="definition">Classification is applied
                                categorization<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>the assignment of resources to
                            a system of categories, called classes, using a predetermined set of
                            principles.</phrase>
                        <xref linkend="chapter-8" xrefstyle="short"/> discusses the broad range of
                        how classifications are used in Organizing Systems. These include
                        enumerative classification, faceted classification, activity-based
                        classification, and computational classification. Because classification and
                        standardization are closely related, the chapter also analyzes standards and
                        standards-making as they apply to Organizing Systems.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <?need 6cm ?>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><xref linkend="chapter-9"/></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-tjy_tnr_lr"><xref linkend="chapter-9"
                            xrefstyle="short"/> complements the conceptual and methodological
                        perspective on the creation of resource descriptions with an implementation
                        perspective. <xref linkend="chapter-9" xrefstyle="short"/> reviews a range
                        of metamodels for structuring descriptions, with particular emphasis on
                            <abbrev>XML</abbrev>, <abbrev>JSON</abbrev>, and <abbrev>RDF</abbrev>.
                        It concludes by comparing and contrasting three <quote>worlds of
                            description</quote>
                        <symbol>&#8212;</symbol>document processing, the web, and the <glossterm
                            linkend="gloss_semantic_web">Semantic
                            Web</glossterm><symbol>&#8212;</symbol>where each of these three
                        metamodels is most appropriate.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <?need 6cm ?>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><xref linkend="chapter-10"/></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-kny_tnr_lr">When Organizing Systems overlap,
                        intersect, or are combined (temporarily or permanently), differences in
                        resource descriptions can make it difficult or impossible to locate
                        resources, access them, or otherwise impair their use. <xref
                            linkend="chapter-10" xrefstyle="short"/> reviews some of the great
                        variety of concepts and techniques that different domains use when
                        interacting with resources in Organizing
                        Systems<symbol>&#8212;</symbol>integration, interoperability, data mapping,
                        crosswalks, mash-ups, and so on. Interactions are characterized by the
                        layers of resource properties they use: instance, collection-based, derived,
                        or properties combined from different resources. <xref linkend="chapter-10"
                            xrefstyle="short"/> extends the idea of an information
                        organization—information retrieval continuum, and describes information
                        retrieval interactions (and others) in terms of information organization
                        (i.e., resource description) requirements. </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <?need 2.5cm ?>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><xref linkend="chapter-11"/></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-bry_tnr_lr"><info>
                            <itermset>
                                <indexterm zone="para-bry_tnr_lr">
                                    <primary>tradeoffs</primary>
                                    <secondary>descriptive versus prescriptive</secondary>
                                </indexterm>
                            </itermset>
                        </info><xref linkend="chapter-11" xrefstyle="short"/> complements the
                        descriptive perspective of chapters 2-10 with a more prescriptive one that
                        analyzes the design choices and tradeoffs that must be made in different
                        phases in an Organizing System’s life cycle. System life cycle models
                        exhibit great variety, but we use a generic four-phase model that
                        distinguishes a domain identification and scoping phase, a requirements
                        phase, a design and implementation phase, and an operational phase. </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><xref linkend="chapter-12"/></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para audience="CORE" xml:id="para-q5y_tnr_lr">In <xref linkend="chapter-12"
                            xrefstyle="short"/> we use the model described in <xref
                            linkend="chapter-11" xrefstyle="short"/> to guide the analysis of
                        studies that span the range of Organizing Systems, and make reference to the
                        principles, guidelines, vocabulary, and models discussed in the preceding
                        chapters.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry audience="Markup">
                <term><xref linkend="PRODNOTES"/></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para xml:id="para-gyy_tnr_lr">In <xref linkend="PRODNOTES"/> we discuss the
                        organization of this book, as a book.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <?need 3.5cm ?>
    </section>
</chapter>
